<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A late printed sermon against false prophets, vindicated by letter, from the causeless aspersions of Mr. Francis Cheynell. / By Jasper Mayne, D.D. the mis-understood author of it.</title>
            <author>Mayne, Jasper, 1604-1672.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 190 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89004</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1471</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E392_15</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201569</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862068</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862068</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114217</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89004)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114217)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 62:E392[15])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A late printed sermon against false prophets, vindicated by letter, from the causeless aspersions of Mr. Francis Cheynell. / By Jasper Mayne, D.D. the mis-understood author of it.</title>
                  <author>Mayne, Jasper, 1604-1672.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 60, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare, M DC XLVII. [1647]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>The roman numeral date in imprint is made with turned C's.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June 14th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cheynell, Francis, 1608-1665 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Mayne, Jasper, 1604-1672. --  Sermon against false prophets.</term>
               <term>Religious disputations --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114217:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A late Printed SERMON AGAINST Falſe Prophets, Vindicated by LETTER, From the cauſeleſs Aſperſions of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. FRANCIS CHEYNELL.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Jaſper Mayne, D.D.</hi> the miſ-under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood Author of it.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>LUKE 21.19.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Yeare, MDCXLVII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:114217:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:114217:2"/>
            <head>A late printed SERMON againſt FALSE PROPHETS, Vindicated by Letter, from the cauſeleſſe Aſperſions of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. FRANCIS CHEYNELL.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S often as I have, for ſome yeares, conſidered the <hi>ſad Distractions</hi> of this <hi>Kingdome,</hi> me-thinkes, thus <hi>divided</hi> againſt it <hi>ſelfe,</hi> it hath verified upon it ſelfe the <hi>Fable</hi> of the <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> ſowne of <hi>Serpents Teeth;</hi> where, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any knowne <hi>Cauſe</hi> of a <hi>Quarrell, Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> ſtarted up ſuddenly armed againſt <hi>Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> and making the place of their <hi>Nativity</hi> the <hi>Field,</hi> and <hi>Scene</hi> of their <hi>Conflicts,</hi> every one fell by the <hi>Speare</hi> of the next, upon the <hi>turfe,</hi> and <hi>furrow</hi> which hatcht and brought him forth. 'Tis true, indeed, ſome have <hi>preacht,</hi> and others have <hi>printed,</hi> that the <hi>Superſtitions</hi> of our <hi>Church</hi> were growne ſo high, that they could not poſſibly be purged but by a <hi>Civill Warre.</hi> But finding, upon my moſt ſober and impartiall Inquiries, that theſe <hi>Superſtitions</hi> were onely the <hi>miſconceipts</hi> of ſome mens <hi>ſicke Fancies,</hi> who called certaine <hi>ſleight harmleſſe pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Church Ceremony Superſtition,</hi> I thought it a peece of <hi>Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> to them and the deluded <hi>people,</hi> to let them no longer remaine in the Caſe of the <hi>diſtracted Midi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ites</hi> in the Booke of<note n="*" place="margin">c. 7. v.</note> 
               <hi>Iudges;</hi> where, upon a Dreame told by a <hi>man</hi> to his <hi>Neighbour,</hi> and upon the ſight of ſuch inconſiderable things as <hi>lamps,</hi> and <hi>broken
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:114217:3"/>pitchers,</hi> every <hi>mans ſword was againſt his fellow;</hi> and a well-or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd <hi>Hoſt</hi> of <hi>freinds,</hi> ſtruck with an imaginary feare, became a confuſed and diſorder'd <hi>heape,</hi> and <hi>rout of enemies.</hi> This deſire to rectifie <hi>miſtakes,</hi> and withall to ſhew upon what ſlender threds of <hi>vanity</hi> their <hi>Sermons</hi> hang, whoſe <hi>accidentall, miſguided Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> under certaine <hi>falſe colours,</hi> have ſtrived to prove <hi>things indifferent</hi> to be <hi>unlawfull;</hi> and then, that thus by them pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced <hi>unlawfull,</hi> they are to be <hi>extirpated</hi> by the <hi>Sword,</hi> cauſed me at firſt to preach a <hi>Sermon</hi> againſt <hi>Falſe Prophets,</hi> which hath ſince paſt the <hi>Travell</hi> of a more <hi>publique Birth:</hi> wherein, what a cold Advocate I am in my pleadings for <hi>Superſtition,</hi> will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to any, who with an unclouded underſtanding ſhall read it: yet <hi>M. Cheynell,</hi> (one of the <hi>Preachers</hi> ſent downe by the <hi>Parliament</hi> to <hi>Oxford</hi>) in a <hi>morning Sermon</hi> of his preacht at <hi>S. Maries</hi> Jan. 17. upon <hi>Eſay.</hi> 40.27. Having directed the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinall</hi> part of it againſt one <hi>M. Yerbury,</hi> an <hi>Independent,</hi> (who publikely in a Diſpute with him held, that the <hi>Fulneſs of the Godhead dwells in the Saints bodily, in the ſame meaſure that it did in Chriſt</hi>) not without much <hi>violence</hi> offer'd to his <hi>Text,</hi> He di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected the <hi>vſe</hi> and <hi>Application</hi> of it to <hi>me;</hi> whom (after ſome <hi>characteriſticall</hi> reproaches of my <hi>perſon,</hi> and defamations of my <hi>Sermon</hi>) He challenged to a publike <hi>Diſputation</hi> with him. This (after two dayes) coming to my knowledge, I diſputed with my ſelfe what I was to doe in ſuch a caſe: To returne <hi>reproaches</hi> for <hi>reproaches,</hi> or to vindicate my ſelfe in the place where I was thus publikely reviled, had bin to make my ſelfe <hi>Second</hi> in a fault, which the whole <hi>Congregation</hi> condemned in him as the <hi>Firſt.</hi> Beſides if I could have diſpens'd with my ſelfe for being ſo unchriſtianly revengefull, as to remove part of the <hi>Civill Warre,</hi> which hath too long imbrued our <hi>Fields,</hi> into the <hi>Temple,</hi> and there to anſwer <hi>Challenges,</hi> and fight <hi>Duells</hi> from the <hi>pulpit,</hi> this licence was denyed me; who have for divers monthes beene compelled to be a <hi>ſpeechleſs member</hi> of this ſilenced <hi>Vniverſity.</hi> Againe, To ſleepe over my <hi>infamy,</hi> and to diſſemble my <hi>diſgrace,</hi> had beene to beget an <hi>opinion</hi> in the <hi>mindes</hi> of thoſe that heard him, that either <hi>I</hi> wanted a <hi>good cauſe,</hi> or elſe my <hi>good cauſe</hi> wants a <hi>Defender.</hi> At length (ſomething contrary I confeſs, to the <hi>peaceableneſs</hi> of my <hi>ſtudies,</hi> which never delighted much in
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:114217:3"/>thoſe <hi>quarrelſome</hi> parts of Learning, which raiſe <hi>tempeſts</hi> between men) following the <hi>Scripture</hi> counſell, which is, to take my <hi>offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Brother aſide in private,</hi> and <hi>to tell him of his fault,</hi> I reſolved by the <hi>ſecreſie</hi> of writing to wipe off thoſe <hi>Calumnies</hi> for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and to anſwer the bold <hi>Challenge</hi> for the preſent, which <hi>hee</hi> hurl'd at me in the <hi>Pulpit;</hi> and having firſt baniſh'd all <hi>gall,</hi> and <hi>Bitterneſſe</hi> from my <hi>pen,</hi> ſent him this following <hi>Letter.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THat a <hi>Text</hi> of <hi>Scripture</hi> in your handling ſhould weare two <hi>faces,</hi> and the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of it ſhould bee made to looke one way, and the <hi>uſe</hi> of it another, is at all no wonder to me. But that pretending ſo much to <hi>Holineſs,</hi> and <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> as you doe, you ſhould thinke the <hi>Pulpit</hi> a fit place to revile me in, would hardly enter into my beleif, were not the <hi>Congregation</hi> that heard you on <hi>Sunday morning</hi> laſt at <hi>S. Maryes,</hi> my <hi>cloud of Witneſſes.</hi> From ſome of which I am informed, that you ſolemnly charged me with <hi>imprudence</hi> and <hi>impudence,</hi> for publiſhing a late <hi>Sermon againſt falſe Prophets.</hi> SIR, Though <hi>report,</hi> and my <hi>name</hi> perfixt in the <hi>Title-Page</hi> might probably perſwade you, that I am the <hi>Author</hi> of it; yet to aſſure you, that I cauſed it to be publiſh'd, or conſented to the <hi>printing</hi> of <hi>it,</hi> will certainly require a more <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible illumination,</hi> then, I preſume, you have. Beſides, if I ſhould grant you that 'twas <hi>printed</hi> with my conſent, (which yet I ſhall not) yet certainely the <hi>ſeaſonableneſs</hi> of it in a <hi>time</hi> where <hi>god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs</hi> is made the <hi>engine</hi> to arrive to ſo much <hi>unlawfull gaine,</hi> will excuſe me from <hi>imprudence,</hi> though perhaps not from an <hi>unthri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving,</hi> in your ſenſe, <hi>wart</hi> of <hi>policy.</hi> And as for the <hi>impudence</hi> you charged me withall, I am confident that all they who heard <hi>you</hi> with impartiall <hi>Eares,</hi> and have read that <hi>Sermon</hi> with impartiall <hi>Eyes,</hi> have, by this time, aſſigned that want of <hi>modeſty</hi> a place in a more capable <hi>forehead.</hi> I heare farther that having in a kinde of <hi>pleaſant diſdaine</hi> ſhuffled <hi>pipes, Surplices, pictures in Church-win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, Liturgy, and Prelacy</hi> together in one period, and ſtiled them the <hi>muſty Relickes</hi> of an at-length-baniſht <hi>Superſtition,</hi> you were pleaſed out of that <hi>heape</hi> to ſelect <hi>Images,</hi> and to call them <hi>Idolls,</hi> and then to charge me as a <hi>defender</hi> of them.</p>
                  <p>SIR, Had you done me but the ordinary Juſtice to pluck my
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:114217:4"/>
                     <hi>Sermon</hi> out of your <hi>pocket,</hi> as you did the <hi>Practicall Catechiſme,</hi> and had faithfully read to your <hi>Auditory</hi> what I have there ſaid of <hi>Images,</hi> I make no queſtion, but they would all have preſently diſcerned that I defend not <hi>Pictures</hi> in <hi>Church windowes</hi> as they are <hi>Idolls,</hi> or have at any time beene made ſo, but that 'tis un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable to baniſh them out of the <hi>Church</hi> as long as they ſtand there meerly as <hi>Ornaments</hi> of the <hi>place.</hi> From which innocent uſe having not hitherto digreſt, for you to call them <hi>Idols,</hi> and then to charge me as if I had made them <hi>equall with God,</hi> by my defence of them ſo <hi>formallized,</hi> will I feare, endanger you in the <hi>mindes</hi> of youre <hi>Hearers,</hi> and beget an <hi>Opinion</hi> in them, that you are one of the <hi>Prophets</hi> who uſe to <hi>ſee Vanity.</hi> I heare farther, that when you had traduced me as a <hi>Defender</hi> of the fore-mentioned <hi>muſty Relicts of Superſtition,</hi> you ſaid, that <hi>this was the Religion to which I profeſt my ſelfe ready to fall a ſacrifice.</hi> Certainely, <hi>Sir,</hi> This is not faire dealing. For if, once more, you had pluckt my <hi>Sermon</hi> out of your <hi>pocket,</hi> and had read to the <hi>Congregation</hi> that paſſage of it which endeavours to prove that 'tis not lawfull to <hi>propagate Religion,</hi> (how pure ſoever it be) by the <hi>ſword,</hi> they would have heard from <hi>your mouth,</hi> as they once did from <hi>mine,</hi> that the <hi>Religion</hi> to which I there profeſſe my ſelf ready to fall a <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice,</hi> is that <hi>defamed, true, Proteſtant Religion,</hi> for which the <hi>holy Fathers</hi> of our <hi>Reformation</hi> died before me. In ſaying, therefore, that I profeſſe my ſelfe ready to fall a <hi>ſacrifice</hi> in the defence of <hi>Surplices,</hi> the <hi>Common Prayer Booke,</hi> or <hi>Church Ornaments,</hi> (things which I have alwayes held not <hi>neceſſary,</hi> unleſſe made ſo, by <hi>right Authority</hi>) you have incurred one danger more, which is, not only to be thought to <hi>ſee Vanity,</hi> but to be guilty of the <hi>next part of the Text.</hi> I am farther told, that to deliver your ſelfe from the number of the <hi>falſe Prophets</hi> there preacht againſt, you <hi>prophecyed</hi> in the <hi>Pulpit;</hi> and choſe for the <hi>ſubject</hi> of your <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction,</hi> a thing which is poſſible enough for you to bring to paſſe; which was, that you <hi>will have my Sermon burnt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sir I have, for your ſake, once more ſeverely conſider'd it. And can neither finde <hi>Socinianiſme,</hi> or any other <hi>Poland Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> there which ſhould deſerve that <hi>doome.</hi> But if it muſt die like <hi>Biſhop Ridley</hi> or <hi>Hooper,</hi> for its <hi>adhaeſion</hi> to the <hi>beſt Religion</hi> that this Kingdome ever enjoyed, I muſt repeat the <hi>words</hi> of my
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:114217:4"/>
                     <hi>Sermon,</hi> and tell you, that (without the fear of being thought by you a <hi>Pſeudo-Martyr</hi>) I ſhall account it one of the <hi>happieſt paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages</hi> to <hi>Heaven,</hi> to be diſſolved to <hi>aſhes</hi> with it in the ſame <hi>fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall-pile.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Laſtly, <hi>Sir,</hi> having, with all the <hi>ſober detraction,</hi> which might probably beget a diſlike in the <hi>mindes</hi> of your <hi>Hearers,</hi> of me and my <hi>Sermon,</hi> ſufficiently <hi>defamed both,</hi> I heare you did beat up a <hi>Drumme</hi> againſt me in the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> and challenged me to a <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like diſpute</hi> with you. If by a <hi>diſpute</hi> you meant a <hi>pen-combate,</hi> I ſhall be as ready to enter the liſts with you, as you have beene to ſummon me to it, if you will grant me two things. The one is, that, if we engage our ſelves in a <hi>Conference</hi> of that nature, you will confine your ſelfe to the <hi>particulars</hi> in my <hi>Sermon</hi> which you <hi>quarrell'd</hi> at; and not uſe your <hi>ſtrange, wilde Art</hi> of multiplying <hi>Queſtions</hi> upon <hi>Queſtions;</hi> or like another <hi>Hydra,</hi> what ever the <hi>Hercules</hi> be, make <hi>three heads</hi> ſpring up in the place where you finde <hi>one convincingly</hi> lopt of. The other is, that, when you have made your <hi>Charge,</hi> and I my <hi>Reſiſtance,</hi> you will conſent that the <hi>debate</hi> of every <hi>queſtion,</hi> thus <hi>diſputed,</hi> may bee made publike and <hi>printed.</hi> But if by a <hi>Diſpute,</hi> you meant that I ſhould fight a <hi>Duell</hi> with you upon the ſame <hi>ſtage,</hi> and in the ſame <hi>Theater</hi> of <hi>men</hi> and <hi>women,</hi> before whom you, and <hi>Mr. Yerbury</hi> played your <hi>prize,</hi> I doubt very much, if I ſhould accept of your <hi>Callenge</hi> in that <hi>ſenſe;</hi> whether all diſcreet men would not count this a ſpice of the <hi>phrenzy</hi> in me, which you complained of in the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> for being imputed to you by <hi>Him</hi> that wrote the <hi>Conference</hi> at your late <hi>Scruple-Houſe;</hi> and ſay I deſerved to be cured by the <hi>Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline,</hi> and <hi>Phyſicke</hi> of a <hi>darke roome.</hi> To deale freely with you, Sir, I by no meanes can approve of an <hi>Engliſh Diſputation</hi> in a <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity.</hi> But becauſe you ſhall not looſe your <hi>challenge,</hi> nor I be thought to deſert the <hi>cauſe,</hi> which I profeſſe to defend, ſo you will chooſe the <hi>Divinity Schoole,</hi> and <hi>Latine weapons,</hi> I ſhall not refuſe (as well as God ſhall enable me) to give you a meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there, and to ſuſtaine the <hi>Anſwerers</hi> part in the <hi>defence</hi> of the <hi>lawfulneſſe</hi> of <hi>white Surplices, Church Ornaments;</hi> the <hi>Common Prayer Booke,</hi> and <hi>Prelacy;</hi> which are the <hi>particulars</hi> in my <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> which you called <hi>Relicts of Superſtition.</hi> To one of theſe two offers I ſhall patiently expect your <hi>anſwer;</hi> unleſſe without
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:114217:5"/>troubling me any further, you will let me quietly retire backe againe into the <hi>ſhade,</hi> from whence you have too importunately called me: Who, neuer the leſs, have learnt ſo much <hi>Charity,</hi> as to pray <hi>God</hi> to forgive you the <hi>wrong</hi> which you intended to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>From my chamber</hi>
                        <date>
                           <hi>this evening. Jan.</hi> 19. 1646.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>The <hi>Author</hi> of the <hi>Sermon</hi> againſt <hi>Falſe Prophets. J. MAYNE.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>To this <hi>letter</hi> (in which (as briefly as the <hi>lawes</hi> of a <hi>Letter</hi> would permit) I indeavour'd to waſh out the <hi>ſpots,</hi> with which <hi>M. Cheynell</hi> in his <hi>Sermon</hi> ſtrived to <hi>defile</hi> and <hi>ſully mine,</hi> and withall to comply with him in any ſober way of <hi>Diſpute,</hi> which might befit two <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity-men</hi>) after two dayes was returned an <hi>Anſwer:</hi> Firſt, <hi>ſtrange</hi> for the <hi>meſſenger's</hi> ſake that brought it, which was <hi>One Jellyman</hi> (ſome ſay) a <hi>preaching Cobler;</hi> who from repairing the <hi>decayes</hi> of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity-mens ſhooes</hi> was now thought fit to have a part in the conveyance of their <hi>diſputes.</hi> Next, for the <hi>double Super ſcription</hi> of it, which without, on the ſide of the firſt paper that encloſed it, was as faire and full of Candor as the <hi>whited ſepulcher</hi> in the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> and was directed, To D. MAYNE AT CHRIST-CHURCH. But this outward ſtone was no ſooner rolled away, but another <hi>Inſcription,</hi> very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like the firſt appear'd, which ran thus. FOR M. JASPER MAYNE (ONE OF THE NEVV DOCTORS) STUDENT AT CHRIST-CHURCH. By which <hi>parentheſis,</hi> it ſeemes <hi>M. Cheynell,</hi> thought it an <hi>errour</hi> in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity,</hi> to make me a <hi>Doctor.</hi> And truely (if I may be believed upon my owne report) as often as I compare my <hi>unworthineſs</hi> with my <hi>degree,</hi> I am of <hi>his opinion;</hi> and thinke I am a <hi>Doctor,</hi> fit only to ſtand in a <hi>paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis;</hi> and, without any iniuſtice done me, to be left out of the <hi>ſentence.</hi> This ſecond <hi>Superſcription</hi> was underwritten with a kind of a <hi>preamble Letter</hi> to the more <hi>inward Letter;</hi> with the <hi>lock</hi> and <hi>guard</hi> of a <hi>ſeale</hi> upon it; and ran thus.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I have ſent ſeverall times to your lodging <hi>this day</hi> to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer your challenge <hi>yeſterday;</hi> if you cannot meet to <hi>morrow,</hi> let me underſtand your minde to <hi>night.</hi> For I have a great deale of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:114217:5"/>buſineſs, ſince the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity</hi> was <hi>ſilenced</hi> for your ſake.</p>
                  <p>What kinde of <hi>meeting</hi> was here meant, or whether I (having I thanke God, the <hi>uſe</hi> of my <hi>underſtanding</hi>) could conſent to it, will appeare by the <hi>Letter</hi> it <hi>ſelfe;</hi> which (being an <hi>Anſwer</hi> to <hi>mine</hi>) was <hi>verbatim</hi> this.</p>
                  <p>SIR, I uſe to ſpend my <hi>morning thoughts</hi> upon a better <hi>ſubiect</hi> then a <hi>pot</hi> of dead drinke, that hath a litle <hi>froth</hi> at <hi>top,</hi> and <hi>dreggs</hi> at <hi>bottom;</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>SIR, It appeares by your <hi>Letter,</hi> that you doe not underſtand my <hi>Text,</hi> and the <hi>learned Scribe,</hi> or <hi>Intelligencer,</hi> did not vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand my <hi>plaine,</hi> very <hi>plaine Engliſh Sermon.</hi> I am not at leiſure to repeat every <hi>Sermon</hi> that I <hi>preach,</hi> (preaching ſoe often as I doe ſometimes <hi>twice,</hi> and upon juſt occaſion <hi>thrice</hi> a day) to every one that is at leiſure to cavill at that which thay heard but at ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond hand; yet to ſhew how much you are miſtaken, I will give you a breife, but ſatisfactorie account.</p>
                  <p>My <hi>Text</hi> ſtands upon record, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.25. the <hi>Doctrine</hi> I raiſed from the words, was as followeth.</p>
                  <p>Doct. <hi>There is no creature in heaven, or earth, like God in all things, or equall to God in any thing.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The firſt <hi>Corollarie</hi> I deduced from <hi>thence,</hi> when I came to make <hi>application,</hi> was breifly <hi>this.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That <hi>no picture can be made of God, becauſe there was nothing like him in heaven or earth.</hi> All <hi>nations</hi> are leſs then <hi>vanity</hi> in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of <hi>God;</hi> to whom then will ye liken <hi>God,</hi> or what <hi>like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> will ye compare unto him? <hi>Iſay.</hi> 40.17.18. The Prophet urgeth this <hi>Argument,</hi> againſt all manner of <hi>images</hi> which are made to repreſent <hi>God,</hi> who ſitteth upon the <hi>circle</hi> of the <hi>earth,</hi> and ſtretcheth out the <hi>heavens</hi> from the 19. <hi>v. of the ſame chap: to the</hi> 23. <hi>ver.</hi> and he enforceth this Argument <hi>verſ.</hi> 21. <hi>have yee not knowne—have ye not underſtood?</hi> &amp;c. as if he had ſay'd, yee are <hi>ignorant ſotts, irrationall,</hi> and <hi>inconſiderate men,</hi> if yee apprehend not the <hi>ſtrength</hi> of <hi>this Argument.</hi> Now, <hi>SIR,</hi> be pleaſed to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce your <hi>ſtrong reaſons,</hi> and overthrow, if you can, the <hi>Doctrine</hi> or the <hi>Corollary:</hi> Your, <hi>Intelligencer</hi> was (if not a <hi>falſe Prophet</hi> yet) a <hi>falſe Hiſtorian,</hi> when he told you that I accuſed you of making <hi>images equall with God.</hi> SIR, I ſaid, that <hi>images were not like unto God;</hi> and <hi>thereupon</hi> wondered that you tooke upon you to pleade for the retaining of thoſe <hi>images</hi> which have beene too
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:114217:6"/>often turn'd into <hi>idolls,</hi> not by the <hi>piety,</hi> but <hi>ſuperſtition</hi> of <hi>forme times.</hi> You ſay, that by the ſame reaſon there ſhould be no <hi>Sun</hi> in the <hi>firmament.</hi> Whence I collect, that you will be forc'd to maintaine, that <hi>images</hi> are as <hi>neceſsary</hi> in the <hi>Church,</hi> as the <hi>Sun</hi> in <hi>heaven;</hi> be pleaſed to read the 22. page of the <hi>falſe Prophet.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Moreover, you plead for <hi>Copes,</hi> and for thoſe <hi>parts</hi> of the <hi>Common-Prayer Booke</hi> which were borrowed from <hi>Rome pag.</hi> 21, 22. The <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iſitors</hi> will ere long enquire, whether there hath not beene a <hi>Superſtitious uſe</hi> of <hi>Copes</hi> at <hi>Chriſt-Church?</hi> and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I did not make any ſuch enquirie in my <hi>Sermon,</hi> but as a <hi>Freind</hi> I give <hi>you</hi> and <hi>your adherents</hi> timely notice of it, becauſe I believe you had need <hi>ſtudy</hi> for an <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>You maintaine, that <hi>ſome things in the excellencies and height of the Doctrines of Chriſtian Religion depend for their credit and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of their truth upon the authority of Chriſts miracles con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed along in tradition and ſtory, pag.</hi> 16. and <hi>therefore</hi> I ſay your <hi>Religion</hi> leanes too <hi>hard</hi> and too <hi>heavy</hi> upon <hi>Tradition.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>You are offended that I ſpoke not diſtinctly concerning <hi>Prela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> you may (if you pleaſe) try your <hi>ſtrength,</hi> and endeavour to <hi>prove</hi> that <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath put the <hi>ſole power</hi> of <hi>Ordination</hi> and <hi>Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction</hi> in the hand of a <hi>Prelate.</hi> 2. You may (if you can) <hi>juſtifie,</hi> that <hi>no Church that ever the Sun look'd upon hath been more bleſt with purity of Religion for the Doctrine of it, or better eſtabliſh'd for the Government and Diſcipline of it, then the Church of England, pag.</hi> 17. if you believe this confident aſſertion, you may proceed and <hi>juſtifie</hi> all the <hi>Doctrines,</hi> which were <hi>publikely countenanced,</hi> or <hi>approved;</hi> all the <hi>ſuperſtitious practiſes,</hi> and <hi>prelaticall uſurpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> nay, the <hi>delegation</hi> of the <hi>Prelates, uſurped power</hi> to <hi>Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors</hi> and all the Tyranny of the <hi>high Commiſſion,</hi> together with all the corruptions and innovations introduced into the <hi>State, Church, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity</hi> from the yeare 1630. till 1640. by a <hi>prevailing faction,</hi> who were not the <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity,</hi> but the <hi>diſeaſe,</hi> indeed the <hi>plague</hi> of both. If you dare not undertake ſo ſad a taske, you cannot juſtifie the 17.18.22, 23.27.35. <hi>pages</hi> of the <hi>Falſe Prophet;</hi> you muſt prove that the proceedings of the <hi>Parliament are Turkiſh, pag.</hi> 15.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. that none of the <hi>Members</hi> of either <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Parli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ent</hi> (who complaine of the blemiſhes of the <hi>Church</hi>) are t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="6 letters">
                        <desc>••••••</desc>
                     </gap>med good <hi>Proteſtants, pag.</hi> 18. that the <hi>Reformation</hi> which they have made is <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> vanities, pag.</hi> 20. that they are
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:114217:6"/>guided by no other <hi>principles</hi> but ſuch as are contrary to all rules of right <hi>judgement,</hi> either common to men or Chriſtians, <hi>pag.</hi> 21. that the <hi>Miniſters</hi> who have appeared for the <hi>Parliament,</hi> are all of them <hi>Falſe Prophets,</hi> who have encouraged the <hi>Parliament</hi> to <hi>oppreſſion, ſacriledge, murther,</hi> and to make all names that are great and ſacred, cheap and odious in the eares of the <hi>people.</hi> That the <hi>Miniſters</hi> are the <hi>liars,</hi> and the <hi>Parliament-men</hi> the <hi>compliers,</hi> as appears by all your unworthy <hi>inſinuations, hints, intimations,</hi> quite throughout your <hi>Scurrillous Libell,</hi> falſly called a <hi>Sermon:</hi> let any prudent man judge whether this be not your maine drift and ſcope, <hi>à carceribus uſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ad metam.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>You talke of a <hi>Religion,</hi> in which you were borne, were you borne in a <hi>Surplice</hi> or a <hi>Cope? Chriſtiani non naſcunt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r ſed fiunt.</hi> Sir, the <hi>Parliament</hi> doth not defame nor will they ſuppreſs the true <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> and therefore if you fall in this <hi>quarrell,</hi> I ſaid, that you muſt be ſacrificed in the defence of <hi>Tyranny, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacy, Popery:</hi> if you put not <hi>Religion</hi> in <hi>Copes, Images, Prelates,</hi> or <hi>Service-Booke, quorſum haec perdito?</hi> why doe you talk of being Martyr'd? ſay, that (if the King will give you leave) you will burne your <hi>Copes</hi> and <hi>Surplices,</hi> throw off the <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Prayer Booke,</hi> you'l break your windowes, and take the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,</hi> and make it evident that you are and ever will be of the <hi>Kings Religion;</hi> for you hold none of theſe things neceſſary now, (whatever you have ſaid heretofore) <hi>unleſs they be made ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary by right Authority.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sir, if I made any prediction, it was that your <hi>Sermon</hi> would be confuted, before it was burnt; you know <hi>Paraeus</hi> was burnt before he was confuted; and if you be not guilty of any <hi>doctrine</hi> received in <hi>Poland,</hi> I wonder, Firſt, why you did endeavour to incenſe an Officer of this <hi>Garriſon</hi> againſt me, becauſe I had refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted M. <hi>Yerburies blaſphemous errors.</hi> 2. Why you did maintaine thoſe <hi>damnable Doctrines</hi> on the laſt <hi>Sabbath:</hi> forgive me this injurie, for I heare you did but vent them, and were no way able to maintain them.</p>
                  <p>Sir, I acknowledge that I doe contend for the reſtitution of the true <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> and contend for the <hi>civill right</hi> which we have to exerciſe the true <hi>Proteſtant Religion:</hi> we were in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt danger to loſe our right, by the force and violence of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent <hi>Enemies,</hi> whereupon the high Court of <hi>Parliament</hi> judged
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:114217:7"/>it fit to repell <hi>force</hi> by <hi>forces:</hi> be pleaſed to ſhew how the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> doth hereby <hi>canonize</hi> the <hi>Alchoran,</hi> or declare them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be of the <hi>Mahumetan perſwaſion;</hi> the <hi>Parliament</hi> will not compell you to be happy, onely take heed that you do not compell them to make you miſerable. Though you renounce all <hi>Doctrines</hi> that M. <hi>Yerberie</hi> maintaines, yet I thinke you are too great a <hi>friend</hi> to the <hi>Rebels</hi> in <hi>Ireland;</hi> you contend for a <hi>Vorſtian liberty,</hi> not for a <hi>liberty</hi> of conſcience, for you deſire a <hi>liberty for</hi> men that have no conſcience, ſuch as turne from being <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants to be Infidels.</hi> There is one of M. <hi>Yerburies</hi> opinion, who ſaith, that the righteous are at liberty, <hi>[he that is righteous let him be righteous ſtill]</hi> and the wicked are at liberty, <hi>[he that is wicked let him be wicked ſtill,]</hi> but you are of a more dangerous opinion, the wicked as (as you think) are at liberty to kill and ſlay, but the godly are not at liberty to defend themſelves by the power of the higheſt <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Juſtice</hi> in the <hi>Kingdome</hi> from illegall and unjuſt oppreſſion, violence. I am convinced by many paſſages in your <hi>Sermon,</hi> eſpecially the 15, 16, 17. <hi>pages,</hi> that you think we ought not to fight againſt the <hi>Rebells</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> becauſe it is part of their <hi>Religion</hi> (as it was of your brethren the <hi>Cavaliers</hi>) to put all <hi>Roundheads</hi> (as you terme them) to the ſword; <hi>miſſajam mordet,</hi> the <hi>Maſs</hi> may be armed, but the <hi>Goſpel</hi> muſt not: What thinke you of the <hi>War</hi> fore-told in the book of the <hi>Revelation?</hi> Sir, you abuſe your betters when you talk of the <hi>Scruple-houſe.</hi> You are not worthy to carrie the books of thoſe Reverend <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters</hi> after them, nor could your <hi>Carfax-Sermon</hi> have ever ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenced the <hi>ungifted Preachers;</hi> you would have found them <hi>gif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Diſputants:</hi> if you think otherwiſe try one or two of them in ſome of their beaten points; Sir, I ſpeake thus freely, becauſe I was not preſent at the <hi>famous meeting, Novemb.</hi> 12. but I ſee you can cite one of your owne <hi>Prophets, Poets</hi> I ſhould ſay, but he is no truer a <hi>Prophet</hi> then you are like to prove a <hi>Martyr,</hi> a <hi>Cretian Prophet.</hi> Sir, the knowledge of my Brethrens worth, and your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous pride and ſelf-conceitedneſs hath provoked me to let my pen looſe, that I might diſabuſe and humble you.</p>
                  <p>It ſeems you are unwilling to come upon the <hi>ſtage</hi> (though that be a fitter place for you then the pulpit) to appear before a <hi>Theater</hi> of <hi>men</hi> and <hi>women:</hi> Sir, you love the <hi>ſtage</hi> too well, take heed you doe not love <hi>women</hi> too ill, there is a friend of yours
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:114217:7"/>that doth entreat you to beware of dark rooms and light women; for though a great <hi>Phyſitian</hi> doth adviſe you to the uſe of ſuch pleaſing <hi>phyſick,</hi> yet the <hi>Frenchmen</hi> will aſſure you, that it is not wholſome for the body, and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> can aſſure you, that it is not good for the ſoul; your kind of <hi>phrenfie</hi> muſt be cured by more ſevere remedies, your <hi>devill</hi> will be better caſt out with prayer and faſting. You are miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>informed when you ſay, that I did beat <hi>up my drum.</hi> No Sir, you did ſound a charge and made a challenge, my acceptance of it was but the eccho which anſwered the 17. and 21. <hi>pages</hi> of the <hi>Falſe Prophet.</hi> In the 17. you ſeem prepared to enter into diſpute preſently with the greateſt <hi>Champion</hi> that appeares for the <hi>Parliament,</hi> Sir, one of the meaneſt that appears for them, takes up that <hi>Gantlet</hi> which you threw forth with ſo much ſcorn and confidence.</p>
                  <p>In your 21. <hi>page</hi> you threaten to preſs us in a rationall logicall way; Sir, doe your beſt, you ſhall find that we have neither loſt our <hi>reaſon</hi> nor our <hi>logick.</hi> We can diſtinguiſh between <hi>demonstration</hi> and <hi>ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> and truly Sir, if you had not put more <hi>Poetry</hi> then <hi>Logick</hi> into your <hi>Sermon,</hi> though your <hi>Sermon</hi> might have been longer, yet your <hi>Libell</hi> would have been ſhorter; if you pleaſe to blot out thoſe few places of <hi>Scripture</hi> which you have abuſed by miſapplication and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prudent inſertion of them into ſo prophane and wild a ſtamp, you may do well to turne your <hi>Libell</hi> into <hi>Verſe,</hi> and then it may paſs currant amongſt the <hi>Balladmongers</hi> for a triobolar <hi>Ballad,</hi> and you will be ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in the number of thoſe who are reputed the moſt excellent <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors,</hi> next to them that write in <hi>Proſe.</hi> If you are offended that I did not ſhew you ſo much reſpect, as I have ſhewed towards the learned <hi>Author</hi> of the <hi>Practicall Catechiſme,</hi> conſider the difference, nay, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance betwen his perſon, education, learning, civility, writings and yours, and you will ſee a very ſufficient and ſatisfactory reaſon. Sir, if that <hi>Author</hi> did overlook your <hi>Letter,</hi> I believe he did adviſe you to contend onely for the <hi>lawfulneſs of Prelacy, becauſe I ſee that is interlined,</hi> and he was preſent at the ſad debate at <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xbridge;</hi> if that learned <hi>Doctor</hi> hath any thing to object againſt me, he knowes my <hi>mind, habet aetatem,</hi> he is able to ſpeake for himſelfe, the <hi>Oratour</hi> needs not borrow eloquence of ſo prophane a <hi>Poet.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>You are unwilling to diſpute in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> to which I anſwer:</p>
                  <p>Firſt, your <hi>Sermon</hi> is <hi>Engliſh.</hi> Secondly, many of the perſons whom you have abuſed and deceived by your <hi>printed Sermon,</hi> underſtand not <hi>Latine.</hi> Thirdly, you have been too much addicted to <hi>Engliſh
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:114217:8"/>Playes,</hi> and <hi>Engliſh Verſes,</hi> and you have with a pleaſant kind of <hi>igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi> ſhuffled them (with other <hi>Verſes</hi> publiſhed in more learned <hi>lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages</hi>) in the ſame book printed by the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity-Printer,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I believe you are moſt able, and moſt ingaged to diſpute in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> for the diſabuſing &amp; undeceiving of thoſe whom you have ſeduced by a <hi>Sermon</hi> preacht and printed in <hi>Engliſh.</hi> Be pleaſed to performe that task to morrow at two of the clock at S. <hi>Maries Church,</hi> where your <hi>Sermon</hi> was preacht, and I will meet you; and if you dare examine your <hi>Sermon</hi> by the <hi>Word of God,</hi> I ſhall be the <hi>Opponent,</hi> becauſe you have choſen to be the <hi>Reſpondent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If when the <hi>Doctor of the Chaire</hi> comes home, you pleaſe to diſpute in the <hi>Divinity Schools,</hi> let us agree upon the <hi>ſtate</hi> of the <hi>queſtions</hi> in controverſie, and I will accept your <hi>challenge</hi> at your owne <hi>weapon,</hi> which will I feare have more <hi>falſe Latine,</hi> then <hi>true ſteele.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>SIR, You make a <hi>diſhonourable retreat,</hi> when you ſay that <hi>Prelacy</hi> is lawfull; you have cried it up <hi>jure divino,</hi> &amp; aſſured the <hi>King,</hi> that hee cannot in conſcience paſſe the <hi>Bill</hi> againſt <hi>Prelacy,</hi> becauſe it is a <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> inſtituted by the will and appointment of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Now ſtand your ground, or confeſs your <hi>errour,</hi> acknowledge that <hi>you</hi> and your <hi>adherents</hi> have perſwaded the <hi>King</hi> to deſtroy ſo many thouſand of his loving and gallant <hi>ſubjects,</hi> that <hi>Prelacy</hi> might be eſtabliſhed in its <hi>tyrannicall height and rigour;</hi> and now the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>heaven</hi> and <hi>Lord of hoſts</hi> hath broken all your <hi>forces,</hi> you tell us that the <hi>Parliament</hi> muſt not purſue their <hi>victory;</hi> but we muſt in charity beare with thoſe <hi>malignant, Prelaticall,</hi> and <hi>Antichriſtian errors,</hi> which will not conſiſt with <hi>faith;</hi> be pleaſed to return ſuch an anſwer as will indure the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like <hi>teſt</hi> and <hi>touchſtone,</hi> and you ſhalbe <hi>rationally,</hi> nay <hi>ſpiritually</hi> dealt with by</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>The <hi>Prior opponent</hi> of the <hi>falſe Prophet, Francis Cheynell.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>To this <hi>letter</hi> (which (as all the world may judge) declines that part of <hi>entercourſe,</hi> which obligeth one mans <hi>letter</hi> to carry ſome <hi>corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondence</hi> to anothers, and inſtead of a <hi>confutation,</hi> only multiplies <hi>que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions,</hi> and urgeth me to prove divers paſſages of my <hi>Sermon,</hi> which M. <hi>Cheynell's</hi> part was to <hi>convince</hi>) becauſe the <hi>ſuperſcription</hi> of it <hi>dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> and the <hi>cloſe</hi> of it more <hi>clearly</hi> required me to meet him at an <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh diſputation</hi> the next day at S. <hi>Maries</hi> before the <hi>Townſmen</hi> and their <hi>wives,</hi> (very unfit <hi>moderators,</hi> certainly, in the points there to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus'd) I for the preſent (to divert that meeting) return'd him this <hi>ſhort Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:114217:8"/>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THough in the <hi>Letter</hi> you ſent me yeſterday by (I think) <hi>Jelly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> the <hi>Cobler,</hi> you have given me ſuch a taſt of your <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick</hi> as well as <hi>civility,</hi> that I have ſmall encouragement to meddle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny farther with you, (unleſs you will promiſe hereafter to write with better <hi>conſequence,</hi> and leſs <hi>diſtemper</hi>) yet, Sir, leaſt you ſhould tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph over me, as one beaten by your <hi>Arguments,</hi> not by your <hi>rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> I have thought fit for once to return you this <hi>anſwer.</hi> Firſt, that without the <hi>danger</hi> of a <hi>dark room</hi> (as I told you before) I cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to <hi>meet</hi> you at S. <hi>Maries</hi> at two a clock. Next, that I do imbrace your <hi>offer</hi> to meet me at <hi>Latine weapons</hi> in the <hi>Divinity Schoole,</hi> when the <hi>Doctor of the Chayre</hi> comes to town. Thirdly, that if your <hi>Syllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſmes</hi> be no better then your <hi>wit,</hi> (which I perceive ſtrived to be <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cete,</hi> when it adventured to ſay, that you <hi>feare</hi> my <hi>weapon will have more falſe Latine then true ſteele</hi>) I doubt the <hi>Poet</hi> you contemne ſo much, will go equall with you in the <hi>conqueſt.</hi> Laſtly, not being inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged (I confeſs) to preach <hi>thrice a day</hi>) I will with as much diſpatch as I can, put <hi>order</hi> to your <hi>chaos,</hi> and return a <hi>fuller anſwer</hi> to your <hi>ſtrange letter;</hi> wherein I know not whether you have leſs <hi>ſatisfied,</hi> or more <hi>reviled</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>From my Chamber <date>this morning Jan. 22. 1646.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>The <hi>Author</hi> of the <hi>Sermon</hi> againſt <hi>falſe Prophets, J. Mayne.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This <hi>Letter</hi> might have beene lengthened with many other <hi>reaſons</hi> (beſides thoſe already ſet down) to ſhew how unfit 'twas for mee to meet M. <hi>Cheynell</hi> at an <hi>Engliſh diſputation</hi> at S. <hi>Maries,</hi> as M. <hi>Yerbury</hi> did. As firſt, becauſe the <hi>frame</hi> and <hi>carriage</hi> of the whole <hi>diſpute</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us, in all probability would have been as <hi>irregular</hi> and <hi>tumultu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> as the other was; where, becauſe neither of them kept themſelves to the <hi>lawes of diſputation,</hi> which enjoyne the <hi>Diſputants</hi> to confine themſelves to <hi>Syllogiſme,</hi> raiſed from the ſtrict rules of <hi>Mood</hi> and <hi>Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure,</hi> which admit not of <hi>extravagancy:</hi> In the judgment of all <hi>Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers</hi> who were preſent, it was not a <hi>Diſpute,</hi> but a wild <hi>conflict,</hi> where neither anſwered one another, but with ſome mixture of <hi>ill language,</hi> were both <hi>Opponents</hi> by turnes. Next, becauſe the greateſt part of the <hi>Auditory</hi> would have conſiſted of ſuch a confluence of <hi>Townſmen</hi> and <hi>women,</hi> as underſtood good <hi>Arguments</hi> and <hi>Replies</hi> as little as they do <hi>Latine;</hi> and ſo the iſſue of this <hi>Diſputation</hi> would probably have been the ſame with the former; where M. <hi>Cheynell</hi> was thought to have the better by <hi>one Sex,</hi> and M. <hi>Yerbury</hi> by the <hi>other.</hi> Loath, therefore to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:114217:9"/>my diſcretion before ſuch an <hi>Incompetent Aſſembly</hi> of witneſſes, with as much diſpatch as one ingaged by promiſe could make, I retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to his <hi>Letter</hi> this fuller <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>Among the other praiſes, which greater friends to the <hi>Muſes</hi> then I perceive you are, have beſtowed upon <hi>Virgil,</hi> he hath been cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Virgin Poet.</hi> Yet <hi>Auſonius</hi> ordering his <hi>Verſes</hi> another way, hath raiſed one of the moſt looſe laſcivious Poems from him that I think ever wore the name of a <hi>Marriage-ſong.</hi> Me thinks Sir (and I doubt not but all they who ſhal compare them together will be of my opinion) you in your Letter have juſt dealt ſo with my <hi>Sermon;</hi> it went from my hands forth a ſober <hi>Virgin,</hi> but falling into yours, it returns to me ſo ſtrumpet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſo diſtorted in the ſenſe, and miſapplied in the expreſſions, that what I preach'd a <hi>Sermon,</hi> you by tranſlating whatever I have ſaid of <hi>falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets</hi> to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> have with the dexterity of a falſification, tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed and changed into a <hi>Libell.</hi> This I do not wonder at, when I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what the <hi>Phyſitian</hi> was, who ſaid, that where the <hi>Recipient</hi> is <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempered,</hi> the moſt wholſome food turns into his diſeaſe; juſt as we ſee in thoſe harmfull creatures, whoſe whole <hi>eſſence</hi> and <hi>compoſition</hi> is made up of <hi>ſting</hi> and <hi>poyſon,</hi> the juice which they ſuck from <hi>flowers</hi> and <hi>roſes,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocts into <hi>venome</hi> and <hi>becomes poyſon</hi> too. Having ſaid this by way of <hi>Preface</hi> to my following <hi>Reply,</hi> firſt, Sir, (confining my ſelf to your <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod</hi>) how you ſpend your morning thoughts, being impoſſible for me outright to know, unleſs your thoughts were either viſible or you tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent; I deſire you wil not think me over-curious, if I open a door upon you, and proceed by conjecture. You ſay, you uſe to <hi>ſpend them upon a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſubject then a pot of dead drink that hath a little froth at top, and dregs at bottome.</hi> To what paſſage of my <hi>Letter</hi> this refers, or why a <hi>language</hi> which I do not underſtand, ſhould poſſeſs the <hi>porch</hi> &amp; <hi>entrance</hi> to <hi>yours,</hi> I am not <hi>Oedipus</hi> enough to <hi>unriddle.</hi> But if I may gueſs what your <hi>mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thoughts were,</hi> when (as you confeſs) you did <hi>let them looſe</hi> by your <hi>pen</hi> to diſcharge themſelves upon me in a ſhower of <hi>rude, untheologicall, flat, downright detraction,</hi> though they were not employ'd upon a <hi>frothy ſubject,</hi> yet they ſhew that you were at that time in <hi>his diſtemper</hi> in the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> a piece of whoſe <hi>raging</hi> and <hi>diſtraction</hi> 'twas to <hi>fome at mouth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Next Sir, had I been preſent at your <hi>Sermon,</hi> (as I am glad I was not, for I deſire not to be an <hi>Auditor</hi> where I muſt hear my ſelf <hi>libelled</hi> from the <hi>pulpit</hi>) I ſhal eaſily grant, by the <hi>taſte</hi> which you have given me in this <hi>ſhort Conference</hi> with you of the perſpicuity of your <hi>ſtile,</hi> and the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:114217:9"/>
                     <hi>clearneſs</hi> of your <hi>matter,</hi> that 't was poſſible enough for me not to <hi>underſtand it.</hi> I doe, therefore, acknowledge it as a <hi>favour</hi> from you, that you will let me no longer wander in uncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or write to you upon the <hi>miſ-report</hi> of a <hi>fallible Intelligencer;</hi> but will <hi>your ſelfe</hi> be my <hi>Clue</hi> to guide me to what you ſaid. Which <hi>favour,</hi> you have much <hi>heightned,</hi> by robbing your <hi>weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier employments</hi> of ſo much <hi>time</hi> to convey it in, as might have been ſpent in providing your ſelfe to preach <hi>thrice a day,</hi> and yet not doe it ſo <hi>haſtily,</hi> or with ſuch a <hi>running negligence,</hi> as to be thought to preach but <hi>once a week.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As for your <hi>Text,</hi> and the <hi>Doctrine</hi> built upon it, at whom ſoever it was <hi>ſhot,</hi> I ſhall not quarrell with it. But how your <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rollary</hi> ſhould concern any thing that I have ſaid in my <hi>Sermon</hi> contrary to your <hi>Doctrine,</hi> I cannot poſſibly <hi>imagine;</hi> who do there onely ſpeak of the <hi>vanity</hi> of ſome of our <hi>Modern Prophets,</hi> who can ſee <hi>Idolatry in a Church-window:</hi> And do onely ſtrive to prove that for <hi>people</hi> to refrain the <hi>Church</hi> (as you know who did) becauſe <hi>ſome</hi> (though perhaps not of <hi>our age</hi>) paid <hi>worſhip</hi> to the <hi>windowes,</hi> was a fear as unreaſonable as <hi>theirs</hi> was, who refuſed to go to <hi>Sea,</hi> becauſe there was a <hi>Painter</hi> in the <hi>City</hi> who <hi>limn'd ſhipwracks.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sir, had you a minde to deal <hi>pertinently</hi> or <hi>ingennouſly</hi> with me, you would witneſs for me, that though I ſpeak in defence of the <hi>Ornamentall uſe</hi> of <hi>Images,</hi> yet I in no paſsage of my <hi>Sermon</hi> do defend any <hi>Image</hi> or <hi>pourtraicture</hi> made of the <hi>Deity.</hi> Sir, 'tis not your ſaying, That <hi>no picture can be made of God, becauſe there is nothing like him in Heaven or Earth,</hi> or the following <hi>proofs</hi> of your <hi>letter</hi> (which I conceive to be a <hi>piece</hi> of your <hi>Sermon</hi> at <hi>St. Maries,</hi> which becauſe I came not to <hi>it,</hi> you in charity have ſent home to <hi>me</hi>) that perſwades me that any ſuch <hi>picture</hi> is <hi>unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: Nature,</hi> as well as the numerous places of <hi>Scripture,</hi> which you have quoted to prove that which I never yet denied, have long ſince taught me, that to <hi>make,</hi> or <hi>draw</hi> any <hi>picture,</hi> or <hi>Image of God</hi> is not onely a <hi>breach</hi> of the <hi>ſecond Commandement,</hi> which is built upon the <hi>inviſibility</hi> of his <hi>Eſſence,</hi> and <hi>Nature,</hi> but that the <hi>Attempt</hi> would be much more <hi>vain,</hi> then if a <hi>Painter</hi> ſhould endeavour to limn a <hi>ſoul</hi> or <hi>minde,</hi> which not affording any <hi>Idea,</hi> or <hi>reſemblance</hi> to his <hi>fancy</hi> to be taken by, cannot poſſibly by him
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:114217:10"/>be expreſt in <hi>Colours.</hi> The Task, therefore, to make any <hi>Draught</hi> or <hi>Figure</hi> of <hi>God</hi> (pray Sir, being miſled by <hi>your example,</hi> do not think me ſuperfluous in my purſuit of an <hi>Argument,</hi> to which I was not bound to <hi>reply</hi>) is (beſides the <hi>ſinfulneſs</hi> of it) much more impoſſible. For, <hi>First,</hi> Sir, if the <hi>School-men</hi> (which I hear you once ſaid you had long ſtudied to little purpoſe) may be <hi>Judges,</hi> He cannot be <hi>limn'd</hi> or <hi>drawn,</hi> becauſe he is a <hi>Spirit:</hi> Therefore not capable to be repreſented by any <hi>groſs, materiall Thing. Next,</hi> becauſe He is <hi>Infinite;</hi> and therefore not capable to fall under <hi>Symmetry,</hi> or be circumſcribed within the <hi>finite lines</hi> which ſtream from a <hi>Painters pencill.</hi> Thirdly, becauſe He is <hi>Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> that is, (as <hi>your Schoolmen</hi> ſay, for you know Sir, I am but an <hi>Engliſh poet</hi>) <hi>All</hi> in <hi>All,</hi> and <hi>All</hi> in <hi>every part:</hi> Or, in other <hi>Termes,</hi> a Thing entirely <hi>uniform,</hi> and <hi>indiviſible</hi> within it ſelf, which admits not of any falſe <hi>repreſentation</hi> of it ſelf by <hi>limbs</hi> or <hi>parts.</hi> Laſtly, Sir, (becauſe I will not be tedious, and go over all his other <hi>Attributes</hi>) who ſhall <hi>paint</hi> his <hi>Omaiſcience,</hi> who his <hi>Omnipotence,</hi> who his <hi>Eternity,</hi> who his <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>biquity?</hi> Knowing this Sir, and much more of him (not by the Help of a <hi>borrowed Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination</hi>) I could not treſpaſse ſo much againſt my own <hi>ſtudies,</hi> and <hi>Conſcience</hi> as to allow of any <hi>picture</hi> of <hi>God.</hi> And therefore, in this particular, challenging me, (as you <hi>impertinently</hi> do) to <hi>produce my ſtrong reaſons, and overthrow,</hi> if I can, your <hi>Doctrine,</hi> or <hi>Corollary, deduced from Eſay</hi> 40.25. where God by his Prophet ſayes, <hi>To whom will ye liken me, or ſhall I be equall ſaith the Holy One?</hi> You would fain have me be your <hi>Adverſary</hi> in an <hi>undefen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Cauſe,</hi> that your <hi>conquest</hi> of me might be the eaſier. In ſhort, you would have me profeſs my ſelfe to be an <hi>Anthropomorphite,</hi> that you might have the advantage to confute me for an <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retike.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sir, ſince you deny that you ſaid in your <hi>Sermon,</hi> that I made <hi>Images equall with God</hi> (which if you had ſaid, my <hi>Sermon</hi> without any new confutation, would have <hi>diſproved</hi> you) I am in that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular <hi>ſatisfied,</hi> and ſhall think it was, though not a <hi>wilfull</hi> one, yet a <hi>miſtake</hi> in the <hi>reporter.</hi> But, then, Sir, I muſt tell you, that I am not at all <hi>ſatisfied</hi> with that which followes. Where you ſay, that <hi>Images are not like unto God,</hi> and <hi>Thereupon wonder that I took upon me to plead for the retaining of thoſe Images which have been
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:114217:10"/>too often turned into Idols, not by the piety, but ſuperſtition of former times:</hi> For here, Sir, if I would take the advantage of <hi>expreſsion</hi> not well conſidered, upon you, in ſaying that <hi>Images are not like unto God,</hi> and <hi>thereupon</hi> that I did ill to plead for the retaining of other <hi>Images</hi> not of <hi>God,</hi> a <hi>Sophiſter</hi> would make the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that you think all <hi>Images</hi> ſuperſtitious, and therefore fit to be baniſht out of the <hi>Church,</hi> but onely ſuch <hi>Images</hi> as are <hi>made of God;</hi> which would expoſe you to the <hi>opinion</hi> of being thought very ſubject to ſpeak <hi>contradictions.</hi> But being a <hi>meer poet,</hi> Sir, whoſe <hi>ability,</hi> you know, lies not in making uſe of <hi>Ariſtotles Eleuchs,</hi> but in the <hi>ſoft, harmleſs compoſure</hi> of an <hi>Elegie</hi> or <hi>Ode,</hi> I ſhall deal more gently with you; That is, take you in the moſt <hi>advantagious ſenſe</hi> which you poſſibly, upon your better <hi>morning thoughts</hi> can put to <hi>your words,</hi> &amp; believe, that the fault you finde with me for the <hi>retainment</hi> of <hi>Images,</hi> is, becauſe by the <hi>ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of <hi>former times</hi> they have been turn'd into <hi>Idols.</hi> Sir, if I be not deceiv'd, my <hi>Sermon,</hi> in this <hi>particular,</hi> is able to ſave me the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of a <hi>reply.</hi> Where I have once for all ſaid that which you wil never be able to controul (how <hi>poetically</hi> (that is <hi>not dully</hi>) ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver you may think it expreſt) that by the ſame reaſon that <hi>Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> are to be turn'd out of the <hi>Church,</hi> becauſe ſome out of a <hi>miſ-guided devotion</hi> have <hi>adored</hi> them, we ſhould not have a <hi>Sun,</hi> or <hi>Moon,</hi> or <hi>Starres</hi> in the <hi>firmament,</hi> but they ſhould long ſince have been baniſht the <hi>skies,</hi> becauſe ſome of the <hi>deluded Heathen worſhipt</hi> them. The <hi>little fallacy</hi> with which you think to entrap me, when you ſay, that <hi>hence you collect that I will be forced to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that Images are as neceſſary in the Church, as the Sunne in the Firmament,</hi> will expire, like all other <hi>thin Sophiſmes,</hi> in <hi>vanity</hi> &amp; <hi>ſmoke,</hi> when I have ſhewn the <hi>weakneſs</hi> and <hi>infirmity</hi> of it, which will be briefly done by repeating onely the <hi>ſenſe</hi> of my <hi>Sermon</hi> in <hi>other words,</hi> and ſaying, that if <hi>Images</hi> doe <hi>agree</hi> with the <hi>Sunne,</hi> in that they have both been made <hi>Idols,</hi> though <hi>one</hi> be no <hi>neceſſary part</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> and the <hi>other</hi> be a <hi>neceſſary part</hi> of the <hi>building</hi> of the <hi>world,</hi> yet if for that <hi>reaſon</hi> wherein they <hi>agree, one</hi> muſt be <hi>baniſht,</hi> any man that hath <hi>Logick</hi> (though he be a <hi>Poet</hi>) may inferre, that t' will be as reaſonable that the <hi>other</hi> ſhould be <hi>baniſht</hi> too.</p>
                  <p>In your next <hi>Paragraph,</hi> or <hi>fardell of I know not what,</hi> you ſay
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:114217:11"/>that <hi>I plead for Copes,</hi> and <hi>for thoſe parts of the Common-Prayer-booke which were borrowed from Rome:</hi> And then <hi>confute</hi> me with the <hi>threats</hi> of an <hi>ere-long Viſitation.</hi> Sir, there is neither <hi>Logick,</hi> nor <hi>School-Divinity</hi> in this. As for <hi>Copes,</hi> you know I joyne them with <hi>Surplices</hi> in my <hi>Sermon;</hi> and ſay that by the ſame <hi>reaſon</hi> that the <hi>falſe Prophets</hi> of <hi>our times</hi> would perſwade the <hi>people that Surplices are unlawfull becauſe Papiſts weare them,</hi> they may endeavour to perſwade them, that <hi>Linnen</hi> is alſo <hi>unlawfull,</hi> becauſe <hi>Papiſts ſhift;</hi> and ſo conclude <hi>Cleanlineſs</hi> to be as <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious</hi> as <hi>Surplices</hi> or <hi>Copes.</hi> Sir, you may call this <hi>Poetry,</hi> but there is a <hi>Logick</hi> in it, which I hope doth not ceaſe to be <hi>Logick,</hi> which you cannot <hi>reſiſt,</hi> becauſe 'tis not <hi>watriſhly</hi> or <hi>flegmatickly</hi> expreſt. As for thoſe <hi>parts</hi> of the <hi>Common-Prayer-booke,</hi> which I doe not ſay were <hi>borrowed</hi> from <hi>Rome,</hi> (as you impoſe upon me) but are to be found in the <hi>Rubrick</hi> of the <hi>Church:</hi> if I had ſaid they had been <hi>borrowed</hi> from that <hi>Church,</hi> yet <hi>you</hi> have ſaid no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to prove, that upon <hi>this ſuppoſition</hi> 'tis <hi>Popery</hi> to uſe thoſe <hi>Prayers</hi> in <hi>Ours.</hi> Foreſeeing, I beleeve, that if you had offered to maintaine that what ever is in the <hi>Popiſh Lyturgie</hi> is <hi>Popery,</hi> that is, <hi>ſuperſtitious,</hi> and fit to be <hi>proſcribed</hi> out of the <hi>Church,</hi> you would (meeting with a <hi>good Diſputant,</hi> and one not addicted to <hi>Poetry</hi>) have been compelled to confeſs, that the <hi>Lords Prayer,</hi> and <hi>Davids Pſalmes</hi> are <hi>Popery</hi> too, (though the one were deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the other by <hi>one</hi> who lived long before <hi>Antichriſt</hi>) becauſe they are bound up in the ſame <hi>volumne</hi> with the <hi>Maſſe.</hi> Sir, if this be your <hi>Logick,</hi> 'tis <hi>Socrate ambulante coruſcavit,</hi> and will be a <hi>falſe fire</hi> to lead you for ever out of the way. But here, Sir, though I need not take the paines to <hi>confute</hi> the <hi>Nothings</hi> you have ſaid againſt me, in <hi>this particular,</hi> yet whenever you ſhal call upon me to make good my <hi>undertaking,</hi> I doe promiſe to make it evident to you, that all the <hi>ancient parts</hi> of the <hi>Common-Prayer-booke,</hi> which I <hi>plead</hi> for, I doe not plead for becauſe they are uſed by the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> but becauſe they were part of the <hi>Lyturgie</hi> of thoſe <hi>Churches</hi> which were thought <hi>primitively pure,</hi> and not <hi>ſuperſtitious,</hi> and were in the world long before <hi>Popery,</hi> or <hi>Antichriſt</hi> was borne. I muſt, therefore, for ought you have yet ſaid to alter my <hi>opinion,</hi> ſtill ſtand to my <hi>former concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> which is, that by the <hi>ſame reaſon</hi> that either the <hi>whole,</hi> or <hi>any
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:114217:11"/>part</hi> of our <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon-Prayer-Book</hi> is to be <hi>turned</hi> out of the <hi>Church,</hi> becauſe in <hi>ſome things</hi> it agrees with the <hi>Lyturgie</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome, Italy,</hi> and <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf is to be <hi>turned</hi> out of the <hi>world,</hi> (&amp; ſo a <hi>new Map</hi> to be made of it where theſe <hi>places</hi> are not) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are the <hi>Popes Territories,</hi> and lye under his <hi>Juriſdiction.</hi> Laſtly, Sir, as for the <hi>Viſitors</hi> you <hi>threaten</hi> both <hi>me</hi> and <hi>Chriſt-Church</hi> withall, (of <hi>whom</hi> ſome <hi>report</hi> that <hi>you</hi> are <hi>one</hi>) when you come to <hi>execute</hi> your <hi>Commiſsion,</hi> ſo you will not urge it as a <hi>Topicke</hi> to <hi>convince</hi> my <hi>underſtanding,</hi> but as a <hi>Delegacy</hi> of <hi>power</hi> to <hi>examine</hi> my <hi>ſtudies, life,</hi> and <hi>manners,</hi> I ſhall bring all the <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion</hi> with me which can be expected from <hi>one</hi> ſubject to the <hi>try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al.</hi> and <hi>examination</hi> of ſuch a <hi>power.</hi> Being withall very confident, that when <hi>that time</hi> comes, however you may perhaps finde an <hi>old Cope</hi> or <hi>two</hi> in our <hi>Colledge,</hi> yet you will never bring <hi>Logick</hi> enough with you to prove, that they are either <hi>Idolatrous,</hi> or have been put to a <hi>ſuperſtitious</hi> uſe. And therefore, Sir, in this <hi>particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar</hi> you have loſt your <hi>friendly counſell,</hi> there being no need at all that we ſhould <hi>againſt that time ſtudy for an Anſwer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In your next <hi>Faſcicle,</hi> you ſay, that I maintaine that <hi>ſome things in the Excellency, and Height of the Doctrines of Chriſtian Religion depend for their credit, and the Evidence of their Truth, upon the Authority of Chriſts Miracles convey'd along in Tradition, and Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry;</hi> And, therefore, conclude that my <hi>Religion leanes too hard, and too heavy upon Tradition.</hi> Sir, though I have alwayes lookt upon the <hi>Scriptures</hi> of the <hi>Old Teſtament</hi> and the <hi>New,</hi> as two <hi>glorious lampes,</hi> which to all <hi>eyes</hi> (that have not loſt the uſe of <hi>ſeeing,</hi> by being kept <hi>ſequeſtred</hi> from the <hi>ſunne</hi> too long in the <hi>darke</hi>) mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually give <hi>light</hi> to <hi>one another,</hi> ſo that a <hi>vigilant Reader,</hi> by compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>Prophecies</hi> with their <hi>Accompliſhments,</hi> will have very great <hi>reaſon</hi> to beleeve that both are <hi>true,</hi> yet becauſe this amounts but to the <hi>diſcourſes</hi> and <hi>perſwaſions</hi> of a <hi>ſingle mans reaſon,</hi> if I prefer <hi>Tradition,</hi> which is the <hi>conſtant, univerſall conſent of all Ages,</hi> as a <hi>fuller medium</hi> to prove <hi>doctrines by</hi> which are hardly <hi>otherwiſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrable,</hi> doe I any more, I pray, then prefer the <hi>univerſall Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony,</hi> and <hi>Report</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of all <hi>Times,</hi> before the more <hi>fallible ſuggeſtions</hi> of a <hi>private ſpirit?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Your next <hi>Paragraph,</hi> is perfectly the <hi>Hydra</hi> with <hi>repullulating Heads</hi> which I warned you of in my <hi>firſt Letter;</hi> And multiplies
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:114217:12"/>ſo many <hi>cauſeleſs queſtions</hi> as make it nothing but a <hi>heape,</hi> partly of ſuch <hi>doubts,</hi> partly of <hi>untruths,</hi> as would make it one of <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cules labours</hi> to <hi>examine</hi> them. Firſt, you bid me <hi>prove that Chriſt hath put the ſole power of Ordination in the hand of a Prelate.</hi> Sir, if the <hi>practice</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> in the <hi>Scripture</hi> in this <hi>point</hi> were not cleare, yet the <hi>practice</hi> and <hi>opinion</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> for 1500 yeeres ought to be of too great <hi>Authority</hi> with you to make this a <hi>ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi> Knowing that no <hi>Church</hi> in the world thought otherwiſe, till the <hi>Preſbyterian Modell</hi> crept forth of <hi>Calvins fancie;</hi> nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>good Proteſtant</hi> in the <hi>Church of England,</hi> till ſuch as <hi>you</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>called <hi>Aërius</hi> from his <hi>grave,</hi> and <hi>Duſt</hi> to oppoſe <hi>Biſhops.</hi> Next, you bid me <hi>juſtifie, that no Church that ever the ſunne lookt upon hath beene more bleſt with purity of Religion for the Doctrines of it, or better eſtabliſht for the Government, and Diſcipline of it, then the Church of England hath.</hi> Sir, you repeat not the words of my <hi>Sermon</hi> ſo faithfully as you ſhould. I am not ſo <hi>extravagant</hi> as to ſay, that <hi>no Church that ever the Sunne lookt upon,</hi> but that the <hi>Sun in all his heavenly courſe for ſo many, many yeeres,</hi> that is, (in my <hi>ſenſe</hi>) for <hi>many Ages,</hi> ſaw not a <hi>purer Church</hi> then <hi>ours</hi> was, both for the <hi>Doctrines,</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline</hi> of it. Againſt this you wildly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, I know not what <hi>Doctrines publiquely countenanced,</hi> but tell me not what theſe <hi>Doctrines</hi> were, ſpeake of certaine <hi>ſuperſtitious practices,</hi> and <hi>Prelaticall uſurpations,</hi> but doe not prove them to be either <hi>ſuperſtitious,</hi> or <hi>uſurpt;</hi> quarrell with the <hi>Delegation of Biſhops power to Chancellors,</hi> then proceed to the <hi>tyrannie of the High-Commiſsion-Court,</hi> and at laſt conclude with I know not what <hi>Imaginary corruptions and Innovations introduced into the State, Church, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity.</hi> Sir, if I ſhould grant this <hi>long-winded Charge</hi> of yours to be true, (as truly I think it is onely a <hi>ſeeing of vanity</hi>) yet my <hi>confident Aſſertion</hi> is not hereby <hi>enfeebled</hi> I hope, when I ſpoke of the <hi>purity of our Church,</hi> you did not think I freed it from all <hi>blemiſhes</hi> or <hi>ſpots.</hi> The <hi>Primitive Church</hi> it ſelfe had <hi>ſome</hi> in it who broacht <hi>ſtrange doctrines;</hi> Saint <hi>John</hi> had not elſe written his <hi>Goſpell</hi> againſt the <hi>Gnoſticks,</hi> nor Saint <hi>Paul</hi> his Epiſtle to the <hi>Galatians</hi> againſt thoſe that held the <hi>neceſsity of Circumciſion.</hi> The <hi>next Ages</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> have not been more diſtinguiſht by their <hi>Martyrs,</hi> then <hi>Heretiques;</hi> yet the <hi>Primitive Church</hi> ceaſed not to be <hi>Apoſtolically pure,</hi> becauſe it had a <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthus,</hi>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:114217:12"/>or <hi>Nicolaitans</hi> in it; nor the ſucceeding <hi>Churches</hi> to be the <hi>Spouſe</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> becauſe <hi>one</hi> brought forth an <hi>Apelles, another</hi> a <hi>Marcion,</hi> a <hi>third</hi> a <hi>Neſtorius,</hi> a <hi>fourth</hi> an <hi>Eutiches,</hi> a <hi>fift</hi> an <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us.</hi> Sir, as long as the beſt <hi>Church</hi> in the world conſiſts of men not <hi>infallible</hi> there will be <hi>errors.</hi> But then you muſt not charge the <hi>Heterodox opinions</hi> or <hi>Doctrines</hi> of <hi>particular men,</hi> though, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, <hi>countenanced</hi> by <hi>ſome</hi> in <hi>publique authority</hi> upon the <hi>Church.</hi> Beſides, Sir, every <hi>Innovation</hi> is not neceſsarily a <hi>Corruption,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it <hi>diſplace,</hi> or lay an <hi>Oſtraciſme</hi> upon ſome other <hi>thing</hi> more <hi>worthy</hi> and <hi>better</hi> then it <hi>ſelfe. You</hi> your ſelfe ſay, that the <hi>corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> introduced were brought in by a <hi>prevailing faction, who were not the Church.</hi> If they were not, my <hi>Aſſertion</hi> holds good, that notwithſtanding ſuch <hi>corruptions,</hi> yet our <hi>Church</hi> in its time was the <hi>pureſt Church</hi> in the world. This, then, being ſo, me thinks, Sir, you in your <hi>purſuit</hi> of <hi>Reformation,</hi> by making <hi>Root</hi> &amp; <hi>Branch</hi> your <hi>Rule</hi> of proceeding, have beene more <hi>ſevere</hi> then the <hi>lawes</hi> of <hi>right Reaſon</hi> will allow you. If there were ſuch a tyrannie as you ſpeake of ſtreaming it ſelfe from the <hi>High Commiſsion Court,</hi> why could not the <hi>tyrannie</hi> be <hi>ſuppreſt,</hi> without the <hi>aboliſhment</hi> of the <hi>Court?</hi> Or if there were ſuch a thing as <hi>Prelaticall uſurpation,</hi> why could not the <hi>uſurpations</hi> be taken away, and <hi>Epiſcopacie</hi> left to <hi>ſtand?</hi> Sir, if you be <hi>Logician</hi> enough to be able to diſtinguiſh betweene the <hi>faults</hi> of <hi>perſons</hi> and the <hi>ſacredneſs of functions,</hi> you cannot but pronounce with me, that to <hi>extirpate</hi> an <hi>order</hi> of the <hi>Church, ancient</hi> as the <hi>Chriſtian Church it ſelfe,</hi> and made <hi>venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> by the <hi>never-interrupted Reception</hi> of it in all the <hi>Ages</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> but <hi>ours,</hi> for the <hi>irregular carriage</hi> of a <hi>Prelate</hi> or <hi>two,</hi> (if any <hi>ſuch</hi> have beene among us) is a <hi>courſe</hi> like <hi>theirs,</hi> who thought there was no way left to reforme <hi>drunkenneſs</hi> in their <hi>State,</hi> but utterly to <hi>root up,</hi> and <hi>extirpate,</hi> and <hi>baniſh Vines.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>remainder</hi> of your <hi>Paragraph</hi> is very <hi>politically</hi> orderd; which is, that becauſe you finde it hard for you to <hi>confute</hi> my <hi>Sermon</hi> by <hi>your Arguments,</hi> you will endeavour to make the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> my <hi>Adverſary,</hi> who, you thinke, are able to <hi>confute</hi> it by <hi>their power:</hi> And bid me prove that <hi>the proceedings of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are Turkiſh.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Here, Sir, methinks, being a <hi>Poet,</hi> I ſee a piece of <hi>Ben Johnſon's</hi> beſt <hi>Comedy,</hi> the <hi>Fox,</hi> preſented to me; that is, <hi>you,</hi> a <hi>Politique
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:114217:13"/>Would-be</hi> the <hi>ſecond,</hi> ſheltring your ſelf under a <hi>capacious Tortoiſe-ſhell.</hi> Why, Sir, can you perſwade <hi>your ſelfe</hi> that the <hi>great Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell</hi> of the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> by <hi>whom</hi> you are imployed, if they will vouchſafe to <hi>reade</hi> my <hi>Sermon,</hi> will not preſently diſcerne your <hi>Art?</hi> And withall perceive, that though the <hi>Text,</hi> upon which I, out of the <hi>Integrity</hi> of my <hi>ſoule,</hi> preacht that <hi>Sermon,</hi> ſtick as cloſe to <hi>Falſe Prophets,</hi> as the <hi>Centaures ſhirt</hi> did to <hi>Hercules,</hi> and ſet them a <hi>raging,</hi> yet that they having never <hi>Parliamentarily</hi> profeſt to <hi>propagate Religion by their ſpeare,</hi> can no way be concerned, when I ſay that <hi>ſuch a perſwaſion in us Chriſtians would be Mahu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metan;</hi> and we thereby ſhould <hi>tranſlate a piece of the Alchoran into a piece of the Goſpel.</hi> Sir, I am ſo confident of the <hi>wiſdome</hi> of that <hi>Honourable Aſſembly,</hi> of my owne <hi>innocent meaning,</hi> and of <hi>your guilt,</hi> (who have beene <hi>one</hi> of thoſe <hi>Turkiſh Prophets,</hi> (and in your <hi>Letter</hi> to me ſtill are) who have preacht that <hi>piece</hi> of the <hi>Alchoran</hi> for <hi>good doctrine</hi>) that for anſwer to all your <hi>ſlye, impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tently-malicious miſ-applications</hi> and <hi>ſhiftings</hi> off that which I have ſaid onely of <hi>ſuch</hi> as <hi>your ſelfe</hi> to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> I ſhall onely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale to my <hi>Sermon.</hi> And by <hi>that,</hi> if you pleaſe to undertake the <hi>Devils part,</hi> and be my <hi>Accuſer,</hi> ſhall be content to <hi>ſtand</hi> or <hi>fall.</hi> In the meane time, Sir, I muſt repeat what I ſaid before, that if it be read, or lookt on through thoſe <hi>refractions,</hi> with which you have <hi>miſ-ſhap'd,</hi> and <hi>crookt</hi> it, I ſhall conſent to what you ſay in the end of your <hi>filthy Paragraph;</hi> That 'twas <hi>once</hi> a <hi>Sermon,</hi> but <hi>you</hi> almoſt <hi>à Carceribus uſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ad metam</hi> have made it a <hi>Libell.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In your <hi>next</hi> (what ſhall I call it?) you are very <hi>Critically plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant;</hi> And becauſe I talke of a <hi>Religion</hi> wherein I was <hi>borne,</hi> aske me, whether I were <hi>borne in a Surplice,</hi> or <hi>Cope;</hi> and then very <hi>diſtinguiſhingly</hi> proceed, and ſay, <hi>Chriſtiani non naſcuntur, ſed fiunt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To the firſt, I reply, that it had been as <hi>unnaturall</hi> for <hi>me</hi> to be <hi>borne</hi> in a <hi>Surplice,</hi> or <hi>Cope,</hi> as for <hi>you</hi> to come into the world, with a <hi>little Geneva ſet-ruffe</hi> about your neck.</p>
                  <p>Next, Sir, for your <hi>ſharpe diſtinction,</hi> I hope, though the <hi>Muſes</hi> be your <hi>Step-dames,</hi> yet you thinke not the <hi>figures</hi> of <hi>Rhetorick</hi> to be ſo <hi>ſuperſtitious,</hi> that it ſhall be <hi>Popery</hi> in <hi>me,</hi> to make uſe of a <hi>Metonymy,</hi> and to expreſs my ſelfe by the <hi>Adjunct,</hi> when I mean the <hi>place,</hi> and <hi>Country.</hi> I grant, Sir, that men are not <hi>borne,</hi> but
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:114217:13"/>
                     <hi>re-born Chriſtians;</hi> yet 'twill be no great <hi>Errour</hi> in <hi>ſpeech</hi> for a man to ſay he is <hi>born</hi> in <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> if he be a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> and were <hi>born</hi> in the <hi>place</hi> where <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> is <hi>eſtabliſh'd.</hi> Sir, I doubt you begin to think <hi>ſecular learning</hi> to be a <hi>profane thing;</hi> And that you are bound to perſecute <hi>Tropes</hi> out of <hi>Expreſſion,</hi> as you have <hi>Liturgy</hi> out of the <hi>Church.</hi> If you do, Sir, we ſhall in time, (if we proceed in this <hi>conflict</hi>) fulfill a <hi>peece</hi> of one of Saint <hi>Paul's Epiſtles</hi> between us; I become a <hi>Barbarian to you,</hi> and <hi>you to me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I am glad to hear you ſay, That <hi>the Parliament will not ſuppreſs the true Proteſtant Religion;</hi> Sir, I never thought they would. But, then 'twill be no harm to <hi>you,</hi> if I pray, That whilſt you <hi>purſue</hi> ſuch a <hi>through Reformation</hi> of it, as of late years hath left it doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in the <hi>minds</hi> of the <hi>people</hi> what the <hi>true Proteſtant Religion</hi> is, you let not in <hi>Popery</hi> at that <hi>Gate,</hi> by which they ſtrive to ſhut it out. If <hi>Queen Maries</hi> dayes do once more break in upon us through the <hi>ſluce</hi> which we open to them by our <hi>unſetledneſs,</hi> and <hi>Diſtractions,</hi> and if I <hi>then fall a ſacrifice</hi> in <hi>defence</hi> of the ſame <hi>Religion</hi> for which I now contend, I hope you then will think your ſelf <hi>confuted;</hi> And no longer beleeve that I am ſuch an <hi>ill Judge</hi> of <hi>Religions,</hi> or ſo profuſely prodigall of my <hi>life,</hi> that I would make it a <hi>Holocauſt,</hi> or <hi>Oblation,</hi> either to <hi>Tyranny,</hi> or <hi>Popery.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In ſhort, Sir, let the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament</hi> agree to <hi>burn Copes,</hi> and <hi>Surplices,</hi> to <hi>throw away the Common-Prayer-Book,</hi> or to <hi>break</hi> our <hi>Windows,</hi> I ſhall not place ſo much <hi>Religion</hi> in them, as not to think them <hi>alterable,</hi> and this done by <hi>Right Authority.</hi> But as for the <hi>Covenant,</hi> 'tis a <hi>pill,</hi> Sir, which no <hi>ſecular intereſt</hi> can ſo ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to me, that I ſhould think my ſelf obliged to be ſo far of <hi>any mans Religion,</hi> as to ſwallow both parts of a contradiction in an Oath, if it appear to me to be ſuch.</p>
                  <p>Your promiſe that my <hi>Sermon</hi> ſhould be firſt <hi>confuted before it be burnt,</hi> gives me hope it will be <hi>longer liv'd,</hi> then upon the firſt report I thought it would. But then I wonder you ſhould paſſe that ſentence on it, and chooſe <hi>Paraeus</hi> for your <hi>precedent.</hi> I muſt confeſſe to you Sir, had I written ſo deſtructively of <hi>Parliaments</hi> as <hi>He</hi> did of <hi>Kings,</hi> I ſhould think it no <hi>injuſtice</hi> from that <hi>High Court,</hi> if they ſhould doom <hi>me</hi> the <hi>Author</hi> to be <hi>ſacrificed</hi> on the ſame <hi>Altar</hi> with <hi>my Book.</hi> But having (upon the <hi>higheſt warrant</hi> that can poſſibly lend <hi>courage</hi> to a <hi>good action</hi>) directed it wholy againſt
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:114217:14"/>
                     <hi>Falſe Prophets,</hi> and no where reflected upon the <hi>Members</hi> of either <hi>Houſe,</hi> but where I maintain it to be unlawfull to <hi>ſpeak evill of dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities,</hi> to condemn it to the <hi>flame</hi> for ſpeaking ſuch <hi>Truths,</hi> as I could not leave <hi>unſpoken,</hi> unleſſe I had <hi>prevaricated</hi> with the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> will be ſo ſar from the <hi>reproach</hi> of a <hi>puniſhment,</hi> that 'twill en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe the <hi>eſteem</hi> and <hi>value</hi> of it from its <hi>ſufferings;</hi> and make it aſcend to heaven as the <hi>Angel</hi> in the <hi>Book</hi> of <hi>Judges</hi> did, in the <hi>breath,</hi> and <hi>ayre,</hi> and <hi>perfume</hi> of an acceptable <hi>ſacrifice</hi> to <hi>God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sir, As your <hi>ſhe-Diſciple</hi> did very much <hi>miſ-inform</hi> you, if <hi>ſhe</hi> told you that I endeavoured to <hi>incenſe an Officer of this Garriſon against you,</hi> ſo 'twas one <hi>Errour</hi> more in her (as upon juſt occaſion I ſhall demonſtrate to you) to tell you that I <hi>vented damnable Doctrines</hi> in her Company, <hi>which I was not able to maintain. She</hi> is my <hi>Gentle Adverſary,</hi> and I deſire <hi>ſhe</hi> ſhould know, that as I deſire not to fight <hi>ſerious duells</hi> with that <hi>unequall Sex,</hi> ſo when ever <hi>ſhe</hi> will again provoke me to a <hi>Diſpute</hi> (ſo it be not at Saint <hi>Maries,</hi> for S. <hi>Paul</hi> forbids <hi>women</hi> to argue in the <hi>Church</hi>) <hi>ſhe</hi> ſhall return with <hi>prizes,</hi> and I will confeſs my ſelf <hi>conquer'd.</hi> In the mean time, Sir, whither <hi>ſhe</hi> came to <hi>you,</hi> or <hi>you</hi> went to <hi>her,</hi> Her <hi>Sex</hi> puts me in mind of ſome <hi>falſe Teachers,</hi> not <hi>mention'd</hi> in my <hi>Sermon,</hi> but <hi>branded</hi> by Saint <hi>Paul,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Tim 3.6</note> * for <hi>creeping into houſes,</hi> and <hi>leading captive ſilly Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi> If your <hi>Intelligencer</hi> be one of theſe (as I ſhrewdly ſuſpect <hi>ſhe</hi> is) I ſhould be ſorry for thoſe <hi>Friends</hi> ſake in whoſe Acquaintance we <hi>both</hi> meet, that <hi>ſhe</hi> ſhould be lyable to the <hi>Character</hi> of ſuch <hi>ſilly women</hi> in the next <hi>verſe;</hi> where 'tis ſaid, <hi>That they were ever learning and never able to come to the knowledge of the Truth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>You proceed, and ſay, <hi>That you were in manifeſt Danger to looſe your Right to the Exerciſe of the Proteſtant Religion, whereupon the High Court of Parliament thought it fit to repell force by force.</hi> Sir, do not entertain me with your own <hi>falſe fears,</hi> and <hi>jealouſies;</hi> but <hi>demonſtrate</hi> to me that the <hi>King</hi> (for <hi>Him</hi> I preſume you mean) meant to <hi>extirpate</hi> the true <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion by the <hi>ſword,</hi> and to plant <hi>Popery</hi> in its ſtead, And you ſhall not more <hi>falſely</hi> charge me that I make the <hi>Parliament</hi> by ſuch a <hi>Reſiſtance</hi> to <hi>Denizon</hi> the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choran,</hi> then I ſhall <hi>truely</hi> pronounce the <hi>Kings party,</hi> in <hi>fighting</hi> for him to <hi>that end,</hi> guilty of a <hi>Mahumetan perſwaſion.</hi> In ſaying this, you exceedingly miſtake me if you think I contend for a <hi>Vorſtian Liberty,</hi> or am hereby a <hi>Friend to the Rebels in Ireland.</hi> Sir, I hope
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:114217:14"/>you can diſtinguiſh between mens <hi>Diſloyalty</hi> and <hi>Religion.</hi> As <hi>Rebels</hi> I hold it fit, if they will not otherway return to their <hi>Alleagance,</hi> that they be reduced by <hi>force.</hi> There is a <hi>right</hi> to their <hi>ſubjection</hi> purſued by ſuch a <hi>War,</hi> which makes all <hi>Armes</hi> warrantable which are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd for the recovery of ſuch a <hi>loſſe.</hi> But to think, that as they are <hi>Papiſts,</hi> nay, (Sir, I ſhall not ſhrink from my word) if they were outright <hi>Infidels,</hi> that the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> is to be impoſed upon them by <hi>force,</hi> is to make our ſelves <hi>guilty</hi> of all the <hi>hard Cenſures</hi> which have paſt upon the <hi>Spaniards Conqueſt</hi> of the <hi>Indians,</hi> where their <hi>Silver Mines</hi> were the true cauſe, and <hi>Religion</hi> the <hi>pretence.</hi> Notwithſtanding your <hi>Holy War,</hi> therefore, mention'd in the <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi> (which place I have conſidered, and find it as <hi>myſterious,</hi> as the <hi>pale</hi> or <hi>black Horſe</hi>) for ought you have ſaid in <hi>diſproof</hi> of it, I find not my ſelf tempted to deſert my <hi>Opinion:</hi> which is, <hi>That to come into the field with an Armed Goſpel, is not the way choſen by Chriſt to make Proſelytes.</hi> And, therefore Sir, I will not ſo much diſtruſt the <hi>Wiſdome,</hi> or <hi>Juſtice</hi> of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> that upon your <hi>bare Aſſertion, they will make me miſerable,</hi> becauſe I maintain that they cannot <hi>warrantably compell</hi> any man to be <hi>happy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Why the bare mention of your <hi>Scruple-houſe</hi> ſhould put you into ſuch a <hi>fit</hi> of <hi>ill language,</hi> as to pronounce me <hi>unworthy to carry the Books of the Reverend Divines after them,</hi> who met there to heal <hi>Doubts,</hi> or why my <hi>Carfax-Sermon</hi> ſhould contribute to the <hi>raging</hi> of <hi>that fit,</hi> I cannot reaſonably imagine. Sir, I have no mind to fight many <hi>Duells</hi> at <hi>Once;</hi> nor, (having received a <hi>challenge</hi> from no other but <hi>your ſelf</hi>) to ingage my ſelf with <hi>them</hi> by <hi>whom</hi> I have not been <hi>provok't.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Whither they be <hi>ungifted preachers,</hi> or <hi>Gifted Diſputants,</hi> is beſt known to themſelves. But, certainly, Sir, if the Report which was made to me (by <hi>ſome</hi> who brought both their <hi>underſtandings</hi> as well as <hi>Eares</hi> with t em to the <hi>famous meeting November</hi> 12.) be true, there was <hi>nothing</hi> ſo <hi>demonſtratively</hi> by them either <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected,</hi> or <hi>replyed</hi> as might incourage <hi>them,</hi> or their <hi>Hearers,</hi> to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve this <hi>peece</hi> of <hi>Popery,</hi> that they are <hi>unerring,</hi> and <hi>infallible</hi> in the <hi>chair:</hi> pray, Sir, do not think my <hi>Famous pride,</hi> or <hi>ſelf-conceited<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> (which you ſay hath <hi>provoked</hi> you to <hi>break</hi> your <hi>chaines,</hi> and <hi>to let looſe your pen,</hi> that you might <hi>whip</hi> me into <hi>Humility</hi>) hath prompted me to ſay this.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:114217:15"/>
Had you named the <hi>Reverend perſons whoſe Books I am not worthy to carry after them,</hi> ſo they be <hi>Greek</hi> or <hi>Latine Books,</hi> and <hi>thoſe</hi> well underſtood by them, perhaps I ſhould have expreſt a greater <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Humility</hi> then you are aware of, and have been content (though one of the <hi>new Doctors</hi> yet by the <hi>ſecond Subſcription</hi> of your <hi>Letter</hi> but a <hi>Maſter of Art</hi>) to ſit a while at the <hi>feet</hi> of ſuch <hi>learned Gamaliel's.</hi> But ſpeaking <hi>indefinitely</hi> as you do, I hope Sir, for twenty years <hi>ſtudy</hi> ſake in this <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity,</hi> (where I have learnt to diſtinguiſh the <hi>letters</hi> of the <hi>Greek Alphabet,</hi> and at firſt ſight do know that it would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get a <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, or <hi>quarrell</hi> among the <hi>Vowells,</hi> if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> in a <hi>word</hi> ſhould uſurp the place of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>) you will find me a <hi>nobler imployment</hi> then to <hi>carry Books</hi> after <hi>Them</hi> who count <hi>Liberaries Superfluous, humane, Secular</hi> Things; And think a <hi>Miniſter,</hi> not <hi>Miniſter of Goſpel,</hi> (as your <hi>Scribe</hi> hath <hi>twice</hi> erred in the <hi>tranſcription</hi> of your <hi>letter,</hi> in a <hi>vowell</hi> very <hi>fatall</hi> to you) needs no other <hi>furniture</hi> but the <hi>Spirit, Cottons Concordance,</hi> and the <hi>Engliſh Bible</hi> without the <hi>Apocrypha.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sir, I am ſorry the <hi>Fit</hi> which the <hi>mention</hi> of the <hi>Scruple-houſe</hi> did put you into, ſhould be <hi>increaſed</hi> by the <hi>mention</hi> of a <hi>Dark Roome.</hi> There goes a Story of <hi>one</hi> who had <hi>taſted</hi> a while of <hi>Bedlam,</hi> and was at length, by the help of <hi>Diſcipline, dyet,</hi> and <hi>Phyſick,</hi> cured of his <hi>Diſtraction;</hi> yet not ſo perfectly, but that ſtill when he came within the ſight of the place, his <hi>fancy</hi> remembred him of his <hi>old Diſtemper,</hi> and tempted him to do ſomething which required a <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond cure.</hi> I ſpeak not this <hi>parable</hi> to upbraid any with an <hi>infirmity</hi> which is unavoydably <hi>naturall</hi> to them, and no way contracted from the <hi>pride,</hi> or <hi>irregularity</hi> of their own <hi>Wills;</hi> But if you have read <hi>Tully's Paradoxes,</hi> you may remember, Sir, that <hi>he</hi> there maintains the <hi>Opinion</hi> of the <hi>Stoicks,</hi> that not onely <hi>they</hi> whoſe <hi>chaines</hi> and <hi>fetters,</hi> proclaim them <hi>diſtempered,</hi> but that all <hi>fooliſh,</hi> over <hi>paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate</hi> men are to be reckoned into the number of thoſe who are to be <hi>cured</hi> by <hi>manacles,</hi> and <hi>chaynes:</hi> pray Sir, do not take it ill, if (being as you ſay a <hi>Poet</hi>) I cite a <hi>Poet</hi> who was of this <hi>Opinion;</hi> but main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains it like a <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> (I will not ſay a <hi>School Divine.</hi>) And ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving inſiſted in <hi>verſe</hi> upon <hi>Covetouſneſs</hi> as <hi>one, Ambition</hi> as <hi>another,</hi> The <hi>love</hi> of <hi>beauty</hi> either in <hi>reall</hi> or <hi>painted faces,</hi> as <hi>another Species</hi> of <hi>Madneſs,</hi> He concludes in <hi>Anger,</hi> and ſayes, <hi>Ira furor brevis eſt;</hi> that is, That the <hi>Cholerick man,</hi> during the <hi>fit</hi> of his <hi>choler,</hi> is
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:114217:15"/>in a <hi>ſhort phrenzy.</hi> That which <hi>Seneca, Tully,</hi> and <hi>Horace,</hi> called <hi>madneſs,</hi> (though not the <hi>other more naturall,</hi> (which I ſhould be <hi>uncharitable</hi> to object to you) <hi>you</hi> by this <hi>letter</hi> (eſpecially the <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry part</hi> of it) have given me very juſtifiable cauſe to apply to you, who (as all <hi>dispaſſionated men</hi> may judge) have fulfill'd the <hi>Poets de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition</hi> of <hi>Madneſs</hi> upon <hi>your ſelf</hi> in <hi>all</hi> the <hi>parts</hi> of it but <hi>one,</hi> which is, that your <hi>Anger</hi> againſt me is not <hi>furor Brevis,</hi> a <hi>ſhort di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction,</hi> but extends from the word <hi>Scruple-houſe</hi> to the <hi>End</hi> of your <hi>Letter.</hi> For firſt, Sir, in Language almoſt as <hi>unclean,</hi> as the ſin of uncleanneſs it ſelf, you endeavour to raiſe a <hi>Suſpition</hi> upon me in the world as if I had been more <hi>familiar</hi> then I ſhould with <hi>light Women in dark Roomes:</hi> Sir, beſides the <hi>poverty</hi> of <hi>your wit,</hi> and <hi>quibling Antitheſes</hi> of <hi>Expreſſion,</hi> (to which I finde you in other places of your <hi>letter</hi> very <hi>ſubject</hi>) I am not afraid (with all the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence</hi> of an <hi>Innocent man</hi>) to tell you, That as I never was an <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi> to that <hi>Sex,</hi> ſo I never converſt with any of them <hi>ſingle,</hi> or in a <hi>dark Congregation,</hi> ſo <hi>looſely,</hi> to deſerve to have the <hi>ſlander</hi> faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned upon me, which <hi>Tertullian,</hi> and <hi>Minutius Faelix</hi> from him, ſay was laboured to be ſtuck upon the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> of thoſe <hi>Times,</hi> which was, That they uſed to meet in <hi>Conventicles,</hi> where their cuſtome was, after the <hi>end</hi> of the <hi>Sermon,</hi> to put out the <hi>Candles,</hi> and then to commit <hi>Folly,</hi> the <hi>holy</hi> with the <hi>holy.</hi> Sir, in plain Termes, (How <hi>blameable</hi> ſoever other <hi>Errours,</hi> or <hi>vanities</hi> of my <hi>life</hi> may make me ſtand in the preſence of <hi>God,</hi> who upon a <hi>true Repentance,</hi> Sir, is not ſo <hi>Fatally</hi> tyed to the <hi>Spindle</hi> of <hi>abſolute Reprobation,</hi> as not to keep his <hi>promiſe,</hi> and to ſeal <hi>mercifull pardons,</hi> yet) in this <hi>particular,</hi> my <hi>known Converſation</hi> in this <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity,</hi> and all other <hi>places,</hi> bids me <hi>defie</hi> you; And challeng not only your ſelf, but the <hi>preciſeſt</hi> of your <hi>Informers,</hi> either <hi>heer,</hi> or <hi>any where</hi> elſe, (who uſe not to ſuffer the <hi>looks, Geſtures,</hi> or thoughts of any who are not of their <hi>Tribe,</hi> much leſs <hi>notorious matter of Fact,</hi> to ſcape <hi>unqueſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi>) to appear in an <hi>accuſation</hi> againſt me; where it ſhall be <hi>proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly,</hi> not <hi>conjecturally</hi> proved, that I have been <hi>frail</hi> with the <hi>frail Sex</hi> either <hi>holy</hi> or <hi>profane.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sir, all they of that <hi>ſoft Sex,</hi> with whom I have converſt, have accuſed me of too great <hi>ſeverity,</hi> and <hi>ruggedneſs,</hi> towards them, but <hi>you</hi> are the <hi>firſt,</hi> who ever endeavoured to make me guilty of being too <hi>amorouſly affected.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:114217:16"/>
Next, ſir, However you may tell me that you <hi>have not ſo loſt your Reaſon, or Logick, but that you, (the meanest who appears for the Parliament) are ready to take up the Gauntlet which I threw down, and to anſwer the challenge which I firſt ſounded in the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit;</hi> yet, certainly, They who ſhall read that <hi>paſſage</hi> of my <hi>Sermon,</hi> where I ſay, <hi>That if I were preſently to enter into a diſpute with the greateſt Patriarch among theſe Prophets, who</hi> (notwithſtanding that which I ſaid before) <hi>will ſtill perverſly ſtrive to prove that our Church ſtood in ſuch need of Reformation, that the growing ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitions of it could not poſſibly be expiated, but by ſo much Civill War, I ſhould not doubt with modeſty enough to prove to him back again, that all ſuch irrationall Arguments, as have onely his zeal for their Logick are compoſed of untemper'd Morter:</hi> And ſhall compare the <hi>wilde Torrent</hi> of <hi>ill language,</hi> with which the <hi>furious remainder</hi> of your <hi>paragraph</hi> over-flows, with the <hi>Sober Web,</hi> and <hi>Compoſition</hi> of my <hi>Sermon,</hi> which you there think no worthier of, then of a <hi>Triobolar Ballad,</hi> They will finde that you have ſaid no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the <hi>progreſs</hi> of at leaſt <hi>forty Folio-lines</hi> together, which ſhews not that your <hi>Reaſon</hi> aſſiſted not your <hi>pen.</hi> One <hi>paſſage</hi> I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe (like a <hi>lucide Intervall</hi>) hath ſome taſte of <hi>ſobriety,</hi> and not <hi>ſhort fury</hi> in it; <hi>which is,</hi> that how meanly ſo ever you think you may ſpeak of <hi>me,</hi> yet you think you are to make a more honourable mention of the <hi>Author</hi> of the <hi>Practicall Catechiſm.</hi> That <hi>learned Doctor,</hi> Sir, I am acquainted with, but not ſo <hi>inwardly</hi> as that <hi>he</hi> ſhould contribute to the <hi>interlining</hi> any <hi>letter</hi> I write to <hi>you;</hi> or ſhould ſuggeſt to me what <hi>he,</hi> not <hi>I,</hi> think fit to be maintain'd. I wiſh your <hi>lucid intervall</hi> had been as long as your <hi>fit;</hi> For, then I perſwade my ſelf you would never have ſuſpected that <hi>he</hi> did <hi>over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>look</hi> my <hi>letter,</hi> or <hi>adviſed me to contend</hi> for the <hi>lawfulneſs</hi> of <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacy,</hi> becauſe he was <hi>preſent at the ſad debate at Vxbridge.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>What you mean when you ſay, <hi>That if the learned Doctor hath any thing to object againſt you, He knows your mind, and</hi> (being none of the <hi>new Doctors,</hi> who you preſume are <hi>Infants</hi>) <hi>is able to ſpeak for Himſelf,</hi> I cannot poſſibly divine: unleſs by this <hi>Oraculous Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion,</hi> you would have him underſtand you ready to enter into a <hi>ſecond conflict</hi> with him, and would put <hi>me</hi> to the <hi>mean imployment</hi> to convey your <hi>challenge.</hi> Sir, if I know that Doctor well, you had beſt content your ſelf with <hi>me,</hi> who am a more <hi>poeticall adverſary;</hi> &amp; whoſe <hi>weapons,</hi> you know, when they <hi>ſtrike</hi> moſt, being ſheath'd in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:114217:16"/>
                     <hi>Roſes,</hi> ought to be <hi>terrible</hi> to <hi>none</hi> but <hi>ſuch,</hi> whoſe <hi>buying</hi> &amp; <hi>ſelling Conſciences</hi> (like the <hi>money-changers</hi> in the <hi>Goſpel</hi>) wil drive them out of the <hi>Temple</hi> at the ſight of a <hi>whip</hi> made of <hi>ſtraws</hi> and <hi>ruſhes.</hi> Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs, Sir, if you be ſo <hi>fruitfully quarrelſome,</hi> that you think your <hi>leiſure</hi> will ſerve you to hold combate with us <hi>both,</hi> let me deſire you to hold this Opinion of <hi>us,</hi> that as I ſhal at no time <hi>recruit</hi> my ſelf fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <hi>him</hi> as an <hi>Oratour,</hi> ſo <hi>he</hi> is too good a <hi>ſchollar</hi> to need my <hi>aſſiſtance</hi> as a <hi>Poet.</hi> This word <hi>Poet,</hi> I do obſerve, through the whole <hi>phrenzy</hi> of your <hi>letter,</hi> you ſtrive to make uſe of in a <hi>diſgraceful ſenſe;</hi> And object it to me as a <hi>Reproach</hi> that the <hi>Muſes</hi> are my <hi>Friends.</hi> In one place you call me a <hi>Cretian Prophet,</hi> That is, (according to your <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>) a <hi>Poet;</hi> In another place you tell me, that <hi>onely the few places of ſcripture which I have miſapplied in my Sermon, can preſerve it from paſſing among the penny-merchandizes of thoſe that ſel Ballads.</hi> In your <hi>next paragraph,</hi> (where you challenge me to <hi>diſpute</hi> with you in <hi>Engliſh</hi> at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Maries,</hi> as <hi>Mr Erbury</hi> did) one of your <hi>Arguments</hi> to move me to that <hi>frantick enterprize</hi> is, becauſe I am an <hi>Engliſh Poet,</hi> and <hi>have been not only addicted to Playes, but have ſhuffled my Mother-tongue Verſes, with other Verſes publiſht in more learned languages, in the ſame Book Printed by the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity-Printer.</hi> Firſt, ſir, though the <hi>ungentleneſs</hi> of your <hi>ſtile,</hi> and <hi>Expreſſions,</hi> do ſufficiently teſtifie that neither the <hi>Muſes,</hi> nor <hi>Graces aſſiſted</hi> at your <hi>Birth,</hi> yet I hope you are not ſuch an enemy to <hi>numbers,</hi> to think <hi>poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Superſtitious,</hi> and therefore to be turn'd with <hi>Imagery</hi> out of the <hi>Church.</hi> If you do, you will compell me to call <hi>Nazianzen</hi> in to my <hi>Ayde;</hi> who, beſides his writing of a <hi>Play</hi> (if <hi>Eraſmus</hi> have not miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numbred them) hath written thirty thouſand <hi>Heroick, Jambick, Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decaſyllable, Elegiack,</hi> and other <hi>verſes. Tertullian,</hi> Sir, you know hath confuted <hi>Marcion</hi> in <hi>Verſe;</hi> and <hi>Syneſius</hi> thought it as great a glory to be called a <hi>good Poet,</hi> as <hi>ſome</hi> who wrote in <hi>proſe</hi> did to be called <hi>fathers of the Church.</hi> I wil not repeat a <hi>peece</hi> of <hi>Proſper</hi> to you nor tel you what S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> hath ſaid in the praif of <hi>Virgil.</hi> To be a <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian Prophet,</hi> that is in <hi>your</hi> ſenſe, a <hi>lying Poet,</hi> but in al theirs who un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the <hi>firſt C. of Titus,</hi> an <hi>Evil Beaſt,</hi> and a <hi>falfe Prophet</hi>) Is I confeſſe a crime. But then, ſir, as one excellently ſayes in his <hi>Defence of Poeſie,</hi> This is a kind of <hi>Poetry</hi> which belongs to <hi>thoſe</hi> who <hi>lye in proſe</hi> as wel as <hi>thoſe</hi> who <hi>fain in Verſe.</hi> For <hi>Pliny,</hi> when he ſpeaks of <hi>men</hi> with <hi>one foot,</hi> whoſe <hi>breadth</hi> interpoſed between them and the <hi>ſun,</hi> ſhades their <hi>whole body,</hi> to be as great a <hi>poet</hi> as <hi>Ovid,</hi> when he ſpeaks of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:114217:17"/>a <hi>Virgin</hi> transformed into a <hi>Laurell,</hi> ſo, Sir, when <hi>you,</hi> (contrary to the direct <hi>minde,</hi> and <hi>Expreſſions</hi> of my <hi>Sermon</hi>) <hi>fain</hi> that to be ſpoken of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> which is onely ſpoken againſt <hi>Falſe Prophets.</hi> you are a far <hi>greater Poet</hi> then I have yet ſhewn my ſelf either upon the <hi>Stage</hi> at <hi>Black-Fryers,</hi> or in any <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity Book</hi> here in <hi>Oxford.</hi> Next, ſir, I was never ſo addicted to <hi>Engliſh Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi> but that in the ſame <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity Book</hi> I had <hi>Latine Verſes</hi> too; And the Reaſon why I wrote in <hi>both Languages</hi> was, becauſe I was prompted to it by my <hi>Obedience</hi> to their <hi>Commands,</hi> who had <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> over me, and thought <hi>Engliſh</hi> the <hi>fitter Language</hi> for that <hi>part</hi> of the <hi>Court,</hi> whoſe <hi>Sex</hi> doth make it a <hi>Soleciſm</hi> to be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to in <hi>Latine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Laſtly, Sir, As for your Arguments to give you one of Mr <hi>Yerbury's Meetings,</hi> at Saint <hi>Maries;</hi> I. <hi>Becauſe my Sermon Preacht there is Engliſh,</hi> next, <hi>becauſe you conceive that to be the readieſt courſe to undeceive the people who underſtand not Latine;</hi> thirdly, <hi>becauſe I am an Engliſh Poet;</hi> if you think I have not ſufficiently anſwered them in my <hi>two former letters</hi> to you, I deſire you once more to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, if I ſhould have conſented to that courſe, whither <hi>you,</hi> as well as <hi>I,</hi> in the opinion of <hi>diſcreet men,</hi> might not have indangered our ſelves to have that <hi>half verſe</hi> in <hi>Horace</hi> applyed to us, <hi>Aut inſanit Home, aut verſus facit,</hi> That either we are <hi>both mad,</hi> or <hi>both Poets,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The way to avoyd ſuch an Imputation, in a <hi>Time</hi> of liberty, where every body may ſay what they liſt, is for us to ſtand conſtantly to the more <hi>Academicall Propoſition</hi> I made you; which was, to meet at <hi>Latine Weapons in the Divinity School.</hi> Where; ſir, not <hi>agreeing</hi> upon the <hi>true ſtate of the Queſtions before hand,</hi> (For if we <hi>agree before hand,</hi> nothing will be left us to diſpute) if you pleaſe, the <hi>Queſtion</hi> ſhall be <hi>that</hi> which concludes your <hi>Letter;</hi> That is, <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacy,</hi> which, how far 'tis, or 'tis not to be defended to be <hi>Jure divino</hi> ſhall then appear. In the mean time, ſir, as I can by no means allow that <hi>victory,</hi> and <hi>Succeſs,</hi> are alwayes the <hi>true ſignes</hi> of a <hi>Right cauſe,</hi> (Becauſe, <hi>The Lord of Hoſts, who,</hi> you ſay, <hi>hath broken all our forces,</hi> is ſometimes falſely thought to <hi>aſſiſt,</hi> when in truth he doth only <hi>permit</hi>) ſo, Sir when you write next to me, let me requeſt you to keep your <hi>promiſe;</hi> which is, to deal with me <hi>rationally</hi> for the <hi>Matter,</hi> and <hi>Spiritually,</hi> that is, like a <hi>Divine</hi> for the <hi>language</hi> and <hi>forme.</hi> Otherwiſe, ſir, though I have long ſince learnt from the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:114217:17"/>
                     <hi>beſt Maſter,</hi> that when I am <hi>reviled,</hi> I am not to <hi>revile againe,</hi> yet, inſtead of a <hi>Conference,</hi> meeting with nothing but <hi>Invectives,</hi> 'tis poſſible you may ſo farre provoke me from my <hi>mild temper,</hi> that the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> expreſſion in <hi>Lucians Nigrinus</hi> may be veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied upon me; <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. The <hi>Engliſh</hi> of it will endure the <hi>publick teſt;</hi> to which if you will be pleaſed to <hi>ſubmit</hi> your <hi>Letters</hi> with the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs that I am content to <hi>ſubmit mine,</hi> I doubt not but the world will judge, that as you have not yet <hi>confuted,</hi> ſo you have very unchriſtianly <hi>injured</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>From my Chamber,</hi>
                        <date>Jan. 23. 1646.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>The</hi> Author <hi>of the</hi> Sermon <hi>againſt</hi> Falſe Prophets, J. MAYNE.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>To this <hi>Anſwer</hi> (in which the <hi>Reader</hi> may ſee, I have not much digreſt from the <hi>copy</hi> which was before me, but have proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned my <hi>Defence</hi> to every conſiderable <hi>particular</hi> of M. <hi>Cheynels</hi> Charge) at the <hi>end</hi> of ſix dayes was return'd this <hi>Reply.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>If I had not anſwered you according to your <hi>folly,</hi> you would have been <hi>wife</hi> in your <hi>owne conceit;</hi> but if I ſhould againe anſwer you according to <hi>your folly,</hi> I feare I ſhould become too <hi>like</hi> unto you, <hi>Prov.</hi> 26.4, 5. I told you that I did <hi>let looſe my pen,</hi> that you might ſee how <hi>eaſie</hi> it is to anſwer you with a <hi>running pen,</hi> nay a <hi>running negligence</hi> in the leſs <hi>ſerious part</hi> of the day; I did <hi>let fly</hi> ſo many <hi>quibbles</hi> that you might ſmell the <hi>ſtench</hi> of your owne <hi>elaborate folly;</hi> glad I am that you have <hi>cenſured</hi> me for <hi>imitating</hi> of you, I hope you will now be at leiſure to <hi>cenſure</hi> your <hi>ſelfe,</hi> for <hi>ſetting</hi> me ſo <hi>foule</hi> a <hi>copy;</hi> doe but read over your <hi>owne Sermons</hi> and <hi>Letters,</hi> and ſuppoſe they were <hi>mine,</hi> and then ſeriouſly and impartially paſs your ſentence on them, and I dare ſay you will be a gainer by this <hi>conflict.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I am very much pleaſed with your faire condeſcenſion to have all things in controverſie <hi>rationally</hi> and <hi>ſpiritually examined.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. Sir, you did as I conceive preach in defence of <hi>all images</hi> ſet up in any <hi>Chappell</hi> in the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity;</hi> you know there are divers <hi>Images</hi> of ſome <hi>perſons</hi> in the <hi>glorious Trinity</hi> ſet up in ſome
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:114217:18"/>
                     <hi>Chappels</hi> within this <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity:</hi> You muſt then acknowledge <hi>all Images</hi> of that <hi>ſort</hi> ought to be <hi>taken downe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Imago nos tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tism<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t memori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ale excitat uti Jeſuitae paſſim. Dico non eſſe tam certum in Eccleſiâ an ſint faciendae ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genes Dei, ſive Trin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tatis, q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>â Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ſti &amp; ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto is hoc <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nim ad ſidem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>erti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t, tilud e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t in opi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>one. <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>lla. deim g l. 2 c. 8</hi> J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>animata ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualem quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam virt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>em exconſecratione adipiſcuntu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>Tho. p. 3. q. 83. art 3.</hi> Deum imagini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus inhabitantè colunt, Deum cut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m virtu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſtam ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>tua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> ret<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quando ſive <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>be eſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m. Caſetanus hac in re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nc Genti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libus quidem ſanientio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tur.</note> You are not perſwaded by any <hi>Scriptures</hi> which I have cited, but <hi>nature hath taught you</hi> (ſo pure is your <hi>nature</hi>) <hi>that it is a breach of the ſecond Commandement to draw a picture of God:</hi> (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe that <hi>fancy</hi>) the <hi>Schoolmen</hi> whom you prefer before the <hi>teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies</hi> cited out of the <hi>Word,</hi> have taught you that it is not onely <hi>ſinfull,</hi> but <hi>impoſsible</hi> to draw any <hi>picture</hi> of <hi>God.</hi> But, be pleaſed to conſider that the <hi>Scriptures</hi> are a <hi>perfect</hi> (nay indeed the <hi>onely All-ſufficient perfect</hi>) <hi>Rule,</hi> &amp; therefore you need not goe about to patch up the <hi>rule</hi> with the <hi>low generall dictates of nature</hi> &amp; <hi>School-men,</hi> you may ſtudy the <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>llian Art.</hi> &amp; fill your <hi>braine</hi> with <hi>Sebund's fancyes,</hi> but my <hi>Schoole-men</hi> (as you call them) are the <hi>beſt Tutors,</hi> &amp; the <hi>beſt Schollars.</hi> If you prove that is is <hi>impoſsible</hi> to <hi>picture God,</hi> you doe not touch the <hi>point</hi> in <hi>Controverſie,</hi> for <hi>vaine men</hi> will fancy and endeavour to doe, that which is <hi>impoſsible</hi> for to be done. Beleeve it Sir, <hi>they</hi> who had conſulted as many <hi>Muſes,</hi> and courted as many <hi>Graces as you</hi> have done, and were able to <hi>demonſtrate</hi> out of their <hi>Poets</hi> that we are <hi>Gods off-ſpring,</hi> yet were not able without the help of <hi>divine Revelation</hi> to infer, from thence, that the <hi>Godhead is not like to Gold,</hi> as you may ſee it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincingly proved; <hi>Act</hi> 17.29. <hi>For as much then as we are the off-ſpring of God, we ought not to thinke that the Godhead is like to Gold or Silver, or ſtone graven by Art or mans device,</hi> I dare not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore make the <hi>Schoolmen</hi> my <hi>Judges</hi> in this <hi>weighty point,</hi> and I beleeve you cannot prove them to be <hi>Judges</hi> in <hi>any point</hi> which concernes the <hi>Myſtery</hi> of <hi>faith</hi> or the <hi>power</hi> of <hi>godlineſs,</hi> but enough of that.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The word <hi>(thereupon)</hi> is ſometimes <hi>Illative,</hi> ſometimes <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinative,</hi> you are ſufficiently <hi>anſwered;</hi> but let me adde, that if no <hi>Image</hi> is like <hi>God,</hi> then ſure thoſe <hi>Images,</hi> which are not made to <hi>repreſent God,</hi> and yet are by <hi>Idolatours</hi> turned into <hi>Idols,</hi> and worſhipped as if they were <hi>divine,</hi> cannot reaſonably be <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended.</hi> Sir, I muſt gueſs at your <hi>meaning,</hi> becauſe I beleeve you have omitted two or three words (ſuch is your <hi>running negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence</hi>) which ſhould help to make your <hi>ſophiſticall criticiſme</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect ſenſe.</p>
                  <p>Truly Sir, if it be ſo high a fault to <hi>picture God:</hi> I may juſtly
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:114217:18"/>wonder that any <hi>picture</hi> of a <hi>Saint</hi> turned into an <hi>Idoll</hi> ſhould be retained and pleaded for by <hi>any man</hi> that pretends to be a <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant,</hi> and if it be <hi>impoſsible</hi> to <hi>picture God,</hi> it is alſo <hi>impoſsible</hi> to <hi>picture God-man.</hi> And I beleeve that you will acknowledge our <hi>Mediatour</hi> to be <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. That the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Images</hi> cannot be put in the <hi>ſcales</hi> of a <hi>compariſon</hi> in point of fitneſs to be <hi>preſerved,</hi> is a truth written with a <hi>Sun-beame;</hi> Sir, I never durſt argue from the <hi>abuſe</hi> of a thing againſt the <hi>uſe</hi> of it, if the thing be <hi>neceſſary;</hi> But the <hi>Sun</hi> is <hi>neceſſary,</hi> and <hi>Images</hi> are <hi>not neceſſary, ergo</hi> there is no parity of reaſon between the termes of your <hi>compariſon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. It appeares to me by your <hi>ſhifting fallacy,</hi> that you make <hi>Copes</hi> as <hi>neceſsary</hi> as <hi>clean Linnen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6. You will never be able to prove, that all, that the <hi>prelates</hi> and their <hi>Faction</hi> have borrowed out of the <hi>Miſſall, Ritualls, Breviary Pontificall</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> are to be found in any <hi>Lyturgie</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by the <hi>Primitive Church;</hi> And I would intreat you to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, whether <hi>they,</hi> who doe profeſs a ſeperation from the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> can in reaſon receive and imbrace ſuch <hi>traſh</hi> and <hi>trumpery.</hi> And yet though you would willingly be eſteemed a <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> I find you very unwilling to part with any thing which the <hi>Prelates</hi> have borrowed from the <hi>Court</hi> (rather the <hi>Church</hi>) of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">7. Your next <hi>Paragraph</hi> doth concerne <hi>Tradition;</hi> I ſhall give you leave to preferre the <hi>conſtant and univerſall conſent of the Church of Chriſt in all ages, before the reaſon of any ſingle man;</hi> but Sir, you doe very ill to call the <hi>teſtimony</hi> of the <hi>ſpirit ſpeaking</hi> in the <hi>word</hi> to the <hi>Conſcience</hi> of <hi>private men,</hi> a <hi>private ſpirit;</hi> I thinke you are more <hi>profane</hi> in the ſtating of this <hi>point</hi> then <hi>Bellarmine himſelfe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="8">8. You have not yet proved that any <hi>Prelate</hi> can challenge the <hi>Sole power of Ordination</hi> and <hi>Jurisdiction Jure divino.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="9">9. I ſhould be glad to know for how many yeares you will juſtifie the <hi>purity</hi> of the <hi>Doctrine, Diſcipline</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> in <hi>England.</hi> I beleeve the <hi>Doctrine, Diſcipline</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> of the <hi>Prelaticall faction</hi> whom you call the <hi>Church,</hi> was not <hi>excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent,</hi> if you reckon from 1630. to 1640. and that is <hi>time enough</hi> for men of <hi>our time</hi> for to examine. I beleeve that you will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:114217:19"/>that the <hi>Prelates</hi> did lay an <hi>Oſtraciſme</hi> upon <hi>thoſe</hi> who did <hi>oppoſe them;</hi> who were in the right both in the point of <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> we ſhall in due time diſpute. Though <hi>Prelacy it ſelfe</hi> be an <hi>uſurpation,</hi> yet there were many other <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croachments</hi> which may juſtly be called <hi>Prelaticall uſurpations,</hi> and the <hi>Parliament</hi> hath ſufficiently declared its <hi>judgement</hi> in this <hi>point,</hi> they have clearly <hi>proved</hi> that <hi>Prelacy</hi> had taken ſuch a <hi>deepe root</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> and had ſuch a <hi>deſtructive influence,</hi> not only into the <hi>pernicious evills</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> but <hi>Civill State,</hi> that the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>right reaſon</hi> (even <hi>Salus populi quae ſuprema lex eſt</hi>) did command and compell them to take away both <hi>roote and branch;</hi> you may diſpute that <hi>point</hi> with <hi>them;</hi> Sir, you cannot prove that <hi>Prelacy is an Order of the Church, as ancient as the Chriſtian Church it ſelf, and made venerable by the never interrupted reception of it in all Ages of the Church but ours.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="10">10. I am no <hi>Turkiſh Prophet,</hi> I never <hi>preacht</hi> any <hi>piece</hi> of the <hi>Alchoran</hi> for <hi>good Doctrine,</hi> much leſs did I ever make it a <hi>piece</hi> of the <hi>Goſpell;</hi> all that I ſay is this, that <hi>Chriſtians incorporated</hi> in a <hi>Civill State</hi> may make uſe of <hi>Civill</hi> and <hi>naturall means</hi> for their outward <hi>ſafety.</hi> And that the <hi>Parliament</hi> hath a <hi>Legall power</hi> more then <hi>ſufficient</hi> to prevent and reſtrain <hi>Tyranny.</hi> Finally, the <hi>Parliament</hi> hath power to defend that <hi>Civill right</hi> which we have to exerciſe the <hi>true Proteſtant Religion,</hi> this laſt point is ſure of higheſt conſequence becauſe it concernes <hi>Gods</hi> immediate <hi>honour,</hi> and the <hi>Peoples temporall</hi> and <hi>eternall</hi> good. Pray Sir, ſhew me if you can, why, he who ſaith the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in <hi>Ireland</hi> may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend their <hi>Civill right</hi> for the free exerciſe of their <hi>Religion,</hi> againſt the <hi>furious aſſaults</hi> of the <hi>bloudie Rebells,</hi> doth by that aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion proclaime himſelf a <hi>Turke,</hi> and <hi>Deniſon the Alchoran;</hi> you talke of the <hi>Papiſts Religion,</hi> Sir, their <hi>faith is faction,</hi> their <hi>Religion</hi> is <hi>Rebellion,</hi> they think they are obliged in conſcience, to put <hi>Heretiques</hi> to the ſword, this <hi>Religion</hi> is <hi>deſtructive</hi> to every <hi>Civill State</hi> into which true <hi>Proteſtants</hi> are <hi>incorporated,</hi> &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I cannot but wonder at your extravagancy in this <hi>point.</hi> Sir, Who was it that would have impoſed a <hi>Popiſh Service Book</hi> upon <hi>Scotland</hi> by <hi>force</hi> of <hi>Armes?</hi> You preſume that I conceive the <hi>King</hi> had an intent to <hi>extirpate</hi> the <hi>Proteſtant Religion;</hi> Sir, I am ſure that <hi>they</hi> who did <hi>ſeduce</hi> or <hi>over-awe</hi> the <hi>King,</hi> had ſuch a
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:114217:19"/>
                     <hi>deſigne.</hi> I doe not beleeve that the <hi>Queene</hi> and her <hi>Agents</hi> (the <hi>Papiſts</hi> in <hi>England</hi> who were certainly <hi>confederate</hi> with the <hi>Iriſh Rebells</hi>) had any intent to <hi>ſettle</hi> the true <hi>Proteſtant Religion;</hi> &amp; you cannot but beleeve that their intent was, to <hi>extirpate</hi> the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion</hi> by the <hi>ſword,</hi> and to plant <hi>Popery</hi> inits ſtead; I know <hi>Chriſt</hi> doth make <hi>proſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ites,</hi> and breake the <hi>ſpirituall power</hi> of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> by his <hi>word</hi> and <hi>ſpirit,</hi> for <hi>Antichriſt</hi> is caſt out of the hearts and conſciences of men by the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of the <hi>Lord Jeſus;</hi> but <hi>Chriſt</hi> is <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Nations</hi> as well as <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Saints,</hi> and will breake the <hi>temporall power</hi> of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> by <hi>Civill</hi> and <hi>naturall meanes.</hi> If <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Delinquents</hi> are in readineſs to <hi>reſiſt</hi> or <hi>aſſault</hi> the <hi>Parliament</hi> by <hi>Armes,</hi> how can the <hi>Parliament</hi> be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended or <hi>Delinquents</hi> puniſhed but by force of <hi>Armes?</hi> I know men muſt be <hi>converted</hi> by a <hi>ſpirituall perſwaſion,</hi> but they may be <hi>terrified</hi> by force of <hi>Armes</hi> from perſecution. All that I ſay, is, the <hi>Parliament</hi> may repell <hi>force</hi> with <hi>force,</hi> and if men were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid to profeſs the <hi>truth</hi> becauſe of the <hi>Queenes Army.</hi> and are now as fearfull to maintaine <hi>errours</hi> for feare of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> the ſcales are even, and we may (by ſtudy, conference, diſputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and prayer for a bleſsing upon all) be <hi>convinced,</hi> and <hi>convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> by the <hi>undenyable demonſtrations of the Spirit;</hi> Sir, this is my <hi>perſwaſion,</hi> and therefore I am ſure far from that <hi>Mahumetan per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion</hi> of which I am unjuſtly accuſed.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. I am glad that you ſpeake out, and give light to your <hi>darke roome;</hi> I did not accuſe you of <hi>Convenicles.</hi> I beleeve you <hi>hate</hi> thoſe <hi>Chriſtian meetings</hi> which <hi>Tertullian</hi> &amp; <hi>Minutius, Pliny</hi> and <hi>others</hi> ſpeake of; we had <hi>lights</hi> and <hi>witneſſes</hi> good ſtore at our <hi>meetings.</hi> And as for your conceit, that I deſerve to be in <hi>Bedlam,</hi> becauſe of the <hi>predominancy of my pride and paſsion, and the irregularity of my will;</hi> Sir, I confeſs that I deſerve to be in <hi>Hell,</hi> a worſe place then <hi>Bedlam;</hi> and if you ſcoffe at me for this acknowledgement, I ſhall ſay as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> did, <hi>Irrideant me arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantes, &amp; nondum ſalubritèr proſtrati, &amp; eliſi à te Deus meus, ega tamen confiteor dedecora mea in laude tua.</hi> Sir, be not too <hi>confident</hi> of the <hi>ſtrength</hi> of your <hi>wit,</hi> make a <hi>good uſe</hi> of it, or elſe you may quickly come to have as <hi>litle wit</hi> as you conceive, <hi>God</hi> hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on <hi>me.</hi> 1. Doe you beleeve that your <hi>nature</hi> is <hi>corrupt?</hi> 2. And doth not a <hi>wanton wit</hi> make the <hi>heart effeminate?</hi> 3. Did
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:114217:20"/>you never <hi>converſe</hi> with any woman of <hi>light behaviour?</hi> rub up your <hi>memory.</hi> 4. <hi>Superſtitious perſons</hi> are uſually <hi>laſcivious,</hi> I could tell you more, but I ſpare you. 5. Are you more <hi>tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate</hi> then the <hi>Diſciples</hi> to whom <hi>Chriſt</hi> gave that <hi>caveat, Luk.</hi> 21.34? you may then apply your ſelfe to <hi>Prayer and Faſting;</hi> doe not ſay that this is a <hi>filthy Caveat,</hi> but beware of that <hi>filthy ſinne,</hi> and acknowledge that the <hi>Caveat</hi> is given you, upon ſad <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="12">12. You tell me that <hi>God</hi> is not ſo <hi>fatally tyed to the Spindle of an abſolute Reprobation,</hi> but that upon your <hi>Repentance</hi> he will <hi>ſeale your Pardon.</hi> Sir, <hi>Reprobatio eſt tremendum Myſterium;</hi> how dare you <hi>jeſt</hi> upon ſuch a <hi>Subject,</hi> at the thought of which each <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an trembles?</hi> Can any man <hi>repent,</hi> that is given up to a <hi>reprobate mind,</hi> and an <hi>impenitent heart?</hi> And is not every man <hi>finally impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent,</hi> ſave thoſe <hi>few</hi> to whom <hi>God</hi> gives <hi>repentance, freely, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werfully, effectually?</hi> See what it is for a man to come from <hi>Ben. Johnſon,</hi> or <hi>Lucian,</hi> to treat immediately of the <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>igh</hi> and <hi>ſtupendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious myſteries</hi> of <hi>Religion;</hi> the <hi>Lord God</hi> pardon this wicked thought of your <hi>heart,</hi> that you may not periſh in the <hi>bond of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity</hi> and <hi>gall of bitterneſs;</hi> be pleaſed to ſtudy the 9. <hi>Chapter to the Romanes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>You ſay if we <hi>agree</hi> upon the <hi>true ſtate</hi> of the <hi>Queſtions before hand, nothing will be left us to diſpute.</hi> Sir, it is 1. one thing to <hi>ſtate</hi> a <hi>queſtion</hi> for debate, ſo that <hi>you</hi> may undertake the <hi>affirmative,</hi> I the <hi>Negative,</hi> or <hi>è contrat:</hi> 2. another thing to <hi>ſtate</hi> a <hi>queſtion</hi> in a <hi>ſuppoſition</hi> as the <hi>Reſpondent</hi> uſually doth, and a third buſineſs to <hi>ſtate</hi> a <hi>queſtion</hi> after the debate in a prudent and convincing <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination,</hi> as the <hi>Moderatour</hi> ſhould doe; I ſpeake of <hi>agreeing</hi> upon the <hi>ſtate</hi> of the <hi>queſtion</hi> in the firſt ſenſe, that the <hi>Queſtion</hi> may be propounded in ſuch <hi>termes</hi> as doe ſo farre <hi>ſtate</hi> the <hi>point</hi> in <hi>Controverſie,</hi> that <hi>you</hi> and I may know which <hi>port</hi> to take, the <hi>Affirmative</hi> or <hi>Negative.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The</hi> queſtions <hi>as I conceive are theſe that follow.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Whether all that our <hi>Prelates</hi> have <hi>borrowed</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>impoſed</hi> upon the <hi>people,</hi> ought to be ſtill <hi>retained</hi> in the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England?</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. Whether the <hi>Images</hi> of our <hi>Mediatour,</hi> and the <hi>Saints</hi> are
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:114217:20"/>
                        <hi>uſefull Ornaments</hi> in <hi>Proteſtant Churches?</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. Whether any <hi>Prelate</hi> be <hi>endued</hi> with the <hi>power</hi> of <hi>ſole Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination</hi> and <hi>Juriſdiction Jure divine?</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4. Whether <hi>they</hi> who <hi>defend</hi> the <hi>Proteſtants of Ireland</hi> againſt the <hi>Rebells</hi> by <hi>force</hi> of <hi>Armes,</hi> are therefore to be <hi>eſteemed Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humetans?</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>5. Whether <hi>that faith</hi> which is <hi>grounded</hi> only upon <hi>Tradition,</hi> ought to be <hi>eſteemed</hi> a <hi>Divine faith?</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>6. Whether the <hi>ſpirit ſpeaking in the word to the conſcience of private men</hi> ought to be <hi>eſteemed</hi> a <hi>private Spirit?</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>7. Whether any <hi>Reprobate</hi> can ever be <hi>converted</hi> or <hi>ſaved?</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>8. Whether the <hi>Papiſts</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> &amp; <hi>Rebells</hi> of <hi>Ireland</hi> with their <hi>Confederates</hi> did endeavour to <hi>extirpate</hi> the <hi>Proteſtant Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> and plant <hi>Popery</hi> in its ſtead?</item>
                     <item>9. Whether <hi>they</hi> who endeavoured to <hi>impoſe</hi> a <hi>Popiſh Service-Booke</hi> upon <hi>Scotland</hi> by <hi>force</hi> of <hi>Armes,</hi> were of the <hi>Mahumetan perſwaſion?</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>10. Whether the <hi>School-men</hi> are <hi>Competent judges</hi> in any <hi>point</hi> which concernes the <hi>Myſterie</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> or <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs?</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>11. Whether the <hi>Nationall Covenant contradict</hi> it ſelfe?</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Sir, if you pleaſe to anſwer upon the <hi>three firſt queſtions</hi> in the <hi>Schools,</hi> and <hi>hold</hi> them as you ſeem to <hi>hold</hi> them <hi>all Affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively,</hi> I ſhall endeavour to <hi>prove</hi> the <hi>Negative.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To all your <hi>ſcoffes</hi> and <hi>abuſes</hi> I have nothing to reply; if <hi>God</hi> bids you <hi>revile</hi> or <hi>curſe</hi> me, I ſhall ſubmit to <hi>God;</hi> you call me <hi>Fool, Bedlam, Turke, Dog, Devill,</hi> becauſe I give you <hi>ſeaſonable</hi> advice: Sure Sir, <hi>Nazianzen, Proſper,</hi> &amp;c. were not guilty of ſuch <hi>Poetry,</hi> nor did <hi>Prudentius</hi> teach you any ſuch <hi>ſtreines.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I did very honeſtly forewarn you of a <hi>viſitation;</hi> it is I thinke proper enough to enquire into <hi>matters</hi> of <hi>fact</hi> at a <hi>viſitation.</hi> Now whether <hi>Copes</hi> have been put to a <hi>ſuperſtitious uſe</hi> is not a queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be determined by <hi>any</hi> but <hi>In-Artificiall Arguments,</hi> I mean by <hi>ſufficient witneſſes.</hi> To that which you Propheſie of, that I am like to be a <hi>Viſitor;</hi> I anſwer 1. I thinke you have litle ground for ſuch a <hi>Prophecy:</hi> I call it a <hi>Prophecy,</hi> for I am ſure the <hi>Houſes</hi> of <hi>Parliament</hi> have not yet named any <hi>Viſitor.</hi> 2. You talke much of the <hi>wiſedome</hi> of the <hi>High Court of Parliament;</hi> and can you
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:114217:21"/>imagine that ſo <hi>wiſe</hi> a <hi>Court</hi> or (as you terme it) <hi>Councell</hi> will make choice of a <hi>Bedlam,</hi> a <hi>Turke, Dog,</hi> &amp;c. to <hi>viſit</hi> ſo many <hi>pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent</hi> and <hi>learned Doctors?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sir, you ſay you are not <hi>ſatisfied</hi> with <hi>my Arguments,</hi> you might have conſider'd that I doe reſerve <hi>my arguments</hi> till we meete at <hi>Schooles,</hi> our worke for the <hi>preſent</hi> is to draw up the <hi>Points</hi> in <hi>Controverſie</hi> into <hi>formall queſtions;</hi> I have you ſee <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med</hi> ſome <hi>queſtions,</hi> if you pleaſe to adde <hi>more,</hi> you may, I ſhall be ready to give you the beſt <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> I can, after <hi>theſe</hi> are <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſed,</hi> if I be not called away to ſome <hi>better imployment</hi> by <hi>thoſe</hi> who have power to <hi>diſpoſe</hi> of</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your humble</hi> Monitor, FRAN: CHEYNELL.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <postscript>
                     <p>An
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Omnia è Miſſali Breviario necnon Pontificali Romano à Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat is noſtris decerpta, populo<expan>
                                    <am>
                                       <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                    </am>
                                    <ex>que</ex>
                                 </expan> obſtruſa in Eccleſiam recipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enda ſint?</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Chriſti Sanctorum<expan>
                                    <am>
                                       <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                    </am>
                                    <ex>que</ex>
                                 </expan> imagines Reformatorum Templis utili ſint ornatui?</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Soli Praelato poteſtas Ordinationis nec non Juriſdictionis Jure divino competat?</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>In hiſce quaeſtionibus animi tui ſententiam expectat</hi>
FRANCISCUS CHEYNELL.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </postscript>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Having read over this <hi>Letter,</hi> I felt two <hi>contrary Affections</hi> move within my ſelfe. Firſt, I was <hi>ſorry,</hi> that it began in that kinde of <hi>bitterneſs,</hi> which uſeth to have the ſame <hi>miſchievous effect</hi> upon <hi>minds</hi> not addicted to <hi>quarrel, as blear eyes</hi> have upon other <hi>eyes more ſound.</hi> Which finde themſelves <hi>inſenſibly infected</hi> by <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding;</hi> And in the <hi>preſence</hi> of thoſe that are <hi>bleared</hi> unawares learne their <hi>imperfections,</hi> and become <hi>bleared</hi> too. Next, I was <hi>glad,</hi> that the <hi>Controverſies</hi> betweene us, (which like the <hi>originall</hi> of <hi>mankinde,</hi> began in <hi>two,</hi> and in a ſhort time had <hi>multiplyed</hi> themſelves paſt <hi>number</hi>) were at length reduced to <hi>three latine queſtions,</hi> and thoſe to be diſputed in the <hi>Divinity School;</hi> where that part of <hi>Oxford,</hi> which underſtands no other <hi>Tongue,</hi> but that in which they dayly utter their <hi>commodities,</hi> if they had been <hi>preſent</hi> towards the making of a <hi>throng,</hi> had yet beene <hi>abſent</hi> to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:114217:21"/>the diſpute. Thus divided, therefore, between my <hi>provocations</hi> to <hi>Anſwer</hi> the <hi>reproachfull Preface,</hi> and my <hi>Alacrity</hi> to <hi>comply</hi> with the <hi>Concluſion</hi> of the precedent <hi>Letter,</hi> I returned this <hi>following Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>When I had open'd the <hi>Letter</hi> you ſent me on <hi>Saturday night</hi> laſt, <hi>Jan.</hi> 30. and found by the firſt period of it, that as your <hi>firſt Letter</hi> ſhew'd you a great <hi>Maſter</hi> in <hi>Detraction,</hi> ſo in <hi>this</hi> you had learnt the <hi>Art</hi> to make the <hi>Scripture revile</hi> me too, and taught <hi>two</hi> of <hi>Solomons</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Pro. 26. 4, 5.</note> 
                     <hi>Proverbs</hi> to call me <hi>Fool;</hi> Finding alſo in the next period how <hi>naturally</hi> and uncompelled <hi>ill language</hi> flows from you; who do here confeſs that you did <hi>let looſe your pen</hi> that I might ſee, how eaſily, and with what an <hi>unforc'd</hi> Dexterity, <hi>in the leſs ſerious part of the Day,</hi> without <hi>premeditation,</hi> or the expence of Study, you could <hi>revile</hi> me; And withall, that you did <hi>let flye ſo many quibbles</hi> (as the <hi>exerciſe of your Recreation,</hi> I preſume) to minde me of my more <hi>induſtrious Trifles,</hi> I muſt confeſs I not onely look't upon you as a <hi>Perſon</hi> fit to <hi>ſit</hi> in the<note n="*" place="margin">Pſa. i. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Seat of the Scornfull,</hi> but as <hi>one</hi> very capable to be requited with a <hi>Proverb;</hi> which the ſame<note n="*" place="margin">Pro. 26.18.19.</note> 
                     <hi>Chapter</hi> which you <hi>quoted,</hi> preſented to me at the 18. &amp; 19. <hi>Verſes;</hi> where 'tis ſaid, <hi>That as a mad-man who caſteth-firebrands, Arrows, and death, ſo as the man that deceiveth his neighbour and ſaith he is in ſport.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sir, I ſhould not have applyed this <hi>price</hi> of <hi>Scripture</hi> to you by way of <hi>Retaliation,</hi> (which may ſeem to have ſome <hi>bitterneſs</hi> in it) had you not at the very <hi>threſhold</hi> and firſt <hi>unlocking</hi> of <hi>your Letter,</hi> verified this <hi>Proverb</hi> upon <hi>your ſelf,</hi> by caſting <hi>firebrands</hi> and <hi>Arrows</hi> firſt, and thereby <hi>deceiving me,</hi> who (upon your <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe</hi> that I ſhould be <hi>ſpiritually dealt with,</hi> that is, as a <hi>Divine</hi> ingaged in a needleſs <hi>Controverſie</hi> with a <hi>Divine</hi> ought to be) un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuccesfully flattered my ſelf, that for the <hi>future,</hi> though I could not expect much <hi>Reaſon</hi> or <hi>proof</hi> or <hi>Argument</hi> from you, yet you would certainly bind your ſelf to the <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>Sobriety,</hi> and <hi>good Language.</hi> How you have made good your <hi>promiſe,</hi> will appear to <hi>any,</hi> who (beſides the <hi>reproachfull proverb</hi> with which you <hi>begin</hi> your <hi>Letter,</hi> and for which, a <hi>greater then Solomon</hi> hath ſaid you ſhall be in<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 5.22</note> 
                     <hi>Danger of Hell-fire</hi>) ſhall read the puddle of <hi>your letter</hi> which ſtreams from the firſt <hi>foul Spring,</hi> and <hi>Head</hi> of it; where, having firſt charged me in my <hi>writing</hi> to you with <hi>Elaborate Folly,</hi> you make it an <hi>Excuſe</hi> to the <hi>Dirt</hi> and <hi>mire</hi> of your <hi>pen,</hi> that I ſet you the <hi>Copy,</hi> and was <hi>foul</hi> in my <hi>Expreſſions firſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sir, Though the ſaying of <hi>Tacitus</hi> be one of the beſt <hi>confutations</hi> of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:114217:22"/>
                     <hi>Detraction, Convitia ſpreta exoleſcunt,</hi> and though I have alwaies thought that to enter <hi>combate</hi> with a <hi>Dunghill</hi> is the way to come off more <hi>defiled,</hi> yet finding my ſelf <hi>engaged</hi> (like one of the <hi>poeticall Knights errant</hi>) with an Adverſary that will not onely <hi>provoke</hi> me to <hi>fight,</hi> but, whoſ <hi>beſt weapon</hi> is to defile me out of the field, I ſhal for once apply as good <hi>perfume</hi> to the <hi>ſtench</hi> you ſpeak of, as can poſſibly in ſuch times make me walk the <hi>ſtreets</hi> in my <hi>own Oxford, uncondens'd</hi> not by <hi>you</hi> made <hi>foggy, Ayre;</hi> And ſhall make it evident, firſt to <hi>your ſelf,</hi> next to the <hi>world,</hi> (if you will conſent that what thus <hi>ſecretly</hi> paſſeth between <hi>us</hi> ſhall be made <hi>publike,</hi> and <hi>Printed</hi>) that you are not onely <hi>fallible</hi> in your moſt ſad, and melancholy conſiderations, but in thoſe more <hi>pleaſant, mirthful chymes</hi> of <hi>quibbling,</hi> for which I before placed you in the <hi>Chaire.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt, ſir, you bid me read over my <hi>two Sermons</hi> and the <hi>two letters</hi> which I have ſent you, <hi>as if they were yours, and then impartially tell you, whether I am not to paſs ſentence upon them as you do;</hi> That they are <hi>Diffoiles Nugae, Elaborate Follies.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To which my Reply is; Firſt, that there is ſo much <hi>loyalty,</hi> and ſo little <hi>ſelf-intereſt</hi> in them, that my imagination can never be ſtrong enough to Suppoſe them to be <hi>yours,</hi> Next, That what <hi>Folly</hi> ſoever betrayes it ſelf in your <hi>expreſſions,</hi> yet the <hi>matter</hi> is built upon ſuch ſure <hi>rocks</hi> of the <hi>Scripture,</hi> that 'tis not all the <hi>waves</hi> or <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt</hi> which you can raiſe againſt them, wil be able to reduce them to the <hi>fate</hi> of a <hi>Houſe built upon the Sand.</hi> Thirdly, (ſince all <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes,</hi> as wel as <hi>wit,</hi> are like a <hi>Reſt Kept up at Tennis,</hi> where <hi>good players</hi> do the <hi>beſt</hi> with the <hi>beſt Gamſters</hi>) I do ſadly promiſe you, that when ever you ſhal either <hi>write</hi> or <hi>urge</hi> to me ſuch <hi>Arguments</hi> of <hi>ſerious Conſideration,</hi> that I ſhal not have reaſon to think <hi>St. Pauls</hi> ſaying verified in thy <hi>Expreſſions,</hi> that my <hi>Fooliſh things</hi> are ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to <hi>confound,</hi> and <hi>bring to nought</hi> your <hi>wiſe;</hi> I wil lay aſide the <hi>Folly</hi> you tax me withal. In the mean time, if you think my <hi>Letters</hi> to you <hi>By</hi> what <hi>Glaſs</hi> ſoever my <hi>Sermons</hi> were made) are <hi>elaborate,</hi> pray compare the <hi>Dates,</hi> and <hi>Receipts</hi> of <hi>them,</hi> with the <hi>No-d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>es,</hi> and uncertain <hi>Receipts</hi> of <hi>yours;</hi> And you wil find that the <hi>longeſt letter,</hi> I have yet written to you, was but the <hi>creature</hi> of <hi>two days,</hi> when your <hi>unelaborate anſwer</hi> to it back again was the <hi>Birth,</hi> and <hi>Travell</hi> of a whole week.</p>
                  <p>Having ſaid this, Sir, by way of <hi>Anſwer</hi> to your <hi>ungoſpel</hi>-like <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face,</hi> I ſhal next, (confining my ſelf once more to your own <hi>method</hi>) addreſs my ſelf to the <hi>examination</hi> of the reſt of your <hi>letter.</hi> A hard
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:114217:22"/>task, I confeſs; It being ſo much a <hi>Twinn-brother</hi> to your <hi>former<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> where your <hi>evaſions,</hi> and <hi>little eſcapes</hi> are ſo <hi>many,</hi> and your true ſubſtantiall, ſolid <hi>diſproofes</hi> of any one thing which I have ſayd either in my <hi>Sermons</hi> or <hi>Letters,</hi> ſo <hi>few,</hi> that, to deal freely with you, my <hi>Conflict</hi> with you hitherto hath been (and for ought I yet foreſee is like to prove) like the <hi>Fight</hi> between <hi>Hercules,</hi> and the <hi>River Achelous;</hi> which when 'twas foyled in one <hi>ſhape,</hi> could tire the <hi>Conquerour,</hi> and preſently provoke him to a freſh encounter <hi>in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> Sir, I could wiſh (without your ſtrange endleſs multiply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of <hi>Queſtions</hi>) you would aſſume to your ſelf ſome <hi>conſtant figure,</hi> wherein I might ſay, I grappled with a bodyed <hi>Adverſary.</hi> But changing <hi>Form,</hi> as you do, and putting me ſtil to <hi>prove</hi> that which you have not yet ſo much as ſeemingly <hi>confuted,</hi> pardon me (I beſeech you) if I ſay, that my <hi>combate</hi> with you is not only like the <hi>combate</hi> of <hi>Hercules</hi> with that <hi>River,</hi> but like his, who thought he had entered <hi>Duell</hi> with a <hi>Gyant,</hi> and after much toyl found himſelf encountred by a cloud.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, you <hi>conceive,</hi> that I <hi>preacht in defence of all Images ſet up in any Chappell within this Vniverſity.</hi> Sir, This is but your <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt,</hi> of which <hi>you,</hi> not <hi>I</hi> am guilty. My ſermon, if you mark it, is not ſo confined either to <hi>Vanlings Draughts,</hi> or any other mans <hi>pencil,</hi> as to defend what ever their <hi>Irregular Fancies</hi> ſhal draw, or not to defend what ever, either heer, or any where elſe, they ſhal <hi>regularly</hi> limb. But if your <hi>conceipt</hi> were true, what doth your <hi>Logick</hi> infer, That becauſe ſome <hi>Chappels</hi> are adorn'd with the <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages</hi> of ſome of the <hi>perſons in the Glorious Trinity, therefore I muſt acknowledg all Images of that ſort ought to be taken down?</hi> Pray, Sir, how long hath the ſingle-<hi>Topick</hi> of your meer <hi>Aſſertion</hi> been of ſuch forcible Authority, that without any other proofe, you ſhould think me obliged to hold ſuch <hi>Images</hi> worthy of expulſion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you ſay they are? Had you either from <hi>Scripture</hi> (the moſt perfect <hi>Rule</hi> for the Deciſion of <hi>Controverſies</hi>) or from <hi>Reaſon,</hi> (Though in your eſteem but a peece of <hi>nature corrupted</hi>) urged any one <hi>neceſſary Argument</hi> to prove them <hi>unlawful,</hi> or things which deſerve to be called the <hi>Idolatry</hi> or <hi>Superſtition</hi> of the <hi>place,</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps being a <hi>ſervant</hi> to <hi>Demonſtration,</hi> (though a <hi>favourite</hi> of the <hi>muſes</hi>) I ſhould have been one of the firſt that ſhould have cryed out for <hi>Reformation.</hi> But this not being done by <hi>you,</hi> nor indeed, poſſible to be done by <hi>any other,</hi> though my ſermon ſpeak not of any <hi>Image</hi> of any <hi>perſon</hi> in the <hi>Trinity,</hi> yet I conceive all <hi>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> which ſhal ſtrive to prove, that no picture of any <hi>perſon</hi> in
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:114217:23"/>the <hi>Trinity</hi> ought to be the <hi>Ornaments</hi> of a <hi>Church,</hi> or <hi>Chappell Window,</hi> will be as frail and brittle as the <hi>Glaſs</hi> in which they ſtand. Sir, I have ſaid in my laſt <hi>Letter,</hi> and ſhal repeat it in this, that 'tis not <hi>you,</hi> but <hi>nature</hi> and the <hi>numerous places of Scripture,</hi> which forbid to make any <hi>picture</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> (either taken for the <hi>Divine eſſence</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all the <hi>three perſons,</hi> or for the perſon of <hi>God</hi> the <hi>Father</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from the other <hi>two</hi>) which perſwade me that any ſuch <hi>picture</hi> (beſides the <hi>impoſſibility</hi>) is <hi>unlawfull.</hi> And therefore you need not have put your ſelf to the unceceſſary trouble to hang your <hi>Margin</hi> with <hi>quotations</hi> taken out of <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> or <hi>Aquinas;</hi> ſince all ſuch <hi>quotations</hi> applyed to that which I have ſaid and you have cited, which is, That <hi>all pictures of God are a breach of the ſecond Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandent,</hi> do ſtrike me no more, then if I ſhould enter conflict with thoſe dead <hi>Arras-Captains,</hi> which in <hi>hangings</hi> threaten to aſſault the ſpectatour with <hi>imaginary, woven Lunces.</hi> Much leſs need you ſo ſuperflouſly have called S. <hi>Paul</hi> from the <hi>third heaven</hi> to prove, that (becauſe he once quoted this <hi>Greek Hemiſtick</hi> out of <hi>Aratas</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, that we are the <hi>Off-ſpring</hi> of <hi>God</hi>) God is not <hi>like to gold, ſilver, or ſtone, graven by the art of mans device.</hi> Since by that which I have ſaid of him in my former Letter, you are obliged to teſtifie for me, that I have urged convincing reaſons to prove he cannot be: which Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſons, as borrowed from <hi>nature</hi> and the <hi>ſchoolmen</hi> (with whom, ſir, I hope you are not implacably fallen out) I do not urge as the <hi>ſupre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> Judges</hi> of what I there prove, but as ſubſervient mediums, which car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry a muſick and conſent to that which <hi>God</hi> hath ſaid of himſelf in the more perfect <hi>Rule</hi> of his <hi>Word.</hi> So that for doing this, to charge me (as you do) with the Study of the <hi>Lullian Art,</hi> is either <hi>nonſence</hi> in your Letter, or an <hi>Illation</hi> which reſolvs it ſelf into a contemptible miſtake; which is, That becauſe <hi>Lullius,</hi> who wrote of <hi>Chymiſtry,</hi> was ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ed <hi>Raymundus,</hi> I, who have read another <hi>Raymundus</hi> who wrote of <hi>Natural Theologie,</hi> am to be called a <hi>Lullianiſt,</hi> which is a <hi>Logick</hi> as wretched, as if I ſhould ſay, Mr <hi>Cheynell</hi> hath read <hi>Caſerane,</hi> and hath made him <hi>a marginal note,</hi> Therefore he is a <hi>ſeeker</hi> of the <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers Stone,</hi> and ſtudys to convert the <hi>Ore</hi> and <hi>Tin</hi> of the <hi>kingdom</hi> into <hi>Gold.</hi> Sir, Your <hi>Logick</hi> is not much mended when you ſay, That the Word <hi>(thereupon)</hi> is ſometimes <hi>Illative,</hi> ſometimes <hi>Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.</hi> For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ke it which way you will, As it ſtands in your laſt <hi>letter,</hi> you are bound to give me thanks as a <hi>Poet,</hi> that I deal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> not with you as a <hi>Sophiſter,</hi> and proclaimed your infirmity for having utter'd a <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction.</hi> Which <hi>contradiction,</hi> I confeſs, might have been avoyded
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:114217:23"/>by the inſertion of the <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>itled worder two,</hi> for w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> of which, yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſay my <hi>ſophiſticall Crititiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> is abortive, and came but with one legg into the World.</p>
                  <p>In anſwer to your next <hi>Paragraph,</hi> I ſhall moſt readly grant, That 'tis a <hi>high fault to picture God.</hi> Becauſe, any ſuch <hi>Draught</hi> not being poſſible to be made of him, but by reſembling of him to <hi>ſomething</hi> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> is able to afford a <hi>Species</hi> or <hi>Idea</hi> to the <hi>ſenſe,</hi> would, (beſides the <hi>Falſeneſs</hi> of it, where a <hi>groſs material figure</hi> ſhould repreſent a <hi>Pur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> inviſible Eſſence</hi>) degrade him from the honour which he ought to hold in our <hi>Minds</hi> which are his Temple; in which <hi>Temple</hi> if he ſhould hang up in a <hi>frame</hi> or <hi>table,</hi> which ſhould contract and ſhrink him to the finite <hi>Model</hi> of a <hi>man</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> any other <hi>creature,</hi> 'twere the way to convert him into an <hi>Idoll;</hi> and ſo (as I have often ſaid) to ſin againſt the <hi>ſecond Commandement,</hi> which as it may be broken by ſpending our <hi>Worſhip</hi> upon <hi>falſe Gods;</hi> ſo it may alſo be broken by our <hi>falſe portraitures,</hi> and <hi>apprehenſions,</hi> and <hi>venerations</hi> of the <hi>True.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The caſe of the <hi>Saints</hi> is far otherwiſe. For whoſe <hi>pictures turn'd into Idols,</hi> as I have no where pleaded, (For as <hi>Idols</hi> I acknowledge they are the crime of thoſe who worſhip them) ſo, as <hi>Orndments,</hi> you will never be able convincingly to prove but that they may be i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently retain'd, and be lookt on by thoſe who do only count them <hi>ſpeechleſs Colours.</hi> The like may be ſaid of <hi>Pictures</hi> made of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which pretend to expreſs no more of him then is capable of <hi>Repreſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,</hi> and exceed not the <hi>lines</hi> and <hi>ſy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>etry</hi> of his <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>fleſh.</hi> For I ſhal grant you that to Limb his <hi>Divinity,</hi> or to draw him in both his <hi>Natures,</hi> as he is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>God</hi> as well as <hi>man,</hi> is altogether impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, and not in the power of any <hi>Painter,</hi> though we ſhould recall <hi>Apelles,</hi> or <hi>Parrhaſius</hi> from their Graves, and once more put <hi>Pencil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> into their Hand. You know, ſir, if a <hi>man</hi> ſhould have his <hi>picture</hi> drawn, 'twould be an impoſſible task, if he ſhould enjoyn the <hi>Painter</hi> to limb his <hi>ſoul,</hi> as well as the <hi>proportion</hi> and <hi>feature</hi> of his <hi>Body,</hi> ſince the <hi>Soul</hi> is a thing ſo unexpreſſible to the ſenſe, that it ſcarce affods any <hi>Idea</hi> to be underſtood by the <hi>mind.</hi> Sir, if you have read Ariſtotles Books <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, you will there find, that the <hi>proper Objects</hi> of al the <hi>ſenſes</hi> beſides thoſe of the <hi>Eye</hi> (though much groſſer then <hi>Spirits</hi> or <hi>Souls</hi>) cannot be brought into <hi>picture.</hi> A <hi>Painter</hi> may draw a <hi>flower</hi> but he cannot limb a <hi>ſcent.</hi> He may paint <hi>fire,</hi> but he cannot draw <hi>heat.</hi> He may furniſh a table with an <hi>imaginary banquet,</hi> but he that ſhould offer to raſte of this <hi>banquet</hi> would find himſelf co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>en'd. The Reaſon is, becauſe <hi>Nature</hi> it ſelf makes it impoſſible for the <hi>proper</hi> Object of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:114217:24"/>one <hi>ſenſe</hi> to be the <hi>Object</hi> of <hi>another;</hi> And finds not <hi>art</hi> or <hi>col<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>s</hi> for any <hi>thing inviſible;</hi> But only for thoſe <hi>Superficie's, Symetry's,</hi> and <hi>ſenſible parts</hi> of Things, which are firſt capable to be <hi>ſeen,</hi> and then to be tranſcribed into a <hi>picture.</hi> But why that part of Chriſt, which after his Reſurrection, (when it began to ceaſe to be any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger a part of this <hi>viſible</hi> World) <hi>was ſeen of above five hundred bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren at once,</hi> may not be painted; Nay, why the <hi>figure</hi> of a <hi>Dove,</hi> or of <hi>cloven Tongues</hi> of <hi>fire</hi> (wherein the <hi>third perſon</hi> in the <hi>glorious Trinity</hi> appeared, when he deſcended upon our Mediator Chriſt, and ſate upon the <hi>heads</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi>) may not be brought into <hi>ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery,</hi> I muſt confeſs to you, I am not ſharp-witted enough to perceive. Though this I ſhal freely ſay to you, (and pray do not call it Poetry) That to maintain that Chriſt thus in <hi>picture</hi> may be <hi>worſhipt,</hi> is ſuch a peece of <hi>Superſtition,</hi> as not only teaches the ſimple to commit I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry, but endeavours to verifie upon him in <hi>colours</hi> the reproach which the calumniating Jews ſtuck upon his <hi>perſon</hi> and to make him thus painted, a Seducer of people.</p>
                  <p>As for your fourth <hi>paragraph,</hi> (which aſſaults me the ſecond time with an Argument without an Edge, which is, that the <hi>Sun and I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages cannot be put in the ſcales of compariſon in point of fitneſs to be preſerved</hi>) having in my former <hi>Letter</hi> already anſwered you, I ſhal not put my ſelf to the needleſs trouble, the ſecond time to confute it.</p>
                  <p>For anſwer to your Fifth, pray, Sir, read that part of my <hi>Sermon</hi> which you have corrupted into a <hi>quibble;</hi> And there you ſhal find, that what I ſay of <hi>clean linnen</hi> is not, as you ſay, a <hi>ſhifting Fallacy.</hi> But I there ſay that which you wil never be able to controule; which is, That by the ſame reaſon that you make <hi>Surplices</hi> to be <hi>ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ious</hi> becauſe <hi>papiſts</hi> wear them, you may make <hi>Linnen</hi> alſo to be <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious</hi> becauſe <hi>papiſts ſhift;</hi> And ſo conclude <hi>cleanlineſs</hi> to be as <hi>unlawful</hi> as <hi>Surplices</hi> or <hi>Copes.</hi> Sir, this is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>; I confeſs, the ſame Anſwer twice ſerved in to you, not out of ſcarcity or barren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or for want of another Reply, but becauſe much of your <hi>Letter</hi> is but <hi>crambe</hi> repetita, a <hi>carret twice boyled.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Your ſixth <hi>paragraph</hi> is a <hi>faggot</hi> bound up with more ſticks in it, then you, without <hi>poetical Licence,</hi> can poſſibly gather from my <hi>Letter;</hi> where, Sir, I only promiſe you, (when ever you ſhal cal upon me) to derive to you all the <hi>ancient parts of our Engliſh Liturgy</hi> from <hi>Liturgy's</hi> which were in the Church before <hi>popery</hi> was born. Of which if any part be to be found in the <hi>Rubricks</hi> of the <hi>Church of Rom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> your <hi>logick</hi> wil never be able to prove, that therefore 'tis to be rejected as
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:114217:24"/>
                     <hi>traſh and trumpery in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>rs. Good things,</hi> Sir, loſe not their <hi>goodneſs,</hi> becauſe they are in ſome places mingled with <hi>ſuperſtitious.</hi> Nor, as I told you before, do <hi>Davids Pſalms</hi> ceaſe to be a piece of <hi>Ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>ical Scripture,</hi> becauſe they are to be found bound up in the volumn with the <hi>Maſs.</hi> Sir, if what ever is made uſe of by the <hi>Pope,</hi> or touches upon <hi>Rome,</hi> ſhould be <hi>ſuperſtitious,</hi> the <hi>River Tiber</hi> would be the moſt blameable <hi>river</hi> in the World. What you mean by a <hi>prelatical Faction</hi> here in <hi>England,</hi> or what they borrowed from the <hi>Rituals</hi> or <hi>pontifical</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> is expreſt to me in ſuch a <hi>miſt</hi> of words (which ſound big to the <hi>common people,</hi> and ſignifie nothing to the <hi>wiſe</hi>) that I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs my <hi>dulneſs,</hi> I do not underſtand you. If you mean, that they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted any <hi>new peeces</hi> into the <hi>old garment</hi> of our <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon-prayer-book;</hi> and thoſe borrowed from the <hi>Miſſal,</hi> or <hi>Breviary of Rome,</hi> I beleeve, Sir, (abſtracting from thoſe <hi>alterations</hi> made in the <hi>prayers</hi> for the <hi>King, Queen,</hi> and <hi>Royal iſſue,</hi> which the <hi>Death</hi> of <hi>Princes</hi> exacted, (unleſs, for conſtancy ſake, you would have them allow of <hi>prayers</hi> for the <hi>dead;</hi> and in <hi>King Charls</hi> and <hi>Queen Mary's</hi> days, to pray ſtill for <hi>King James</hi> and <hi>Queen Anne,</hi> which would be a piece of <hi>popery</hi> equal to the <hi>invocations of ſaints</hi>) you will find nothing <hi>medern</hi> or of ſuch <hi>new contrivance,</hi> as paſt not <hi>Bucers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>xamen</hi> in the <hi>raign of</hi> Edward <hi>the ſixth;</hi> And was confirmed b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Act of Parliament</hi> in the <hi>raign</hi> of Queen <hi>Elizabeth.</hi> In ſaying this in their defence, who had the ordering of ſuch <hi>changes,</hi> I hope Sir, you will not ſo uncharitably think me imbark't in their <hi>Faction</hi> (which truly to me ſtil preſented it ſelf like the <hi>conceal'd Horſes under ground,</hi> a <hi>fiction</hi> made to walk the <hi>ſtreets,</hi> to terrifie the <hi>people</hi>) as to perſwade your ſelf, after my ſo many profeſſions to <hi>fall a ſacrifice</hi> to the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> that it can be either in the power of the Church or <hi>court of Rome,</hi> to tempt me from my <hi>Reſolution:</hi> Which is, to go out of the world, in the ſame Religion I came in.</p>
                  <p>Sir, I gave warning in my laſt <hi>letter</hi> not to venture your writings upon the Arg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ment, which deceives none but very <hi>vulgar underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings,</hi> and which I in my Ser<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on cal the <hi>Mother of miſtakes;</hi> which is, from an <hi>accidental concurrence</hi> in <hi>ſome things</hi> to infer an outright <hi>ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude</hi> and <hi>agreement</hi> in <hi>all.</hi> Becauſe <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſays <hi>tradition</hi> is a better <hi>medium</hi> to prove ſomethings by, then a <hi>private ſpirit,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I in this particular have ſaid ſo too, you tacitely infer that I and <hi>Bellarmine</hi> are of the ſame Religion; which is the ſame, as if a <hi>Turk</hi> and a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> ſaying that the <hi>Sun</hi> ſhines, you ſhould infer, that the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> is a <hi>Mahumetan,</hi> and for ſaying ſo, a <hi>Turk.</hi> I confeſs, you do not ſay we are both of the ſame Religion: but that I, in preferring
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:114217:25"/>
                     <hi>Tradition,</hi> which you your ſelf, in your ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap>h <hi>paragraph,</hi> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ow to be the <hi>Conſtant and uni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>erſal Report of the Church</hi>) befo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> he Teſtimony of the <hi>Spirit, ſpeaking in the Word to the Conſci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> of private men,</hi> am more <hi>profane</hi> than <hi>he.</hi> Heer, ſir, you muſt not take it ill, if I expoſe you to the cenſure of being deſervedly thought guilty of a double <hi>miſtake.</hi> The one is, that if <hi>Bellarmine</hi> in this <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular</hi> were in an <hi>Errour,</hi> and if I had out-ſpoken him in his <hi>Errour,</hi> yet the Laws of <hi>ſpeech</hi> will not allow you to ſay, That in an <hi>unprof<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> ſubject, either of us is <hi>profane;</hi> more <hi>heretical,</hi> or <hi>miſtaken</hi> you might perhaps have ſaid: and this, though a falſe Aſſertion, might yet have paſt for right Expreſſion. But to call him <hi>poſitively,</hi> and me <hi>compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively more profane,</hi> becauſe we both hold, That a <hi>Drop</hi> is more liable to corruption then the <hi>Ocean,</hi> or the <hi>teſtimony of al ages</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> is a fuller <hi>proof</hi> of the meaning of a <hi>text</hi> in <hi>Scripture,</hi> then the <hi>ſolitary Expoſition</hi> of a <hi>man</hi> who can perſwade none but himſelf, is as incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruous, as if you ſhould ſay, that becauſe <hi>Bellanmine</hi> wrote but <hi>three Volumn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> and <hi>Abulenſis</hi> twelve, therefore <hi>Abulenſis</hi> was: a greater <hi>Adulterer</hi> then <hi>He.</hi> Your other <hi>miſtake</hi> is, That you confound the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> of God ſpeaking in the <hi>Scripture</hi> with the <hi>private Spirit</hi> (that is) <hi>Reaſon, Humour,</hi> or <hi>Fancie</hi> of the <hi>perſon</hi> ſpoken to. Sir, let that <hi>bleſſed Spirit</hi> decide this controverſie between us. He ſayes<note n="*" place="margin">2 Pet. 1.20</note> 
                     <hi>that no Propheſie of the Scripture is of private Interpretation.</hi> That is, ſo <hi>calculated,</hi> or <hi>Meriduanized</hi> to ſome ſelect <hi>mind</hi> &amp; <hi>underſtandings,</hi> that it ſhall hold the <hi>candle</hi> to them <hi>only,</hi> and leave <hi>All others</hi> in the <hi>Darke.</hi> But, if you will conſent to the Comment of the moſt primitive <hi>Fathers</hi> on that <hi>Text,</hi> The meaning of it is, That as <hi>God</hi> by his <hi>Spirit</hi> did at firſt dictate the <hi>ſcripture,</hi> ſo he dictated it in thoſe things which are <hi>neceſſary</hi> to <hi>Salvation,</hi> intelligible to all the world of M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n, who will addict their minds to read it. It being therefore a <hi>Rule</hi> held out to all <hi>mankind,</hi> for them to order their lives and actions by and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore univerſally <hi>intelligible</hi> to them, (it ſhould elſe ceaſe to be either <hi>Revelation</hi> or a <hi>Rule</hi>) for you to hold that is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>not be underſtand without a <hi>ſecond Revelation,</hi> made by the ſame <hi>Spirit</hi> that wrote it, to the <hi>private ſpirit of you the more-Cabinet Reader,</hi> is as if you ſhould incloſe and impale to your ſelf the <hi>Ayre,</hi> or <hi>Sun-be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>es;</hi> And ſhould maintain that God hath placed the <hi>Sun</hi> in the firmament, and given you only eyes to ſee him In ſhort, ſir, 'tis to make as <hi>word,</hi> which was ordained to give <hi>light</hi> to all the <hi>World,</hi> a <hi>Dark Lanthorn,</hi> In which a <hi>candle</hi> ſhines to the uſe of <hi>none</hi> but <hi>him</hi> that bears it.</p>
                  <p>Your <hi>Eighth Paragraph</hi> being the <hi>third</hi> of your <hi>eleven Queſtions</hi> as alſo the <hi>cloſe</hi> of your <hi>ninth,</hi> ſhall receive a <hi>latine</hi> Anſwer from me in the <hi>Divinity School.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:114217:25"/>
Your next <hi>Paragraph</hi> is againe the <hi>Hydra</hi> with <hi>repullulating Heads:</hi> Where, firſt, you put me to prove the purity of the <hi>Doctrine, Diſcipline,</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> in <hi>England.</hi> Which, being managed by a <hi>Prelaticall faction, whom,</hi> you ſay, I call the <hi>Church, was not excellent, if I reckon from the yeare</hi> 1630. <hi>to</hi> 1640. As for the <hi>Doctrine,</hi> Sir, I told you before, that the <hi>Primitive Church</hi> it ſelfe was not free from <hi>Hereſies.</hi> If therefore I ſhould grant you (which I never ſhall, till you particularly tell me what thoſe <hi>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous doctrines</hi> were) that ſome men in our <hi>Church</hi> were <hi>hete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodox,</hi> nay <hi>hereticall</hi> in their <hi>opinions,</hi> yet I conceive it to be a very neere neighbour to <hi>hereſie</hi> in you to charge the <hi>doctrines</hi> of <hi>perſons</hi> upon the <hi>Kingdome</hi> or <hi>Church.</hi> Such <hi>Doctrines</hi> might be <hi>in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> (as you whether out of Choice or Luck have ſaid) yet not by the <hi>Tenets</hi> or <hi>Doctrines</hi> of the <hi>Land:</hi> No more, then if you ſhould ſay, that becauſe M. <hi>Yerbury</hi> and ſome few <hi>others</hi> hold the <hi>Equ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lity</hi> of the <hi>Saints</hi> with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the whole <hi>Kingdome</hi> is a <hi>bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphemer,</hi> and was by you confuted at S. <hi>Maries.</hi> The <hi>publick do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> I call none but that which was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to be ſo by an <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Pa liament</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> and that, Sir, was contained in the 39. <hi>Articles.</hi> If any <hi>Prelate</hi> or <hi>inferiour Prieſt,</hi> for the <hi>Cicle</hi> of <hi>yeares</hi> you ſpeak of, either held or taught any thing contrary to <hi>theſe,</hi> (as it will be hard I beleeve for you to inſtance in <hi>any</hi> of that <hi>ſide</hi> who did) you ſhall have my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, in that particular, to count them no part of our <hi>Church.</hi> In the meane time, Sir, I beſeech you be favourable to this <hi>Iſland;</hi> and think not that for <hi>ten yeares ſpace</hi> 'twas <hi>hereticall</hi> in all the parts of it on this ſide <hi>Berwick.</hi> Withall, Sir, I deſire (ſince you have aſſigned me an <hi>Epocha</hi> to reckon from) that you will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the worſt <hi>doctrines</hi> which wore the <hi>date</hi> of the <hi>Trojan Warre</hi> amongs us, with thoſe which have ſince broke looſe in the ſpace of a <hi>Warre</hi> not halfe ſo long, and you will find, that our <hi>Church</hi> for thoſe <hi>ten yeares</hi> you ſpeak of <hi>wore a garment,</hi> I will not ſay, as <hi>ſeamleſs</hi> and <hi>undivided</hi> as <hi>Chriſts coat:</hi> But ſince the <hi>Soldiers</hi> did <hi>caſt lots</hi> upon it, ſo much <hi>hereſie,</hi> as well as <hi>ſchiſme,</hi> hath torne it aſunder, that 'tis now become like <hi>Joſephs coat</hi> imbrued in <hi>bloud,</hi> where no one <hi>piece</hi> carryes <hi>colour</hi> or <hi>reſemblance</hi> to another. As for the <hi>Diſcipl ne</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> of our <hi>Church,</hi> (if you would ſpeak your <hi>conſcience,</hi> and not your <hi>gall</hi>) you would confeſs, that
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:114217:26"/>the <hi>frame</hi> and <hi>ſtructure</hi> of it was raiſed from the moſt Primitive <hi>Modell</hi> that any <hi>Moderne Church</hi> under the <hi>Sunne</hi> was governed by. A <hi>Government</hi> ſo well <hi>ſized</hi> and <hi>fitted</hi> to the <hi>Civill Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> that till the <hi>inſurrection</hi> of ſome <hi>falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi> who preſumed to offer <hi>ſtrange fire</hi> before the <hi>Lord,</hi> and reduced a <hi>Land</hi> which flowed with <hi>milk</hi> and <hi>honey,</hi> into a <hi>wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe;</hi> they agreed together like the two <hi>Scripture-brothers, Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron;</hi> and were the two <hi>banks</hi> which ſhut up <hi>ſchiſme</hi> within its <hi>channell,</hi> and ſuffered not <hi>hereſie</hi> or <hi>ſedition</hi> to overflow their <hi>bounds.</hi> In ſhort, Sir, I know not into what <hi>new forme</hi> this <hi>Kingdome</hi> may be <hi>moulded,</hi> or what <hi>new creation</hi> may creep forth from the ſtrife-full <hi>heap</hi> of things, into which, as into a ſecond <hi>Chaos,</hi> we are fallen; But if the <hi>Civill State</hi> doe ever returne to its former <hi>ſelfe</hi> againe, your <hi>Preſbyterian Government,</hi> which was brought forth at <hi>Geneva,</hi> and was ſince nurſed up in <hi>Scotland,</hi> mingled with it, (if I be not deceived in the <hi>principles</hi> of that <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi>) will be but a <hi>wild Vine</hi> ingrafted into a <hi>true.</hi> Vpon which unequall, diſproportioned <hi>Incorporation,</hi> we may as well expect to gather <hi>Figs</hi> of <hi>Thiſtles,</hi> or <hi>grapes</hi> of <hi>thornes,</hi> as that the <hi>one</hi> ſhould grow ſo <hi>Southerne,</hi> the <hi>other</hi> ſo <hi>Northerne;</hi> that one harmonious, muſicall <hi>Body</hi> ſhould ariſe from them thus <hi>joyned.</hi> What <hi>Errors</hi> in <hi>Government</hi> or <hi>Diſcipline</hi> were committed by the <hi>Prelates,</hi> I know not; neither have you proved them hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to chargeable with any; unleſs this were an <hi>error,</hi> that they laid an <hi>Oſtraciſme</hi> (as you ſay) <hi>upon thoſe that oppoſed your Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> I beleeve, Sir, when <hi>Presbytery</hi> is ſet up, and you placed in your <hi>Conſiſtory</hi> with your <hi>Spirituall</hi> and <hi>Lay-Brethren,</hi> you will not be ſo negligent, or ſo much aſleep in your place, as not to find an <hi>Oſtraciſme</hi> for thoſe, who ſhall oppoſe you in your office. In the meane time, Sir, to call <hi>them,</hi> or <hi>thoſe,</hi> who ſubmitted to their <hi>Government, A Prelaticall faction,</hi> becauſe the then wheels of their <hi>Government</hi> moved with an <hi>unanimous</hi> undiſturbance, is, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, a calumny, which you would faine faſten upon them, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked (I ſuppoſe) by the deſcription which I have made of the <hi>conſpiracy</hi> of the <hi>Falſe Prophets</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> in my <hi>Sermon.</hi> I muſt deal freely with you, Sir, do but probably make it appear to me, that this <hi>Faction</hi> in <hi>your letter</hi> was like the <hi>Conſpiracy</hi> in <hi>my Sermon;</hi> Do but prove to me, that the <hi>Prelates devoured ſoules;</hi> That they took to themſelves the <hi>Treaſure,</hi> and <hi>precious things</hi> of the <hi>Land;</hi>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:114217:26"/>That to effect this, they kindled the firſt <hi>ſpark</hi> towards a <hi>Civil War;</hi> &amp; then blew it into ſuch a <hi>flame,</hi> as could not be quencht but with the bloud of <hi>Husbands</hi> raviſht from their <hi>Wives,</hi> and the ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>parents</hi> preſt and raviſht from their <hi>children:</hi> Doe but prove to me that they made <hi>one widdow,</hi> or built their <hi>Honours</hi> upon the <hi>ruine</hi> or <hi>calamity</hi> of one <hi>Orphane;</hi> Laſtly, do but prove to me that the <hi>Prieſts</hi> (whom you make to be the <hi>lower orbe</hi> of their <hi>Faction</hi>) did ſo mingle, and confound the <hi>ſervices</hi> of the <hi>Church, as to put no difference between the holy, and profane,</hi> or that in complyance with them, they <hi>ſaw vanity, and divined lyes to the people,</hi> and I ſhall think them capable of all the hard language, which you or others have for ſome yeares heapt upon them. Till then, Sir, pray miſtake not <hi>Concrets</hi> for their <hi>Abſtracts;</hi> nor charge the faults of <hi>perſons,</hi> upon the innocency of their <hi>functions. Prelacy</hi> is an <hi>Order</hi> ſo well rooted in the <hi>Scripture,</hi> though now deprived of all its <hi>Branches</hi> in this Kingdome, that I verily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade my ſelfe, that as <hi>Caiaphas</hi> in the <hi>Goſpell</hi> when he ſpoke <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy,</hi> perceived not himſelf at that time to be a <hi>Prophet;</hi> ſo you (over-rul'd by the guidance of a <hi>higher power</hi>) have in this <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph</hi> exceedingly praiſed <hi>Prelacy,</hi> whilſt you laboured to revile it. For either it muſt be <hi>Non-ſenſe,</hi> or a very great <hi>Encomium</hi> of it, when you ſay, that <hi>as long as it enjoyed a root</hi> here in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, it had <hi>not onely a deſtructive influence into the evils of the Church, but of the Civill State too.</hi> If the <hi>Influence</hi> of it were ſo <hi>deſtructive of evils,</hi> (as indeed it was) pray with what Logick can you ſay, that <hi>Salus populi quae ſuprema lex eſt,</hi> did compell the <hi>Parliament</hi> to extirpate a thing ſo <hi>preſervative</hi> and full of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dote</hi> both to <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sir, if mens <hi>ſtyles</hi> &amp; <hi>denominations</hi> be to be given to them by the <hi>place</hi> &amp; <hi>clymate</hi> where they are <hi>borne</hi> &amp; <hi>bred,</hi> I ſhall grant you are an <hi>Engliſh,</hi> nay an <hi>Oxford Chriſtian.</hi> But if you preach, &amp; maintain, that <hi>Religion as to be propagated by the Sword,</hi> I muſt tell you, that an <hi>Engliſh Presbyter</hi> may in this caſe be a <hi>Turkiſh Prophet;</hi> and that though his <hi>Text</hi> be choſen from the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> yet the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> raiſed from it, may be a piece of the <hi>Alchoran.</hi> I ſhall allow you to ſay that <hi>the Proteſtants in Ireland had a Right to the defence of the free exerciſe of their Religion againſt the furious aſſaults of the bloody Rebels.</hi> But when you tell me that <hi>Chriſt is King of Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:114217:27"/>as well as King of Saints,</hi> (which I ſhall grant you) and ſay, that as one of his wayes to <hi>make Proſelytes</hi> is by the <hi>perſwaſion of his Word and Spirit;</hi> ſo, if that will not do, his other <hi>way to break the power of Antichriſt,</hi> that is, (as I conceive you mean) to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert men from <hi>Popery,</hi> is by <hi>civill</hi> and <hi>naturall</hi> meanes that is, (if you meane any thing) to compell them to be <hi>Proteſtants</hi> by the <hi>Sword;</hi> Me-thinks I am at <hi>Mecha,</hi> and heare a piece of <hi>Turciſme</hi> preacht to me by one of <hi>Mahomets Prieſts.</hi> In ſhort, Sir, whether the <hi>Papiſts</hi> in <hi>England</hi> were <hi>confederate</hi> with the <hi>Iriſh Rebels</hi> I know not: But doe you prove <hi>demonſtratively,</hi> not <hi>jealouſly,</hi> to me, that the <hi>Queene</hi> and her <hi>Agents</hi> had an intent to <hi>extirpate</hi> the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> and to <hi>plant Popery</hi> by the <hi>Sword;</hi> and the <hi>Army</hi> that ſhould bring that <hi>deſigne</hi> to paſs, ſhall, in my opinion, be ſtyled an <hi>Army,</hi> not of <hi>Papiſts,</hi> but of <hi>baptized Janizaries.</hi> As for your bidding me diſpute the <hi>right of taking up Armes</hi> in ſuch a caſe, with the <hi>Parliament;</hi> Firſt, I muſt deſire you to accept the Anſwer which <hi>Favroinus</hi> the <hi>Philoſopher</hi> gave to a friend of his, who askt him, why he would let <hi>Adrian</hi> the <hi>Emperour</hi> have the better of him in a <hi>Diſpute;</hi> I am loth to enter into an <hi>Argumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> with <hi>thoſe</hi> who command <hi>Thirty Legions.</hi> Next, Sir, if I were of conſideration enough to be heard to ſpeak publickly to that <hi>Great Aſſembly,</hi> having firſt kiſt my <hi>weapon,</hi> I ſhould not doubt, with all the <hi>reſpective liberty,</hi> which might witneſs to them that I ſtrive not to diminiſh the <hi>rights</hi> of their <hi>power,</hi> but to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the <hi>truth</hi> of my <hi>cauſe,</hi> to tell them, that <hi>to come into the field with an armed Goſpel, is not the way choſen by Chriſt to make Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites.</hi> If this be an <hi>error</hi> or <hi>miſ-perſwaſion</hi> in me, ſhew me but one <hi>undenyable demonſtration</hi> of the <hi>Spirit</hi> to diſprove it, beſides your <hi>unto picall perſwaſion</hi> of <hi>your ſelfe</hi> to the contrary, and, without any farther <hi>conference,</hi> or <hi>diſpute</hi> in this point, I ſhall acknowledge my ſelfe your <hi>convert,</hi> and be moſt glad to be <hi>convinced.</hi> In the mean time, Sir, you are obliged, (though I be in your opinion in an <hi>error</hi>) to think more <hi>nobly</hi> of <hi>me,</hi> then of thoſe <hi>Cowards</hi> of your <hi>ſide,</hi> who durſt not <hi>ſpeak Truth</hi> in a <hi>time</hi> of <hi>danger,</hi> when you ſee me, in the like <hi>time,</hi> ſuch a reſolute <hi>Champion</hi> (as you conceive) for the <hi>wrong.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sir, 'tis one of the prayſes of a good <hi>picture</hi> to be drawne ſo <hi>livingly,</hi> that every one in the room that beholds it, ſhall thinke it
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:114217:27"/>looks <hi>only</hi> on <hi>him;</hi> 'Tis juſt ſo with ſome <hi>Texts</hi> in <hi>Scripture,</hi> and ſome parts of <hi>morall Philoſophy;</hi> which when they ſpeake very Characterizingly of an irregular <hi>paſsion,</hi> or <hi>vice,</hi> if they meet with a man <hi>Conſcious,</hi> and one ſubject to ſuch <hi>paſsions,</hi> remember him of his <hi>guilt,</hi> and prick his <hi>minde</hi> as if <hi>he only</hi> were ſignified by that which was writ to all the <hi>World.</hi> By your charging me that I dealt more ſharply with you then I ſhould, you give me cauſe to ſuſpect, that my <hi>Letter</hi> proved ſuch a <hi>picture</hi> to you; and you to your <hi>guilty ſelfe</hi> ſeemed a perſon ſo <hi>concerned.</hi> The words of bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs which you have layed together in one <hi>heape,</hi> are compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of ſuch <hi>Language,</hi> as upon your twentieth perufall you will never be able to finde in my <hi>Letter.</hi> Sir, <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> and my <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion</hi> (however you in your letter forgot <hi>both</hi>) have taught me not to returne <hi>Vomit</hi> for <hi>Vomit.</hi> And the love which I beare to to the <hi>Civility</hi> of <hi>expreſsion,</hi> would never ſuffer me to be ſo <hi>revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly broad.</hi> If I made uſe of one of <hi>Seneca's Epiſtles,</hi> or of <hi>Tully's Paradoxes,</hi> or <hi>Horace</hi>'s <hi>poeticall Controverſies,</hi> and if you would apply what they ſaid of <hi>Ambition, Pride,</hi> or <hi>Choller</hi> to your ſelf, certainly, Sir, you have no reaſon to call this the <hi>Luxuriancy</hi> of my <hi>wit.</hi> And thereupon to inferre theſe <hi>provocative concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous;</hi> that my <hi>wit</hi> is <hi>wanton,</hi> therefore I am <hi>effeminate.</hi> That I am <hi>ſuperſtitious,</hi> therefore <hi>laſcivious</hi> too. Sir, as my <hi>wit</hi> is ſo <hi>poore</hi> that I ſhall obſerve your <hi>Councell,</hi> that is, never wax <hi>proud</hi> upon the <hi>ſtrength</hi> of it, or <hi>deſpiſe thoſe</hi> that are more <hi>weake,</hi> ſo (without ſparing me at all) I doe once more challenge you to prove, that the <hi>wantonneſs</hi> of it hath betrayed me to the <hi>looſe Converſation</hi> of any that are <hi>light.</hi> Laſtly, Sir, I hope you doe not thing I have ſo much of the <hi>vaine glory,</hi> or <hi>ſelfe-conceitedneſs</hi> of thoſe <hi>Reverend Hypocrites</hi> in the Goſpell in me, who were able to boaſt of their <hi>long Prayers,</hi> and <hi>broad phylactaries,</hi> and of their <hi>faſting twice a weeke,</hi> that I will offer to thinke my ſelfe <hi>more temperate then the Apoſtles.</hi> Yet, Sir, I dare once more challenge you, &amp; the <hi>preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt</hi> of your <hi>inſpired informers,</hi> to prove me at any time guilty of the breach of the <hi>Text</hi> you quote againſt <hi>Surfeiting,</hi> and <hi>Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs. Luk.</hi> 21.34. That part of your <hi>Paragraph,</hi> therefore, which ends in <hi>exhortation,</hi> is a piece of <hi>Homily,</hi> which returnes to you, to be made uſe of towards ſome other on the next <hi>laſt Wedneſday of the month,</hi> where <hi>Faſting,</hi> and <hi>Sobriety</hi> will be <hi>ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ams.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:114217:28"/>
I grant, Sir, that <hi>Reprobation is a Myſtery to be trembled at.</hi> Yet Sir, all they who (maintaining it to be <hi>abſolute</hi>) doe revive the fiction of the three <hi>deſtinies,</hi> where one holds the <hi>Diſtaffe</hi> on which the <hi>Thred</hi> of every mans <hi>Fate</hi> is <hi>ſpun,</hi> and doe preach a piece of <hi>Zeno's Philoſophy</hi> for a piece of Saint <hi>Paul's Epiſtles,</hi> can have no reaſon to accuſe me of a <hi>jeſt,</hi> becauſe I apply'd a <hi>ſpindle</hi> to the <hi>Diſtaffe,</hi> on which mens <hi>fates</hi> are <hi>rolled.</hi> Sir, in plainer termes, as <hi>abſolute Reprobation,</hi> is a piece of <hi>Stoiciſme,</hi> which was never held to be <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> till it crept forth into the Church from the ſame <hi>fancy,</hi> which was the <hi>wombe</hi> in which the <hi>Preſbyterian Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> was formed, ſo me thinks, <hi>Lucian,</hi> Sir, (how cheaply ſoever you think of <hi>him,</hi> or <hi>me,</hi> for having cloſed my <hi>laſt letter</hi> to you with a piece of his <hi>Nigrinus</hi>) in his confutation of this <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh Errour</hi> (which hath made ſo many hang themſelves) urgeth Arguments which would become one of the <hi>Fathers</hi> of the <hi>Church.</hi> I know not whether you have read his <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. But if you have, he there tells you, that if there be ſuch a thing as the <hi>fatall Decree,</hi> you ſpeak of; 1. That all they who lye under the <hi>Inflexibility</hi> of it, being tyed by an unalterable <hi>neceſsity</hi> to do what they do, can in no reaſon be <hi>rewarded</hi> if they do <hi>well,</hi> nor with any Juſtice be <hi>puniſht</hi> if they do <hi>ill.</hi> Next, that the <hi>Sinnes</hi> which they commit, (if they cannot but commit them) are not to be called <hi>their Sinnes,</hi> but the <hi>Sinnes</hi> of that <hi>Decree</hi> which laid this <hi>neceſsity</hi> upon them. And, therefore, Thirdly, that a <hi>murtherer</hi> (thus predeſtined) if he ſhould be <hi>arraigned,</hi> may ſay to any <hi>Judge</hi> thus <hi>ſtoically perſwaded.</hi> Why doe you accuſe <hi>me?</hi> Pray call my <hi>Deſtiny</hi> to the <hi>Bar;</hi> and do not ſentence <hi>me,</hi> but my <hi>fate</hi> to the Racke and Wheel. I was but an overſway'd <hi>Inſtrument</hi> in this <hi>Murther;</hi> and was but ſuch an <hi>Engine</hi> to my <hi>Deſtiny,</hi> as my <hi>Sword</hi> was to <hi>me.</hi> Though this were ſpoken by a <hi>Heathen,</hi> only in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof of <hi>Fate,</hi> yet ſince Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> in more then <hi>three Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> had ſaid the ſame things in diſproofe of <hi>abſolute Reprobation,</hi> I hope, sir, neither <hi>Calvin,</hi> nor <hi>Piſcator,</hi> have ſo miſtaught you to underſtand Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> as from any <hi>Epiſtler</hi> of <hi>his</hi> to conclude peremptorily, that any without their <hi>deſert,</hi> are given up to a <hi>Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate minde,</hi> and <hi>finally</hi> ſtruck &amp; <hi>neceſsitated</hi> to a remedileſs <hi>impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence.</hi> The 9. <hi>Chap. of the Romans,</hi> I have long ſince conſider'd, and ſtudyed it by the moſt <hi>ſere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e, impartiall lights</hi> which might <hi>uncloud</hi>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:114217:28"/>the great <hi>Myſterie</hi> to me which lyes ſo obſcurely there wrap'd up. And to deale freely with you, the beſt <hi>Commentator</hi> I ever yet met with to lead me through the darkneſs of it, was another place of <hi>Scripture</hi> or two ſet in preſence, and <hi>ſcale</hi> with <hi>this,</hi> both which <hi>joyned,</hi> me thought, made perfectly the <hi>Cloud</hi> which guided the <hi>Jewes</hi> through the <hi>Wilderneſs,</hi> which was a <hi>Cloud</hi> to the <hi>Aegypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> but a <hi>pillar of fire</hi> to the <hi>Iſraelites.</hi> Sir, I know that neither Saint <hi>Paul</hi> hath written <hi>Contradictions,</hi> nor any other of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> written that which is <hi>Contradictory</hi> to Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> Sir, I preſume, alſo, that <hi>Ariſtotles Book</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> hath not ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken your <hi>memory,</hi> but you know that an <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſall Affirmative,</hi> and a <hi>particular Negative</hi> are a perfect <hi>Contradiction,</hi> and cannot both be <hi>true.</hi> Here, then, ſtands the caſe. You, building your <hi>Opinion</hi> upon the <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> or <hi>great depth</hi> of the <hi>ninth Chapter</hi> to the <hi>Romans,</hi> inferre from thence that <hi>God gives Repentance only to ſome few,</hi> whoſe peremptory will 'tis that <hi>they only</hi> ſhall be <hi>ſaved.</hi> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in his firſt <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to <hi>Timothy, Chapter</hi> 2. <hi>verſ.</hi> 4. gives us a <hi>line</hi> and <hi>plummet</hi> to ſound this <hi>Depth;</hi> and ſaves expreſly, That 'tis <hi>the will of God that all men ſhould be ſaved.</hi> Between theſe <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, 'tis his will that all ſhall,</hi> and <hi>'tis his will that only a few ſhall be ſaved,</hi> there is no <hi>Medium,</hi> in which they may be reconciled; but one of them muſt neceſsarily be <hi>true,</hi> the other <hi>falſe.</hi> This, then, being ſo, I have alwayes held it ſafer to build my <hi>Faith</hi> upon thoſe <hi>cleare</hi> places of the <hi>Scripture,</hi> which have no <hi>vaile</hi> before their <hi>face,</hi> then thoſe which are <hi>myſterious,</hi> and lead me to a <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> over which I ſtand <hi>amazed,</hi> but cannot from thence <hi>infer.</hi> I doe farther profeſs to you, that I am not ſo wedded to <hi>this</hi> or <hi>any other Speculative Opinion,</hi> but that, if you will ſhew more convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing <hi>Scripture</hi> for the <hi>contrary,</hi> I ſhall moſt readily renounce my <hi>owne</hi> thoughts, and eſpouſe my ſelf to <hi>yours.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Your <hi>premonition</hi> or <hi>forewarning</hi> of me that we at <hi>Chriſt-church</hi> would e're long taſte of a <hi>viſitation,</hi> hath ſince come to paſs, and in part approved it ſelf to be <hi>true Prophecy.</hi> Whether <hi>im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ired</hi> by <hi>you</hi> or no, I know not, but there have been <hi>two</hi> with us, who have taken away as many <hi>Copes</hi> and <hi>guilt can leſticks,</hi> as if they had been <hi>ſuperſtitious.</hi> Sir, 'tis no wonder to me that in our times <hi>ſilver</hi> ſhould be <hi>Popery;</hi> Or that <hi>Church utenſills</hi> if they be <hi>Gold</hi> ſhould be called <hi>ſuperſtition.</hi> But certainly, Sir, 'twas a great <hi>miſinfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:114217:29"/>to ſend them to ſearch for <hi>Copes</hi> or <hi>things of value</hi> to my <hi>poor Proteſtant Chamber;</hi> where there never was a <hi>Cope,</hi> though, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, they might have found a long-difuſed <hi>Surplice,</hi> there. And as for <hi>Idolls</hi> of <hi>price,</hi> if they had <hi>ſearcht</hi> my <hi>purſe,</hi> I beleeve that all the <hi>popery,</hi> which, in theſe <hi>impoveriſhing</hi> Times, they could have found in it, <hi>caſt</hi> into the <hi>fire,</hi> like the <hi>Jewiſh Earerings,</hi> would neither have come forth a <hi>Silver Crucifix;</hi> much leſs ſo <hi>wealthy</hi> an <hi>Idoll</hi> as a <hi>Golden Calfe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sir, ſince at length I underſtand you, that by agreeing upon the <hi>true ſtate of the queſtions before we diſpute them,</hi> you mean that we ſhould <hi>agree</hi> upon the <hi>termes</hi> in which they are to be <hi>held,</hi> I am very ready to comply with you in that <hi>reaſonable</hi> particular. But to accept of any, either of your <hi>eleven Engliſh,</hi> or yout <hi>three La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine queſtions,</hi> in the <hi>terms</hi> in which you have <hi>formed</hi> them, I can by no meanes conſent. Firſt, Sir, Becauſe I find a piece of Artifice in the <hi>Web,</hi> and <hi>contrivance</hi> of them, which hath ſomething of a <hi>Trap,</hi> and <hi>Snare,</hi> and <hi>Engine</hi> in it. Which is, that by making them as <hi>Popiſh queſtions</hi> as you can, (eſpecially one of them) where you inſert the words <hi>Miſſall, Breviary,</hi> and <hi>Pontificall</hi>) words <hi>odious</hi> to the people, and part of the <hi>diſmall ſpell</hi> which for ſix yeares hath raiſed the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of <hi>diſcord</hi> to walk among us; if I ſhould hold it <hi>affirmatively</hi> under theſe <hi>termes</hi> of <hi>hatred,</hi> 'tis poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble it may beget an opinion in the minds of thoſe that know me not, that, though I have more then once profeſt my ſelfe ready to <hi>fall a ſacrifice</hi> in the defence of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> yet that this was but a <hi>diſguiſe</hi> which concealed my <hi>hypocriſie,</hi> 'till provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked I were put to defend the <hi>ſuperſtitions</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi> Sir, I know upon what <hi>leſſer ground<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> then this, <hi>ſome</hi> in our <hi>credu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous times</hi> have been unjuſtly called <hi>Papiſts.</hi> Next, Sir, if I ſhould hold them <hi>affirmatively,</hi> with their <hi>fares</hi> thus <hi>looking</hi> towards <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery,</hi> and ſhould bring them thus clothed in your <hi>termes</hi> of <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition</hi> into the <hi>Divinity Schoole,</hi> I doubt very much whether the <hi>publickneſs</hi> of the <hi>Defence</hi> may not draw an aſperſion not onely upon <hi>me,</hi> and the <hi>Moderator,</hi> (if he will vouchſafe to ſit in the <hi>Chaire</hi> whilſt we quarrell) but upon the <hi>Whole</hi> already too much <hi>defame <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity,</hi> which <hi>ſuch</hi> as <hi>you</hi> have from numerous <hi>Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits</hi> called long ſince <hi>Ropiſhly affected;</hi> But if it ſhould allow of ſuch a <hi>Diſpute,</hi> 'twould lend <hi>fuell</hi> to your <hi>calumnies,</hi> and be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangered
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:114217:29"/>to be no longer thought <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>piſh,</hi> but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> right a <hi>Papiſt.</hi> Thirdly, Sir, your <hi>firſt</hi> and laſt <hi>Queſtion</hi> (if they were purged of their <hi>odious termes</hi>) cannot <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>liquely</hi> be maintained without ſome affront to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> who by one <hi>Ordina<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> have put down the <hi>Common-prayer-book,</hi> by another <hi>Epiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>y.</hi> If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, under your <hi>termes,</hi> I ſhould <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>quely</hi> ſtand up in defence of them, you had need procure a third <hi>Ordinance,</hi> which when I have done may keep me ſafe. Yet, Sir, to aſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>e you that this is no <hi>evaſion</hi> in me to decline a <hi>diſpute,</hi> becauſe my <hi>Sermon</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>as the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of your <hi>challenge</hi> of me in the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> and of this <hi>private conference</hi> betweene <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s ſince; Since alſo you allow me the <hi>liberty</hi> of <hi>alteration,</hi> and to adde my <hi>ſtroke</hi> to the <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ill</hi> on which the <hi>queſtions</hi> to be diſputed on between us are to receive the laſt <hi>form,</hi> and <hi>ſhape,</hi> in which, with leaſt <hi>offence,</hi> and <hi>ſcan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>l,</hi> they may walk into the <hi>publique.</hi> Laſtly, ſince the three Latine <hi>Queſtions</hi> you ſent me are <hi>dree paſſages</hi> of my <hi>Sermon,</hi> but ſo <hi>corrupted</hi> from <hi>themſelves,</hi> as ſhew them to have been once p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>y <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>ſtant,</hi> but paſſing through your hands have <hi>degenerated,</hi> and <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>ed</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with a to-be-ſuſpected <hi>robe</hi> of <hi>Popery,</hi> the neareſt way I knew for us to agree upon their <hi>true ſtate,</hi> is to deale with them as the <hi>Biſhops</hi> at the <hi>Reformation</hi> dealt with the <hi>Religion</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome;</hi> that is, p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rge them from their <hi>corruptions,</hi> and reſtore them to the <hi>Primitive rule</hi> from whence they have di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſt. Which <hi>Ride,</hi> being my <hi>Sermon,</hi> (if you read it with open eyes) preſents you with your <hi>three queſtions,</hi> in this more <hi>ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e forme.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>An
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Liturgia Ang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ican<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> ideò elimin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>da ſie, qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> 
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                                 <desc>••••</desc>
                              </gap>ullas partes ab Eccleſiâ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap> na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>â <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap> eſt,</hi> Neg.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Chriſti, Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>rum<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> imagines in Reformater. Eccleſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>itè r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>eri p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ſsi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>t,</hi> Aff.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Regimen Eccleſia Anglic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>na per Epiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>s ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>t Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtianum, ex eo quòd Eccleſia Romana (qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulli ſedem Antichriſti ſtatuunt) ſic gubernatur,</hi> Neg.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Vpon theſe <hi>three Queſtions</hi> (which are but <hi>three periods</hi> of my <hi>Sermon</hi> caſt into a <hi>problematicall forme</hi>) if you approve of them, and, like a <hi>generous Adverſary,</hi> will promiſe me, that neither for <hi>ſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ing</hi> of them to you <hi>now,</hi> nor for <hi>defending</hi> them <hi>hereafter,</hi>
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:114217:30"/>I ſhall be queſtion'd, (for this I require no other <hi>ſecurity</hi> but your <hi>word</hi>) I will not faile (God aſſiſting me) to meet you in the <hi>Divinity Schoole</hi> at <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity weapons,</hi> when ever you ſhall think fit to call upon me; and to bring with you thoſe <hi>Arguments,</hi> which, you ſay, you <hi>reſerve for that place,</hi> and in your <hi>two letters</hi> have not vouchſafed to afford me, who doe daily pray (for I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to be weary of <hi>fighting</hi> with <hi>ſhades</hi>) that this <hi>unneceſſary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict</hi> may at length end in a <hi>Chriſtian peace</hi> between <hi>you</hi> the <hi>oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent,</hi> and <hi>me</hi> the <hi>defender</hi> of</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>From my Chamber this Afternoone,</hi>
                        <date>Feb. 4. 1646.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>The</hi> Sermon <hi>againſt</hi> Falſe Prophets, J. MAYNE.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>In the <hi>evening</hi> to the <hi>afternoone,</hi> in which this Letter was ſent, M. <hi>Cheynell</hi> returned an <hi>Anſwer,</hi> not ſo <hi>large,</hi> I confeſs, as I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected; but compoſed of <hi>Language,</hi> ſo <hi>complying</hi> with my <hi>deſires,</hi> that I unfainedly felt a new ſtrife within my ſelf, how, having hitherto tolerably borne his <hi>rougher aſſaults,</hi> I ſhould preſerve my ſelf from being conquer'd by his <hi>civilities.</hi> Which I confeſs, have ſuch a <hi>forcible charme</hi> upon my <hi>nature, ſoftend,</hi> and <hi>tutor'd</hi> to it by <hi>Religion;</hi> that the World cannot afford an <hi>Enemy,</hi> who ſhall raiſe ſuch a <hi>tempeſt</hi> of <hi>perſecution</hi> againſt me, but that I ſhall be ready to afford him my <hi>Imbraces,</hi> and <hi>Armes,</hi> if he will be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to be received there in a <hi>calme.</hi> I do farther confeſs, that M. <hi>Cheynell,</hi> by undertaking to ſecure me againſt the <hi>danger</hi> which might have followed a <hi>publique diſpute,</hi> hath not onely veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied my expreſſion, and ſhewne himſelfe a <hi>generous adverſary,</hi> but by that <hi>engagement</hi> of <hi>himſelf,</hi> hath made me ſee, what reaſon I have to complaine of my <hi>hard fortune,</hi> which hath left me onely the <hi>will,</hi> and not the <hi>power,</hi> to be in the like kind, as <hi>generous</hi> to <hi>Him</hi> back again. His <hi>Letter</hi> was to a <hi>ſyllable</hi> this.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:114217:30"/>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>You may be confident that the <hi>Meſſenger</hi> was not ſent by <hi>me,</hi> becauſe he return'd <hi>without</hi> you and <hi>without</hi> his <hi>fees.</hi> I never writ up one <hi>Letter</hi> to <hi>London</hi> that did in the leaſt meaſure <hi>reflect</hi> upon you; if <hi>your Sermon</hi> had not been <hi>printed,</hi> I had not <hi>ſpoke</hi> one word againſt it. I deſire to deale with you in a <hi>rationall way,</hi> and therefore I doe accept of your <hi>Academicall propoſition</hi> or <hi>challenge</hi> ſo often ſent me; and becauſe I find my <hi>prayers</hi> in ſome meaſure <hi>anſwered,</hi> and <hi>you</hi> more <hi>civill</hi> then heretofore, I ſhall deale <hi>freely</hi> with you. I doe here under my <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nd</hi> aſsure you, that if you be <hi>queſtioned</hi> for defending theſe <hi>Propoſitions</hi> in a <hi>Scholaſticall</hi> way, (you know <hi>reproaches</hi> are not <hi>Scholaſticke</hi>) in the <hi>publique Schools,</hi> I will anſwer for you; the <hi>Parliament</hi> will not queſtion you for any <hi>learned nationall debate</hi> about <hi>Prelates</hi> or the <hi>Common-Prayer-Booke,</hi> for the ſatisfaction of <hi>your ſelf</hi> and <hi>others.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I will meet you if you pleaſe, at the <hi>Doctor</hi> of the <hi>Chaire</hi> his lodgings to <hi>morrow</hi> about two of the clock in the <hi>afternoon;</hi> I doubt not but by his advice we ſhall, agree upon <hi>termes</hi> fit to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the points in <hi>Controverſie;</hi> if you like the <hi>propoſall</hi> be pleaſed to ſend your approbation of it in <hi>two lines</hi> by this <hi>bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer</hi> to<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Mert. Coll.</hi>
                        <date>
                           <hi>Feb.</hi> 4. 1646.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your friend to ſerve you,</hi> FRAN: CHEYNELL.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>To this <hi>Letter</hi> (which was the <hi>laſt</hi> I received from him) by the <hi>ſame Meſſenger</hi> that brought it, I return'd this <hi>Anſwer,</hi> which was the <hi>laſt</hi> he received from <hi>me.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I ſhall (God willing) meet you to <hi>morrow</hi> at your <hi>houre,</hi> at the <hi>Doctor</hi> of the <hi>Chaire's Lodging.</hi> Where if you be as willing to ſubmit to the <hi>termes</hi> which he ſhall think fit to put the <hi>Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions</hi> in, which we are to <hi>diſpute</hi> upon as I ſhall be, there will be no <hi>variance<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> between us there, nor ſhall we I hope, bring any with us from the <hi>Divinity School.</hi> Where Sir, you ſhall meet <hi>one</hi> who is ſo great a <hi>lover</hi> of <hi>truth,</hi> that if you can <hi>convince</hi> me for
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:114217:31"/>being all this while in an <hi>Errour,</hi> I ſhall think my ſelf indeed, a <hi>gainer</hi> by this <hi>conflict.</hi> And no longer ſtile my ſelf the <hi>defender</hi> of the <hi>Sermon</hi> againſt <hi>Falſe Prophets,</hi> but <hi>one,</hi> who for being <hi>confuted</hi> by <hi>you</hi> ought to remain</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>From my Chamber,</hi>
                        <date>
                           <hi>Feb.</hi> 4. 1646.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your</hi> Affectionate friend <hi>and</hi> Servant, J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>SPE<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> MAYNE.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Here, if any be <hi>curious</hi> to know how this <hi>laſt act</hi> of our <hi>conf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nce</hi> ended, or what <hi>Cataſtrophe</hi> did ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> up the <hi>conflict</hi> between us, which had ſo much <hi>buſie Epitaſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and <hi>expectation</hi> in it, I could wiſh Maſter <hi>Cheynell</hi> himſelf were the <hi>Hiſtorian.</hi> Nevertheleſs, none will have reaſon to thinke me <hi>partiall</hi> or <hi>unfaithfull</hi> in my <hi>Report,</hi> having not only Maſter <hi>Wilkinſon,</hi> if I deliver <hi>falſe ſtory,</hi> but the <hi>Doctor</hi> of the <hi>Chaire</hi> to <hi>diſprove,</hi> and <hi>contradict</hi> me. At whoſe <hi>lodging</hi> in <hi>Chriſt-church</hi> when we met, Firſt, with a <hi>prudence</hi> becoming the <hi>gravity</hi> of his <hi>perſon,</hi> and the <hi>Dignity</hi> of his <hi>pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e,</hi> he told us, that he could not think it fit to fit <hi>moderatour</hi> to any <hi>diſputation</hi> which was not either <hi>preformâ,</hi> and conduced to the taking of a <hi>degree,</hi> or <hi>pro T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> which is a <hi>Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ity exerciſe,</hi> at which the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity Statutes</hi> require his preſence in the <hi>chaire.</hi> Next, if we reſolved to meet in the <hi>Schools</hi> without a <hi>moderatour,</hi> his <hi>advice</hi> was, that Maſter <hi>Cheynell</hi> ſhould have his <hi>ſcribe</hi> and I <hi>mine,</hi> to write down faithfully his <hi>Arguments</hi> and my <hi>Replyes:</hi> which thus <hi>taken</hi> and <hi>compared,</hi> would not be ſo liable to the <hi>va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riations</hi> of <hi>report,</hi> as when the <hi>eares</hi> and <hi>memories</hi> of the <hi>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ers</hi> are their <hi>only Regiſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There remained but one <hi>difficulty,</hi> which was, how to make us <hi>agree</hi> upon <hi>queſtions</hi> fit to be <hi>diſputed</hi> in ſuch a <hi>publike way.</hi> M. <hi>Cheynell</hi> utterly refuſed <hi>Mine,</hi> and the <hi>Doctor</hi> of the <hi>Chaire</hi> thought it no way <hi>reaſonable,</hi> that in the <hi>dangerous attire</hi> they wore, I ſhould accept of <hi>his;</hi> eſpecially the <hi>firſt:</hi> Which upon M. <hi>Cheynells</hi> unlocking of the full <hi>extent</hi> and <hi>meaning</hi> of the <hi>termes,</hi> revealed it ſelf to be a kinde of <hi>Trojan horſe; conſecrated</hi> indeed to <hi>Pallas</hi> without, but lined with an <hi>Ambuſh</hi> of <hi>Armed enemies</hi> within. For, beſides the Words <hi>Miſſall, Breviary,</hi> and <hi>Pontificall</hi> (againſt which I before gave in my <hi>exceptions</hi>) by <hi>A pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerpta,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:114217:31"/>popido<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>, obtrufa,</hi> Maſter <hi>Cheynell</hi> ſaid, he not only meant thoſe parts of our <hi>Engliſh Lyturgie</hi> which have been borrowed from the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> but the <hi>Scotch Lyturgie</hi> too, as it was impoſed upon that <hi>Nation</hi> by the <hi>Sword.</hi> Which, though it were a miſtake in him to ſay it was <hi>impoſed</hi> by the <hi>ſword,</hi> (ſince the date of the <hi>reception</hi> of it in that <hi>Church</hi> was the year 1637. At which time the <hi>Sword</hi> of both <hi>Nations</hi> lodged peaceably in the <hi>Scab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berd</hi>) and though upon the peruſall of it ſince, E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nde it the ſame in all points with ours, but only in the contraction of the <hi>forme</hi> of the <hi>Adminiſtration</hi> of the <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rds Supper,</hi> and ſo for the matter of it as <hi>defenſible</hi> as <hi>ours,</hi> yee having been turned out of that <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> and <hi>Church</hi> as ſolemnly as it was at firſt introduced, that is, by an <hi>Act of Parliament;</hi> To whoſe birth the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Houſes</hi> concurred, for me to have diſputed <hi>publiquely</hi> for the ſecond re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of it, had been the way not only to raiſe a <hi>Northern Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi> of men againſt my ſelf, (who would, doubtleſs, have thought it a very <hi>bold piece</hi> of <hi>inſolence</hi> in me to diſallow in a <hi>publique di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute,</hi> the <hi>proceedings</hi> of a whole <hi>State</hi>) but of ſuch <hi>Northerne Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> too, whoſe <hi>zeale</hi> upon the firſt reading of that <hi>innocent Lyturgie,</hi> miſtook it for the <hi>Maſs booke,</hi> and thereupon conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted their <hi>Joynt-ſtools,</hi> upon which they ſate, into <hi>Weapons,</hi> with which they invaded the <hi>Reader,</hi> and chaced him, with his <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born Popery</hi> in his hand, out of the <hi>Church.</hi> Theſe <hi>Reaſons</hi> being layed to thoſe other, which in my laſt <hi>letter</hi> but one, produced to ſhew how ſcandalous, as well as unſafe, it would in all likely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, prove both to the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity</hi> and <hi>my ſelf,</hi> if I ſhould <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely</hi> maintaine a <hi>queſtion</hi> which carryed ſo much <hi>danger</hi> with it, I preſt M. <hi>Cheynell</hi> with the <hi>intimation</hi> which he gave me in his <hi>laſt letter,</hi> which was, to ſtand to that <hi>frame</hi> of <hi>Queſtions</hi> which the <hi>Doctor</hi> of the <hi>Chaire</hi> ſhould contrive for us. To whoſe <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering</hi> of the <hi>terme</hi> of his firſt <hi>Queſtion</hi> if he would ſubmit, I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed him to accept of his <hi>other t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> (th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in the <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Chaires</hi> opinion, the <hi>termes</hi> of his <hi>third Queſtion</hi> were ſomething hard) in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> into which he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſt them. To this his reply was, that after the Words <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pulo obtruſa,</hi> in his <hi>firſt Queſtion,</hi> he would allow me to inſert theſe two words of <hi>Miti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, ut fertur.</hi> Whereto my anſwer was, that this <hi>addition</hi> would ſo litle deſerve the name of a <hi>Mitigation,</hi> that it very much
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:114217:32"/>increaſt my burthen, and hung more <hi>weights</hi> upon me. Since here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I obliged my ſelf, not only to ſtand up for the <hi>Re-admiſsion</hi> of the <hi>Scotch Lyturgie;</hi> which could not be done without an <hi>affront</hi> offered to the <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>State</hi> that baniſht it, but for the <hi>Juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of all the <hi>unknown practices</hi> of the <hi>Prelates,</hi> who had the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivance of that <hi>Lyturgie,</hi> againſt the <hi>Siniſter reports,</hi> and <hi>Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies</hi> of the <hi>incenſed people.</hi> Who, as for ſome yeares, they have been falſely taught to thinke the <hi>Order</hi> of <hi>Biſhops Antichriſtian,</hi> ſo looking upon their <hi>perſons</hi> through the <hi>miſt</hi> caſt by ſome <hi>Falſe Prophets</hi> before their eyes, it ought to be no wonder if their <hi>beſt Actions</hi> have ſeemed <hi>Popery.</hi> The <hi>Concluſion</hi> of all was this. M. <hi>Cheynell</hi> at length, without any farther <hi>Clouds</hi> of <hi>diſcourſe,</hi> told me plainly, that to any other <hi>alterations</hi> then <hi>this</hi> he could not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; being <hi>bound up</hi> by his <hi>inſtructions</hi> to hold this <hi>Queſtion</hi> only in the <hi>latitude</hi> &amp; <hi>ſenſe,</hi> which was ſignified by the <hi>termes</hi> in which he had <hi>Arrayed</hi> it. Whereupon, the long expected <hi>ſcene</hi> between us cloſed, and the <hi>Curtaine</hi> to this <hi>Controverſie</hi> was let fall. And <hi>we,</hi> after ſome mutuall exchanges of <hi>Civility, parted,</hi> I hope like <hi>two Divines,</hi> in <hi>perfect Charity</hi> with <hi>one another.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:114217:32"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
